<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>JSP Generator</title>
		<version>0.9</version>
		<type>Technical document</type>
		<authors>
			<person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
		 </authors>
		 <abstract>This document describes the jsp generator of Cocoon.</abstract>
	</header>
	<body>
		<s1 title="JSP Generator">
			<p>The JspGenerator selects a JSPEngine component. The JSPEngine component
                          launches a JSP servlet engine of your servlet container, 
                          feeds the HttpRequest into the 
                          JSP servlet engine, and pipes the jsp response as SAX events into Cocoon.
                          The JSP page is specified by the HttpRequest.
                        </p>
                        <p>
                          This way you can continue to use your JSP pages. 
                          Your migration from JSP to XSP may be done step by step. 
                          You may specify your JSP pages either as JSP scriptlets or as JSP-XML.
                          But keep in mind that your JSP output should be valid XML.
                        </p>
			<ul>
				<li>Name : jsp</li>
				<li>Class: org.apache.cocoon.generation.JspGenerator</li>
				<li>Cacheable: ?.</li>
			</ul>
<source>
     <![CDATA[
  <map:generate type="jsp"/>
     ]]>
</source>
		</s1>
                <s1 title="JSPEngine">
                  <p>As JSP servlet engines are implemented differently, you may have to
                    select the appropriate JSPEngine component. 
                    The default is a JSPEngine working with Tomcat's JSP servlet engine Jasper.
                    You may override the cocoon.roles by your own my.roles, as described 
                    in the <link href="../../faq.html">FAQs</link>.
                  </p>
                  <p>The JSPEngine component of Tomcat's JSPEngine is implemented in JSPEngineImpl. 
                    If you want to use another JSPEngine component, you may specify it in a my.roles file.
                    The following sample specify in file WEB-INF/my.roles a JSPEngine workging with WebLogicServer:
                  </p>
<source>
  <![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<role-list>
  <role name="org.apache.cocoon.components.jsp.JSPEngine"
    shorthand="jsp-engine"
    default-class="org.apache.cocoon.components.jsp.JSPEngineImplWLS"/>
</role-list>
  ]]>
</source>
                  <p>Defining the file my.roles this way you must ensure that your 
                    cocoon.xconf refernces my.roles, like that:
                  </p>
<source>
  <![CDATA[
   ...
   <cocoon version="2.0" user-roles="WEB-INF/my.roles">
   ...
  ]]>
</source>

                  <p>Currently there are tree JSPEngine components available:
                  </p>
                  <table>
                    <tr><th>JSPEngine</th><th>ServletEngine</th></tr>
                    <tr><td>JSPEngineImpl</td><td>Tomcat, generic jsp servlet class</td></tr>
                    <tr><td>JSPEngineImplWLS</td><td>WebLogic 5.1, 6.0(?)</td></tr>
                    <tr><td>JSPEngineImplNamedDispactcherInclude</td><td>Generic JSP Servlet</td></tr>
                  </table>
                  <p>The next sections describe the settings of the JSPEngine components.
                  </p>
                  <s2 title="JSPEngineImpl">
                    <p>This JSPEngine is the default engine selected in cocoon.roles. 
                      By default it uses Tomcats' JASPER  JSP servlet engine.
                    </p>
                    <p>Running under a different JSP servlet engine, you can try to change the settings
                      in cocoon.xconf, by modifying parameter name servlet-class to your needs.
                    </p>
<source><![CDATA[
  <jsp-engine>
    <parameter name="servlet-class" value="my.servlet.MyJspServletOfMyServletEngine"/>
  </jsp-engine>
  ]]>
</source>                    
                    <p>JSPEngineImpl instances directly the JSP servlet engine class, and services
                      HttpRequest to this instance.
                    </p>
                    <p>JSPEngineImplNamedDispatcherInclude delegates the selection of a JSP servlet engine
                      instance to the servlet engine. It selects by servlet-name, and not by servlet-class.
                      This is the key differences of these two implementations.
                    </p>
                  </s2>
                  <s2 title="JSPEngineImplWLS">
                    <p>This JSPEngine is implemented especially for WebLogic 5.1. WebLogic 6.0, and WebLogic 6.1
                      may work, too. JSPEngineImplWLS finds the named request dispatch for jsp, the jsp response
                      is piped into Cocoon.
                    </p>
                    <p>The name of the JSP servlet is by default set to '*.jsp'. This is the default servlet name
                      of the JSP servlet engine under WLS. You may adopt the parameter servlet-name to your needs.
                    </p>
                    <p>If you want to specify a different JSP servlet name, you can change the settings
                      in cocoon.xconf, by modifying the parameter servlet-name.
                    </p>
<source><![CDATA[
  <jsp-engine>
    <parameter name="servlet-name" value="MyNameOfMyJspServletOfMyServletEngine"/>
  </jsp-engine>
  ]]>
</source>
                  </s2>
                  <s2 title="JSPEngineImplNamedDispatcherInclude">
                    <p>This JSPEngine is implemented like JSPEnginImplWLS without using any WebLogic classes.
                      You may try to use this JSPEngine if JSPEngineImpl does not meet your requirements.
                    </p>
                    <p>The name of the JSP servlet is by default set to '*.jsp'. This is the default servlet name
                      of the jsp servlet engine under WLS. You may adopt the parameter servlet-name to your needs.
                    </p>
                    <p>If you want to specify a different JSP servlet name, you can change the settings
                      in cocoon.xconf, by modifying the parameter servlet-name.
                    </p>
<source><![CDATA[
  <jsp-engine>
    <parameter name="servlet-name" value="MyNameOfMyJspServletOfMyServletEngine"/>
  </jsp-engine>
  ]]>
</source>
                  </s2>
                </s1>
	</body>
</document>
