<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>Stream Generator</title>
		<version>0.9</version>
		<type>Technical document</type>
		<authors>
            	<person name="Kinga Dziembowska" email="kingadziembowska@msn.com"/>
			<person name="Davanum Srinivas" email="dims@yahoo.com"/>
		 </authors>
		 <abstract>This document describes the stream generator of Cocoon.</abstract>
	</header>
	<body>
		<s1 title="Stream Generator">
	            <p>
      	      The StreamGenerator is a class that reads XML from an HttpRequest 
            	InputStream and generates SAX Events. StreamGenerator expects 
	            XML data coming as POST message. 
      	      </p>
			<ul>
				<li>Name : stream</li>
				<li>Class: org.apache.cocoon.generation.StreamGenerator</li>
				<li>Cacheable: no.</li>
			</ul>
           		<p>
         		For POST requests with mimetype of application/x-www-form-urlencoded, 
		      the xml data expects to be associated with the name specified 
            	in the sitemap parameter.
	            </p>

      	      <p>
            	For POST requests with mimetypes: text/plain, text/xml, application/xml 
	            the xml data is in the body of the POST request and its length is 
      	      specified by the value returned by getContentLength() method.
            	</p>
			<s2 title="PostInputStream">
            	<p>
	            The StreamGenerator uses helper class org.apache.cocoon.util.PostInputStream 
      	      for InputStream reading operations. At the time that Parser reads the data 
            	out of InputStream - Parser has no knowledge about the length of data to be
	            read. The only way to signal to the Parser that all data was read from the 
      	      InputStream is to control reading   operation - PostInputStream- and to 
            	return to the requestor -1 when the number of bytes read is equal to the 
	            getContentLength() value.
      	      </p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="See it in Action">
	            <p>
            	The Generator is a generic object, i.e. it can process any stream out of the 
      	      POST message there are two ways to see StreamGenerator in action:
	            </p>
            
            	<ul>
	                <li>To invoke URL http://localhost:8080/cocoon/Order</li>
      	          <li>To use telnet program to generate POST request</li>
            	</ul>
            
      	      <p>  
	            The first option is not a "pure" stream invocation, but it is quick way to 
            	observe desired effects. The result of this invocation is a form containing 
      	      the XML document embedded in the textarea of the form. Submission of this 
	            form will invoke StreamGenerator. The testarea name/value par is specified 
            	as a parameter in the sitemap definition for the StreamGenerator. The expected 
      	      result is the submitted xml document send back to the browser.
	            </p>
            
            	<p>
      	      The second or "pure" option of testing StreamGenerator "in action," requires the 
	            use of Telnet program or any other process able to generate correct POST message. 
            	The procedure is:
      	      </p>

	            <ul>
            	    <li>To invoke telnet, connect to localhost 8080 and to use content of 
      	              <link href="telnet.txt">telnet.txt</link> file as a post message. 
	                </li>
            	    <li>Here, the Copy-Paste method should be used.</li>
      	          <li>Remember to hit the enter button twice enter after the contents of the post are set in telnet.</li>
	            </ul>

            	<p>
      	      It is important because Content-len is calculated assuming two "enter" in the end of http message. 
	            Once again, the performed task results in the mirror of the original document being sent back to the requestor. 
            	</p>
            
      	      <p>
	            The "pure" stream generation can be observed using the telnet utility where you can invoke a 
            	message targeting my processing. Any other method is good (URL object connection) as 
      	      long the message is well formed.
	            </p>
<source>
     <![CDATA[
  <map:generate type="stream"/>
     ]]>
</source>
        		</s2>
		</s1>
	</body>
</document>
