<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Velocity Generator</title>
  <subtitle>in @doctitle@</subtitle>
  <version>0.9</version>
  <type>Technical document</type>
  <authors>
  <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
  </authors>
  <abstract>This document describes the Velocity template generator.</abstract>
 </header>
 <body>
  <s1 title="Velocity Generator">
  <p>
   Allows Velocity template to be used as a generator. 
   Builds upon the Velocity servlet functionality - overrides 
   the output method in order to pipe the results into SAX events.
  </p>
  
  <ul>
   <li>Name : velocity</li>
   <li>Class: org.apache.cocoon.generation.VelocityGenerator</li>
   <li>Cacheable: ????.</li>
  </ul>
  <source>
<![CDATA[
<map:generate type="velocity"/>
]]>
  </source>

  <p>
   Cocoon Generator that produces dynamic XML SAX events
   from a Velocity template file.
  </p>
 
  <s2 title="Sitemap Configuration">
   <p>
    Attributes:
   </p>
   <dl>
    <dt>usecache (optional; default: 'false')</dt> 
    <dd>
     set to 'true' to enable template caching on the 'cocoon'
     resource loader
    </dd>
   
    <dt>checkInterval (optional; default: '0')</dt>
    <dd>
     This is the number of seconds between modification checks when
     caching is turned on.  When this is an integer &gt; 0, this represents
     the number of seconds between checks to see if the template was
     modified. If the template has been modified since last check, then
     it is reloaded and reparsed. Otherwise nothing is done. When &lt;= 0,
     no modification checks will take place, and assuming that the
     property cache (above) is true, once a template is loaded and
     parsed the first time it is used, it will not be checked or
     reloaded after that until the application or servlet engine is
     restarted.
    </dd>
   </dl>
 
   <p>
   Child Elements:
   </p>
   
   <dl>
    <dt>&lt;property key="propertyKey" value="propertyValue"/&gt;
     (optional; 0..n)</dt>
    <dd>
     An additional property to pass along to the Velocity template
     engine during initialization
    </dd>
    
    <dt>&lt;resource-loader name="loaderName" class="javaClassName"/&gt;
     (optional; 0..n; children: property*)</dt>
    <dd>
     The default configuration uses the 'cocoon' resource loader
     which resolves resources via the Cocoon SourceResolver. Additional
     resource loaders can be added with this configuration
     element. Configuration properties for the resource loader can be
     specified by adding a child property element of the resource-loader
     element. The prefix '&lt;name&gt;.resource.loader.' is
     automatically added to the property name.
    </dd>
    
    <dt>&lt;export-object key="objectMapKey" name="velocityContextName"/&gt;
     (optional; 0..n)</dt>
    <dd>
     Export the object specified by <em>key</em> from the Cocoon
     object map to the Velocity context of the template.  The object can
     be accessed from the template as <em>name</em>. Be careful to use a
     valid VTL variable name.
    </dd>
   </dl>
 
   <p>
    Default Java objects exported to the Velocity context:
   </p>
   
   <dl>
    <dt>request (org.apache.cocoon.environment.Request)</dt>
    <dd>The Cocoon current request</dd>
    
    <dt>template (java.lang.String)</dt>
    <dd>The path of the template file currently being evaluated</dd>
    
    <dt>response (org.apache.cocoon.environment.Response)</dt>
    <dd>The Cocoon response associated with the current request</dd>
    
    <dt>context (org.apache.cocoon.environment.Context)</dt>
    <dd>The Cocoon context associated with the current request</dd>
    
    <dt>parameters (org.apache.avalon.framework.parameters.Parameters)</dt>
    <dd>Any parameters passed to the generator in the pipeline</dd>
   </dl>
 
   <p>
    Additional Java objects can be exported from the Cocoon object
    map to the Velocity context by adding one or more &lt;export-object
    key="objectMapKey" name="velocityContextName"/&gt; child elements
    to the generator configuration in the sitemap.
   </p>
 
  </s2>
 </s1>
 </body>
</document>
