<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>cTwIG - Cocoon Two Idiots Guide - Getting Started</title>
		<authors>
			<person name="Jeremy Aston" email="jez@pigbite.com"/>
		</authors>
	</header>

	<body>
		<s1 title="Getting Started">
			<s2 title="What is Cocoon?">
				<p>Cocoon is a framework for delivering web sites and applications that are based around XML technologies.  In addition to being able to do XML and XSL transformations, it provides it's own page logic templating system called XSP which is basically analogous to ASP, JSP, PHP, CFM etc.  Of course this is XML based as well.</p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="Why use Cocoon?">
				<p>For me it's because it really can help you develop applications that have content, layout and logic truly separated.  ASP, JSP etc are all OK but for any one (like me) who has had to develop and support multi-lingual, branded, customisable and highly dynamic sites, they just do not cut the mustard.  On top of that it is free, supported by proven open source development principles and augments other frameworks and platforms such as EJB.</p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="What do I need to make it work?">
				<p>Primarily you need a servlet engine.  This would be something like (but not exclusively) <fork href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/index.html">Tomcat</fork>, <fork href="http://www.jrun.com">JRun</fork> or <fork href="http://www.weblogic.com">Weblogic</fork>.  This is because Cocoon is a servlet and needs the servlet engine.  Most servlet engines provide a web (HTTP) server which is fine for development purposes but in most production environments you would want to sit the servlet engine on a web server such as <jump href="http://www.apache.org">Apache</jump> or IIS.  The only other usual requirement is the <jump href="http://java.sun.com">Java SDK</jump>.</p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="Where do I get it from?">
				<p>Go to <fork href="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/">http://www.apache.org/cocoon/</fork> and download it from there.  The latest distribution for any operating system can be found in the 
				<fork href="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/dist/">Cocoon distribution folder</fork>.  The distribution that you can download from there contains the Cocoon code, samples, documentation and the Java libraries that enable the Cocoon to work such as Xerces and Xalan.</p>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="What assumptions have you made?">
				<p>I assume no knowledege of Cocoon but:</p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						I do assume that the reader has a basic understanding of XML and what XSL is.  For more information and tutorials about XML/XSL please go to somewhere like <fork href="http://www.xml.org">www.xml.org</fork> or <fork href="http://www.xml.com">www.xml.com</fork>
					</li>
					<li>
						I assume that Cocoon is to be configured on a Windows NT or 2000 machine, the machine has Apache 1.3.19, Tomcat 3.2.3 and Java 1.3 running
					</li>
					<li>
						I assume a basic familiarity with the above environment
					</li>
					<li>
						I hope that if you are working on a different environment you will find the time to <link href="ctwig-contributing.html">advise</link> me of any differences in process so I can augment the documentation.  I also hope that if you find a mistake in the documentation here or you know of a better way of doing something then again you will <link href="ctwig-contributing.html">relay</link> your thoughts so I can make this resource as useful as possible.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</s2>
		</s1>
	</body>
</document>
