<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>cTwIG - Cocoon Two Idiots Guide - Resources</title>
		<authors>
			<person name="Jeremy Aston" email="jez@pigbite.com"/>
		</authors>
	</header>

	<body>
		<s1 title="Resources">
			<s2 title="Apache Cocoon Web Site">
				<p>The main place is <link href="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/"><code>http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/</code></link></p>
				<p>The C2 documentation is still (and always will be) under development. There is a lot of useful information there and it goes into a lot more detail than here.  Read it and digest it.  I am certainly doing that as I go along and quite quickly understanding more of the architecture and concepts.  I will seek to distill the main points into this site, but the main place is still the supplied documentation.</p>
				<p>You will also find the documentation in your C2 installation under {COCOON_HOME}/docs/</p>
			</s2>
			<s2 title="Apache Cocoon Users Mail List">
				<p><link href="mailto:cocoon-users-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link> to the Cocoon users mail list!  This is a great resource for asking and answering questions.  For more details, and pointers to other related lists, see the <fork href="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/mail-lists.html">documentation</fork>.</p>
				<p>You can also access an excellent, searchable, archive of the users mail list at <fork href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=xml-cocoon-users">The Aims Group</fork>.  Use this 'cos lots of things are there!  Other list archive information is available in the <fork href="http://xml.apache.org/cocoon/mail-archives.html">documentation</fork>.</p>
			</s2>
			<s2 title="Other Pages">
				<ul>
					<li>David Parry has put together a really good <fork href="http://www.suranyami.com/XSPtutorial/">XSP Tutorial</fork> which is C1.8 based but has all the basic principles you need for C2.</li>
					<li>Michael Bierenfeld directed me to a cocoon-users <fork href="http://mailman.real-time.com/pipermail/cocoon-users/2001-June/016150.html">posting</fork> that has an example taglib (logicsheet) download.  Thanks to Gary Clark for the posting and example.</li>
					<li><link href="mailto:ccambien@ivision.fr">Cyril Cambien</link> has developed more examples at his <fork href="http://chello.sourceforge.net/">CHello!</fork> (Cocoon Hello!) site.</li>
					<li><link href="mailto:lmocz@galatea.com">Lajos Moczar</link> has developed some more advanced hints and tips at his <fork href="http://www.galatea.com/flashguides/cocoon-tips-2.xml">flashguides</fork> site.</li>
				</ul>
			</s2>
			<s2 title="Credits">
				<p>Although I have constructed these pages, the basic information I have presented is thanks to users of the above mailing list, particuarly Giacomo Pati, Thomas Hofer and Michael Bierenfeld.  If you have anything to add then please do <link href="ctwig-contributing.html">contribute</link>!</p>
			</s2>
		</s1>
	</body>
</document>
