<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document> 
  <header> 
	 <title>Creating and Using Actions</title>
	 <version>0.3</version> 
	 <type>Overview document</type> 
	 <authors>
           <person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org"/> 
           <person name="Giacomo Pati" email="giacomo@apache.org"/>
           <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
           <person name="Christian Haul" email="haul@apache.org"/>
	 </authors> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
   <s1 title="The Actions"> 
   <s2 title="What is an Action?"> 
    <p>
     Apache Cocoon has a rich set of tools for publishing web documents, and while
     XSP and Generators provide alot of functionality, they still mix content
     and logic to a certain degree.  The Action was created to fill that gap.
     Because the Cocoon Sitemap provides a mechanism to select the pipeline
     at run time, we surmised that sometimes we need to adjust the pipeline
     based on runtime parameters, or even the contents of the Request parameter.
     Without the use of Actions this would make the sitemap almost
     incomprehensible. 
    </p>
    <p>
     The quick and dirty definition of an Action is "a Sitemap Component that
     manipulates runtime parameters".  Actions must be ThreadSafe, and they
     can be as complex as you need.  The Action is the proper place to handle
     form processing, and even dynamic navigation.  The Action is
     differentiated from the other sitemap components (Generator, Transformer,
     Serializer, and Reader) primarily by the fact that it does not produce
     any display data. <link href="actions.txt">actions.txt</link> contains 
     excerpts from discussions on the cocoon-dev@ mailing list regarding Actions.
    </p>
    </s2>
    <s2 title="When to use an Action instead of XSP">
     <p>
       Sometimes it is going to be quicker for you to create and handle
       logic in XSP, because Cocoon recognizes if there have been any
       changes.  However, many times it is more desirable to have a separation
       between the logic and the display.  For instance, we will use a
       multipage form.  In XSP the logic to handle the results for one
       page have to be implemented in the following page.
     </p>
     <source>
<![CDATA[
<xsp:logic>
  // handle the previous page's values.
  String name = <xsp-request:get-parameter name="name"/>;
  String password = <xsp-request:get-parameter name="password"/>;
  int userid;

  <esql:connection>
    <esql:dbpool>mypool</esql:dbpool>
    <esql:execute-query>
      <esql:query>SELECT userid FROM users
        WHERE name=<esql:parameter>name</esql:parameter>
        AND password=<esql:parameter>password</esql:parameter></esql:query>
      <esql:row-results>
        <xsp:logic>
          userid = <esql:get-int column="userid"/>
        </xsp:logic>
      </esql:row-results>
      <esql:no-results>
          <xsp-response:send-redirect url="/home"/>
      </esql:no-results>
    </esql:execute-query>
  </esql:connection>
</xsp:logic>
]]>
     </source>
     <p>
      This can get very messy, as you will invariably have alot of processing
      for things that don't even belong in the context of this page.  When
      you come back later to add features or someone else starts to maintain
      the code, you have a mess on your hands.
     </p>
     <p>
      The alternative is to use Actions.  Actions handle the pure logic
      handling portions of your site.  This allows you to create each page
      in the multipage form to handle any logic it needs to for display
      purposes only.  Your form handling information is kept separate, and
      can even predictably change the pipeline used in the sitemap.
     </p>
    </s2>
   </s1>
   <s1 title="Actions at Work">
    <p>
     Actions are components that allow two way communication between the
     Sitemap and the Action.  This section describes how to define them
     in the sitemap, and create one in real life.  We are going to write
     an Action that is our version of "Hello World".
    </p>
    <p>
     The problem domain is this: we "need" a component that will create
     an HTTP request parameter named "hello" with a value of "world", and
     it will create a sitemap parameter named "world" with a value of
     "hello".  Why?  So we can show you the two manners in which the Action
     can be used, and let your imagination go from there.
    </p>
    <s2 title="Creating the Action">
     <p>
      There is nothing like a little sample code to get your feet wet.
      We are performing something very simple here, but you can get
      more complex examples from the Cocoon code-base.
     </p>
     <source>
<![CDATA[
package test;

import org.apache.avalon.framework.parameters.Parameters;
import org.apache.cocoon.acting.AbstractAction;
import org.apache.cocoon.Constants;
import java.util.Map;
import java.util.HashMap;
import org.apache.cocoon.environment.Request;
import org.xml.sax.EntityResolver;

public class HelloWorldAction extends AbstractAction {
  public Map act (Redirector redirector, 
                  SourceResolver resolver, 
                  Map objectModel, 
                  String source, 
                  Parameters params) {
    Map sitemapParams = new HashMap();
    sitemapParams.put("world", "hello");

    Request request = (Request) objectModel.get(Constants.REQUEST_OBJECT);

    request.setAttribute("hello", "world");

    return sitemapParams;
  }
}
]]>
     </source>
    </s2>
    <s2 title="Using the Action">
     <p>
      In order to use the Action we just created, we need to define it
      in the sitemap.  After it has been defined, we must use it in the
      sitemap.
     </p>
     <s3 title="Defining the Action">
      <source>
<![CDATA[
<map:actions>
  <map:action name="hello-world" src="test.HelloWorldAction"/>
</map:actions>
]]>
      </source>
     </s3>
     <s3 title="Using the Action">
       <source>
<![CDATA[
<map:match pattern="file">
  <map:act type="hello-world">
    <map:generate type="serverpages" src="{world}_world.xsp"/>
  </map:act>
  <map:serialize/>
</map:match>
]]>
       </source>
       <p>
        Using this approach, we will generate the file named "hello_world.xsp"
        because the value of the Sitemap parameter "{world}" is "hello".  Also,
        the file "hello_world.xsp" can use the request parameter "hello" to
        produce the value "world".
       </p>
       <source>
<![CDATA[
<para>Hello <xsp-request:get-parameter name="hello"/>.</para>
]]>
       </source>
     </s3>
    </s2>
    <s2 title="Communication between Sitemap and Action">
       <p>
        As stated previously there is a two way communication between the
        Sitemap and the Action. The Sitemap can pass the parameters
        and the source attribute to the Action and the Action can return
        a Map object with new values which can be used in the sitemap.
       </p>
       <source>
<![CDATA[
<map:match pattern="file">
  <map:act type="hello-world" src="optional src">
    <!-- and here come the parameters: -->
    <map:parameter name="first parameter" value="test"/>

    <map:generate type="serverpages" src="{world}_world.xsp"/>
  </map:act>
  <map:serialize/>
</map:match>
]]>
       </source>
       <p>This Map object does not replace the previous Map object put
       is stacked on top of it. The other Map objects are still
       accessible through a path expression.</p>
<source>
<![CDATA[
<map:match pattern="*">
  <map:act type="validate-session">
    <map:generate type="serverpages" src="{../1}.xsp"/>
  </map:act>
  <map:serialize/>
</map:match>
]]>
</source>
       <p>The above example shows how to access the next to last map
       by prefixing the key with "<code>../</code>"</p>
    </s2>
    <s2 title="Flow Control">
       <p>
        In addition to delivering values to the Sitemap, the Action can
        also control the flow. If the action returns <code>null</code>
        all statements inside the <code>map:act</code> element are
        not executed. So, if in the example above the hello world action
        would return <code>null</code> the server page generator
        would not be activated.
       </p>
       <p> In other words: The statements within the
       <code>map:act</code> element are <em>only</em> executed if the
       action returns at least an empty Map object.</p>
    </s2>
   </s1>
   <s1 title="Action Sets">
    <p>
     You can arrange actions in an action set. The sitemap calls the
     act method of those actions in the sequence they are defined in the 
     action set. It is possible to signal to the sitemap to
     call an action only if the Environments getAction method returns
     a String identical to the value supplied with an action attribute.
     In the current implementation of the HttpEnvironment the value 
     returned by the getAction method is determined by a http parameter 
     called "cocoon-action".</p>
     <p> Above we have seen that a successfully executed action
     returns a Map object that can be used to communicate with the
     sitemap. In case of an action set this is similar. With action
     sets all returned Map objects are merged into a single Map. Of
     course a Map can contain only one value per key so that if
     multiple actions within an action set use the same key to
     communicate to the sitemap, only the last one "survives".</p>
     <p>
      So far let's have a look at at possible action set definition:
    </p>
    <source>
<![CDATA[
<map:action-sets>
  <map:action-set name="shop-actions">
    <map:act type="session-invalidator" action="logoff"/>
    <map:act type="session-validator"/>
    <map:act type="cart-add" action="addItem"/>
    <map:act type="cart-remove" action="removeItem"/>
    <map:act type="cart-remove-all" action="removeAll"/>
    <map:act type="cart-update" action="updateQty"/>
    <map:act type="order-add" action="addOrder"/>
    <map:act type="order-verify" action="verifyOrder"/>
    <map:act type="screen-navigator" src="{1}"/>
  </map:action-set>
</map:action-sets>
]]>
    </source>
    <p>And this is a possible pipeline snipped which uses this action set:</p>
    <source>
<![CDATA[
   <map:match pattern="*">
    <map:act set="shop-actions">     <--- HERE -->
     <map:generate  type="serverpages" src="docs/xsp/{nextpage}.xsp"/>
     <map:transform src="stylesheets/page2html.xsl"/>
     <map:serialize type="html"/>
    </map:act>
   </map:match>
]]>
    </source>
    <p>
Let me explain some of those actions in the set first. 
    </p>
    <p>
The "session-invalidator" action gets called when an action of logoff is
requested (ie. a html submit button named "cocoon-action" with the 
value "logoff" was pressed). 
    </p>
    <p>
The "session-validator" action is called on every request. It assures that
an http session is created and available to the other sitemap components
(other actions and xsp pages selected for resource production).
    </p>
    <p>
The other actions in the set with an action attribute do specific things
like adding an item to the cart, removing one or all items from the cart
etc. They are called depending on the value returned by the getAction method
of the HttpEnvironment object passed to the sitemap engine as described 
above ( see "session-invalidator" action).
    </p>
    <p>
The screen-navigation action is always called because it has knowledge 
about the flow/sequence of pages and it knows how/where the preceding actions
stores their execution status (ie. as an request attribute). Depending on those
stati the screen-navigation action sets up a Map with an element called 
"nextpage" with the value of the page that produces the next "view".
    </p>
    <p>
However, one is not limited to specify distinct values at the action attribute.
It is possible and I think useful to mark several actions with the same
action attribute value which will then be called in sequence. This allows you
to choose a granularity of your actions at will.
    </p>
   </s1>
  </body>
</document>
