<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
	 <title>Caching</title>
	 <version>0.9</version>
	 <type>Technical document</type>
	 <authors><person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
	 </authors>
	 <abstract>This document explains the basic caching algorithm of Apache Cocoon.</abstract>
  </header>
  <body>
	 <s1 title="Goal">
		<p>This document explains the basic caching algorithm of Apache Cocoon.</p>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="Overview">
		<p>The caching algorithm of Cocoon has a very flexible and powerful design.
               The algorithms and components used are not hardcoded into the core of 
               Cocoon. They can be configured using Avalon components.</p>
            <p>This document describes the components available for caching,
               how they can be configured and how to implement your own cacheable components.
            </p>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="Caching of event pipelines">
		<p>The algorithm used for caching depends on the event pipeline configured. 
               For more information about configuration see the chapter below.</p>
            <p>The following subchapters describe the available caching algorithms.</p>
		<s2 title="The CachingEventPipeline">
			<p>The CachingEventPipelineuses a very easy but effective approach
                     to cache the event pipelines of a request: The pipeline process
                     is cached up to the most possible point.</p>
                  <p>Each sitemap component (generator or transformer) which might be
                     cacheable must implement the Cacheable interface. When the
                     event pipeline is processed each sitemap component starting with
                     the generator is asked if it implements this interface. This
                     test stops either when the first component does not implement
                     the Cacheable interface or when the first cacheable component is
                     currently not cacheable for any reasons (more about this in a moment).</p>
			<p>The Cacheable interface declares a method <code>generateKey()</code>
                     which must produce a unique key for this sitemap component inside
                     the component space. For example the FileGenerator generates a hash
                     of the source argument (the xml document read). All parameters/values
                     which are used for the processing of the request by the generator must
                     be used for this key. If, e.g. the request parameters are used by
                     the component, it must build a key with respect to the current request
                     parameters.</p>
			<p>If for any reason the sitemap component detects that the current request
                     is not cacheable it can simply return <code>0</code> as the key. This has
                     the same effect as not declaring the Cacheable interface.</p>
			<p>Now after the key is build for this particular request, it is looked up
                     in the cache if it exists. If not, the new request is generated and cached
                     for further requests.</p>
                  <p>If a cached response is found for the key, the caching algorithm checks
                     if this response is still valid. For this check each cacheable component
                     returns a validity object when the method <code>generateValidity</code>
                     is invoked. (If a cacheable component returns <code>null</code> it
                     is temporarily not cacheable, like returning <code>0</code> for the key.)</p>
                  <p>A <code>CacheValidity</code> object contains all information the component
                     needs to verify if the cached content is still valid. For example the
                     file generator stores the last modification date of the xml document parsed
                     in the validity object.</p>
                  <p>When a response is cached all validity objects are stored together with
                     the cached response in the cache. Actually the <code>CachedEventObject</code>
                     is stored which encapsulates all this information.</p>
                  <p>When a new response is generated and the key is build, the caching
                     algorithm also collects all uptodate cache validity objects. So if the
                     cached response is found in the cache these validity objects are compared.
                     If they are valid (or equal) the cached response is used and feed into
                     the pipeline. If they are not valid any more the cached response is removed
                     from the cache, the new response is generated and then stored together with
                     the new validity objects in the cache.</p>
			<s3 title="Examples">
				<p>If you have the following pipeline:</p>
                        <p>Generator[type=file|src=a.xml] -> Transformer[type="xslt"|src=a.xsl] -> Serializer</p>
				<p>The file generator is cacheable and generates a key which hashes the src 
         			   (or the filename) to build the key. The cache
                           validity object uses the last modification date of the xml file.</p>
				<p>The xslt transformer is cacheable and generates a key which hashes
                           the filename to build the unique key. The cache validity object
                           uses the last modification date of the xml file.</p>
				<p>Both keys are used to build a unique key for this pipeline,
                           the first time it is invoked its response is cached. The second time
                           this pipeline is called, the cached content is get from the cache.
                           If it is still valid, the cached content is directly feed into
                           the serializer.</p>
				<p>Only part of the following pipeline is cached:</p>
                        <p>Generator[type=file|src=a.xml] -> Transformer[type="xslt"|src=a.xsl] -> Transformer[type=sql] -> Transformer[type="xslt"|src=b.xsl] -> Serializer</p>
				<p>The file generator is cacheable and generates a key which hashes the src 
         			   (or the filename) to build the key. The cache
                           validity object uses the last modification date of the xml file.</p>
				<p>The xslt transformer is cacheable and generates a key which hashes
                           the filename to build the unique key. The cache validity object
                           uses the last modification date of the xml file.</p>
				<p>The sql transformer is not cacheable, so the caching algorithm stops
 				   at this point although the last transformer is cacheable.</p>
				<p>So the cached response is absolutely the same as in the first example
                           and therefore the unique key build from the two keys (from the
                           generator and the first transformer) is the same as in the first example.
				   The only difference is when the cached response is used. It is not
                           feed into the serializer but into the sql transformer.</p>
			</s3>
		</s2>
		<s2 title="The XMLSerializer/XMLDeserializer">
			<p>The caching of the sax events is implemented by two Avalon components: 
                     The XMLSerializer and the XMLDeserializer. The XMLSerializer gets
                     sax events and creates an object which is used by the XMLDeserializer
                     to recreate these sax events.</p>
			<s3 title="org.apache.cocoon.components.sax.XMLByteStreamCompiler">
			      <p>The <code>XMLByteStreamCompiler</code>compiles sax events into a byte stream.</p>
			</s3>
			<s3 title="org.apache.cocoon.components.sax.XMLByteStreamInterpreter">
				<p>The <code>XMLByteStreamInterpreter</code> is the counterpart of the 
				   <code>XMLByteStreamCompiler</code>. It interprets the byte
                           stream and creates sax events.</p>
			</s3>
		</s2>
            <s2 title="The Event Cache">
			<p>The event cache contains the cached event pipelines (or the
                     <code>CachedEventObject</code>). It is another Avalon component which 
                     can be configured. It is possible to use the memory as a cache, 
                     or the file system or a combination of both etc. This depends on 
                     the used/configured event cache.
                  </p>
		</s2>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="Caching of stream pipelines">
		<p>The algorithm used for caching depends on the configured stream pipeline. 
               For more information about configuration see the chapter below.</p>
            <p>The following subchapters describe the available caching algorithms.</p>
		<s2 title="The CachingStreamPipeline">
			<p>The <code>CachingStreamPipeline</code> uses a very easy but effective approach
                     to cache the stream pipelines of a request: If the underlying
                     event stream and the serializer is cacheable the request is cached.
                     If a reader is used instead and it is cacheable, the response
                     is cached, too.</p>
			<p>An event pipeline is cacheable if it implements the <code>CacheableEventPipeline</code>
                     interface. It generates a unique key for this event pipeline
                     and delivers the cache validity objects. The current CachingEventPipeline
                     for example is cacheable if all sitemap components are cacheable,
                     this includes the generator and all transformers. The generated key
                     is build upon the returned keys of the sitemap components and
                     the validity objects are the collected validity objects from the 
                     sitemap components. If the response is cacheable the <code>CachingStreamPipeline</code>
                     informs the <code>CacheableEventPipeline</code> by calling the
                     method <code>setStreamPipelineCaches</code>. The event pipeline
                     can now decide if it also wants to cache the response thus nearly
                     duplicating the cached contents.</p>
			<p>A serializer is cacheable if it implements the <code>Cacheable</code> interface.
                     In the case of a serializer the implementation is in most cases very
                     simple as a serializer often has no other input than the sax events. In
                     this case the key for this serializer can be a simple constant value
                     and the validity object is the <code>NOPCacheValidity</code>.</p>
                  <p>A reader is cacheable if it implements the <code>Cacheable</code> 
                     interface.</p>
                  <p>When a response is cached all validity objects are stored together with
                     the cached response, which is actually a byte array, in the cache. 
                     The <code>CachedStreamObject</code> encapsulates all this information.</p>
                  <p>When a new response is generated and the key is build, the caching
                     algorithm collects all uptodate cache validity objects. So if the
                     cached response is found in the cache these validity objects are compared.
                     If they are valid (or equal) the cached response is used and directly
                     returned. If they are not valid any more the cached response is removed
                     from the cache, the new response is generated and then stored together with
                     the new validity objects in the cache.</p>
		</s2>
            <s2 title="The Stream Cache">
			<p>The stream cache contains the cached stream pipelines (or the
                     <code>CachedStreamObject</code>). It is another
                     Avalon component which can be configured. It is possible to use
                     the memory as a cache, or the file system or a combination of both
                     etc. This depends on the used/configured event cache.
                  </p>
		</s2>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="Configuration">
		<p>The caching of Cocoon can be completely configured by different Avalon
               components. This chapter describes which roles must/can be changed
               to tune up your Cocoon system.</p>
		<s2 title="The Stream and the Event Pipeline">
			<p>The stream and the event pipeline are represented by two Avalon 
                     components which can be configured in the cocoon.xconf:</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
<event-pipeline
    class="org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline.CachingEventPipeline"/>

<stream-pipeline
    class="org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline.CachingStreamPipeline"/>
     ]]>
    </source> 
			<p>If you want to completely turn off caching, use the following
                     definitions:</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
<event-pipeline
    class="org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline.NonCachingEventPipeline"/>

<stream-pipeline
    class="org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline.NonCachingStreamPipeline"/>
     ]]>
    </source> 		</s2>
			<s2 title="The XMLSerializer/XMLDeserializer">
			<p>The XMLSerializer and XMLDeserialzer are two Avalon components which
			   can be configured in the cocoon.xconf:</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
<xml-serializer
    class="org.apache.cocoon.components.sax.XMLByteStreamCompiler"/>

<xml-deserializer
    class="org.apache.cocoon.components.sax.XMLByteStreamInterpreter"/>
     ]]>
    </source> 
			<p>You must assure that the correct (or matching) deserializer is 
                     configured for the serializer.</p>
		</s2>
		<s2 title="Event Cache and Stream Cache">
			<p>The EventCache and the StreamCache are two Avalon components which
			   can be configured in the cocoon.xconf:</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
<event-cache class="org.apache.cocoon.caching.EventMemoryCache"/>

<stream-cache class="org.apache.cocoon.caching.StreamMemoryCache"/>
     ]]>
    </source>
		</s2>
 	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="Java APIs">
		<p>For more information on the java apis refer directly to the
               javadocs of Cocoon.</p>
            <p>The most important packages are:</p>
		<ol>
			<li><code>org.apache.cocoon.caching</code>: This package declares all interfaces for caching.</li>
			<li><code>org.apache.cocoon.components.pipeline</code>: The interfaces and implementations of the pipelines.</li>
		</ol>
  	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="Utility classes">
		<s2 title="Hash Util">
			<p>The <code>org.apache.cocoon.util.HashUtil</code> class provides some
                     methods for the <link href="http://www.serve.net/buz/hash.adt/java.000.html">BuzHash algorithm by Robert Uzgalis</link>.</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
       package org.apache.cocoon.util;

       public class HashUtil {

         public static long hash(String arg);
         public static long hash(StringBuffer arg);
       }
     ]]>
    </source>
		</s2>
  	 </s1>
  </body>
</document>
