<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Entity resolution with catalogs</title>
  <subtitle>Resolve external entities to local or other resources</subtitle>
  <version>1.5</version> 
  <type>Technical document</type> 
  <authors>
   <person name="David Crossley" email="crossley@indexgeo.com.au"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
 <s1 title="Introduction">
  <p>
   Apache Cocoon has the capability to utilise an entity resolution mechanism. 
   External entities (e.g. Document Type Definitions (DTDs), character entity
   sets, XML sub-documents) are resources that are declared by an XML instance
   document - they exist as separate objects. An entity catalog assists with
   entity management and the resolution of entities to accessible resources.
   It also reduces the necessity for expensive and failure-prone network
   retrieval of the required resources.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="Overview">
  <p>
   "Entities" represent the physical structure of an XML instance document,
   whereas "elements" represent the logical structure. The complete entity
   structure of the document defines which pieces need to be incorporated, so
   as to build the final document. Those entities are objects from some
   accessible place, e.g. local file system, local network, remote network,
   generated from a database. Example entities are: DTDs, XML sub-documents,
   sets of character entities to represent symbols and other glyphs, image
   files.
  </p>

  <p>
   So how are you going to define the accessible location of all those pieces?
   How will you ensure that those resources are reliably available? Entity
   resolution catalogs to the rescue. These are simple standards-based
   plain-text files to map public identifiers and system identifiers to local
   or other resources.
  </p>

  <p>
   Do you wonder why we cannot use the sitemap to resolve these resources?
   This is because the resolution of all entities that compose the XML
   document is under the direct control of the guts of the parser and the XML
   structure. The parser has no choice - it must incorporate all of the defined    pieces. If it cannot retrieve them, then it is broken and reports an error.
  </p>

  <p>
   With the powerful catalog support there are no such problems. This document
   provides the following sections to explain Cocoon capability for
   resolving entities ...
  </p>

  <ul>
   <li>
    <link href="#background">Background</link>
    - explains the need, explains some terminology, describes the solution
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#demo1">Demonstration #1</link>
     - explains a remote resource and how it gets resolved
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#cat">Catalogs overview</link>
     - briefly explains how catalogs resolve entity declarations
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#demo2">Demonstration #2</link>
     - explains more detailed need and use of catalogs
     and shows catalogs in action
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#default">Default configuration</link>
     - explains the default automated configuration
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#config">Local configuration</link>
     - explains how to extend the default configuration for your local
     system requirements and provides an example
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#imp">Implementation notes</link>
     - describes how support for catalogs is added to Cocoon
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#dev">Development notes</link>
     - some minor issues need to be addressed
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#notes">Other notes</link>
     - assorted dot-points
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#summ">Summary</link>
   </li>
   <li>
    <link href="#info">Further information</link>
     - links to some useful resources
   </li>
  </ul>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="background"/>
 <s1 title="Background">
  <p>
   The following article eloquently describes the need for all parsers and
   XML frameworks to be capable of utilising entity resolvers.
   "<link href="http://www.arbortext.com/Think_Tank/XML_Resources/Issue_Three/issue_three.html">If You Can Name It, You Can Claim It!</link>"
   by Norman Walsh. Please read that document, then return here to apply
   entity catalogs to Cocoon.
  </p>

  <p>
   (Note: That article (and Java classes) evolved to become the Sun
   <code>resolver.zip</code> Java package that has been added to Cocoon
   - a more recent version of the article is available with the Sun download
   (see below). The API javadocs for <code>resolver</code> have further information.
   However, you do not need to know the gory details to understand catalogs
   and configure them.)
  </p>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="demo1"/>
 <s1 title="Demonstration #1">
  <p>
   This snippet from an XML instance shows the Document Type Declaration.
   Notice that it declares its ruleset, the Document Type Definition (DTD),
   as an external entity. Notice also that the resource is network-based.
  </p>

<source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V4.1.2.5//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/4.1.2.5/sdocbook.dtd"
<article>
 ... content goes here
</article>
]]></source>

  <p>
   Now consider what will happen when Cocoon tries to process this XML
   instance. Whether you have set validation=yes or not, the parser will
   still want to resolve all of the entities that are required by the XML
   instance (i.e. the DTD and any other entities that the DTD might declare).
   So it will happily trundle across the network to get them. It will do this
   every time that the document is processed. This is obviously a needless
   overhead. Worse still, what happens if that host is down or the network is
   congested. Additionally, if your Cocoon is an off-line server then it is
   always broken because it cannot retrieve the network-based resources.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="cat"/>
 <s1 title="Catalogs overview">
  <p>
   As the Walsh document explained, the secrets to entity resolution are the
   public identifiers, system identifiers, and the catalog to map between them.
   Here we provide an overview and show an example catalog which we will then
   use with the <link href="#demo2">Demonstration #2</link> below.
  </p>

  <s2 title="External entity declarations">
   <p>
    To define an external entity in an XML instance document, you must 
    provide an external declaration consisting of at least a
    <strong>system identifier</strong> and optionally a 
    <strong>public identifier</strong>. The system identifier defines the
    physical location of the external entity. The public identifier is a
    unique symbolic name that can be used to map to a certain physical location.
    Note that if you provide both a public and a system identifier, then the
    public identifier is listed first and the system identifier is not 
    preceded by the keyword <code>SYSTEM</code>.
    Here are four separate examples ...
   </p>

<source><![CDATA[
<!ENTITY pic SYSTEM "images/pic.gif" NDATA gif>
<!ENTITY % ISOnum PUBLIC
  "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Numeric and Special Graphic//EN//XML" "ISOnum.pen">
<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "dtd/document-v10.dtd">
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1/docbookx.dtd">
]]></source>

  <p>
   (In your XML instance document, or DTD, you would include those entities
   like this ... <code>%ISOnum;</code>)
  </p>

  <p>
   None of those system identifiers looks reliable or easily managed.
   Use a catalog to make them so.
  </p>
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Simple example catalog">
   <p>
    The <code>catalog</code> maps public identifiers to their corresponding
    physical locations. The catalog entries in an OASIS catalog are a simple
    whitespace-delimited format.
    (The <link href="#info">specification</link> fully defines the format.) 
    There about a dozen different types of catalog entry - two important
    ones are:
   </p>

   <ul>
    <li><strong>PUBLIC</strong> <code>publicId systemId</code>
     <br/>- maps the public identifier <code>publicId</code> to the system
     identifier <code>systemId</code>
    </li>
    <li><strong>SYSTEM</strong> <code>systemId otherSystemId</code>
     <br/>- maps the system identifier <code>systemId</code> to the alternate
     system identifier <code>otherSystemId</code>
    </li>
   </ul>

<source><![CDATA[
-- this is the default OASIS catalog for Apache Cocoon --

OVERRIDE YES

-- ISO public identifiers for sets of character entities --
PUBLIC "ISO 8879-1986//ENTITIES Added Latin 1//EN//XML"
       "ISOlat1.pen"
PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Added Latin 1//EN//XML"
       "ISOlat1.pen"
PUBLIC "ISO 9573-15:1993//ENTITIES Greek Letters//EN//XML"
       "ISOgrk1.pen"
PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Publishing//EN//XML"
       "ISOpub.pen"
PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES General Technical//EN//XML"
       "ISOtech.pen"
PUBLIC "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Numeric and Special Graphic//EN//XML"
       "ISOnum.pen"

-- these entries are used for the catalog-demo sample application --
OVERRIDE NO
PUBLIC "-//Arbortext//TEXT Test Override//EN"
       "catalog-demo/override.xml"
OVERRIDE YES
PUBLIC "-//Arbortext//TEXT Test Public Identifier//EN"
       "catalog-demo/testpub.xml"
SYSTEM "urn:x-arbortext:test-system-identifier"
       "catalog-demo/testsys.xml"
PUBLIC "-//Indexgeo//DTD Catalog Demo v1.0//EN"
       "catalog-demo/catalog-demo-v10.dtd"
-- end of entries for the catalog-demo sample application --
]]></source>

   <p>
    System identifiers can use full pathnames, filenames, relative pathnames,
    or URLs - in fact, any method that will define and deliver the actual
    physical entity. If it is just a filename or a relative pathname, then the 
    Catalog Resolver will look for the resource relative to the location of
    the catalog.
   </p>

   <p>
    When the parser needs to load a declared entity, then it first consults
    the Catalog Resolver to get a possible mapping to an alternate system
    identifier. If there is no mapping for an identifier in the catalogs
    (or in any sub-ordinate catalogs), then Cocoon will carry on to
    retrieve the resource using the original declared system identifier.
   </p>
  </s2>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="demo2"/>
 <s1 title="Demonstration #2">

  <p>
   See catalogs in action with the 
   <link href="../../overview.html#samples">Cocoon Samples</link> ...
   <link href="samples/catalog-demo">catalog-demo</link>. The demonstration
   intends to be self-documenting. The top-level XML instance describes its
   role, and each included external entity reports how it came into being.
   This example builds upon the example provided by the Walsh article.
   (Tip: To see the error message that would result from not using a catalog,
   simply rename the default <code>catalog</code> file before starting
   Cocoon.)
  </p>

<note>TODO: ensure that the link to samples works OK in the various documentation situations (i.e. static site, local docs build)</note>

  <p>Here is the source for the top-level XML instance document
   <code>test.xml</code> ...
  </p>

<source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE catalog-demo PUBLIC "-//Indexgeo//DTD Catalog Demo v1.0//EN"
  "http://www.indexgeo.com.au/dtd/catalog-demo-v10.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY testpub PUBLIC "-//Arbortext//TEXT Test Public Identifier//EN"
   "bogus-system-identifier.xml">
 <!ENTITY testsys SYSTEM "urn:x-arbortext:test-system-identifier">
 <!ENTITY testovr PUBLIC "-//Arbortext//TEXT Test Override//EN"
   "testovr.xml">
 <!ENTITY % ISOnum PUBLIC
   "ISO 8879:1986//ENTITIES Numeric and Special Graphic//EN//XML"
   "ISOnum.pen">
 %ISOnum;
 <!ENTITY note "Note:">
]>

<catalog-demo>
 <section>
  <para>This sample application demonstrates the use of catalogs for
   entity resolution. &note; see the Apache Cocoon documentation
   <link href="/cocoon/documents/catalog.html">Entity resolution with
   catalogs</link> for the full background and explanation, and the XML
   source of this document (test.xml).
  </para>

  <para>This top-level XML instance document is test.xml - it declares
   three other XML sub-documents as external entities and then includes
   them in the sections below. The real system identifiers will be looked
   up in the catalog, to resolve the actual location of the resource.
  </para>

  <para>The Document Type Definition (DTD) is declared using both a public
   identifier and a system identifier. The system identifier for the DTD is
   a network-based resource (which is deliberately non-existent). However,
   the catalog overrides that remote DTD to instead use a copy from the
   local filesystem at the location defined by the catalog entry. Note that
   it is via the use of a public identifier that we gain this power.
  </para>

  <para>The internal DTD subset of the top-level document instance goes on
   to declare the three external sub-document entities using various means.
   It also declares and includes the ISOnum set of character entities,
   so that we can use entities like &amp;frac12; (to represent &frac12;).
   Finally the internal DTD subset declares an internal general entity
   for &quot;note&quot;.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section>
  <para>testpub ... this entity is declared with a PUBLIC identifier and a
   bogus system identifier (which will be overridden by the catalog)
  </para>
  &testpub;
 </section>

 <section>
  <para>testsys ... this entity is declared with a SYSTEM identifier
   (which will be resolved by the catalog)
  </para>
  &testsys;
 </section>

 <section>
  <para>testovr ... is declared with a PUBLIC identifier and a system
   identifier (the catalog is set to not override this one, so the
   declared system identifier is used)
  </para>
  &testovr;
 </section>

</catalog-demo>
]]></source>

  <p>
   Here is the source for one of the included sub-document external entities
   <code>testpub.xml</code> ...
  </p>

<source><![CDATA[
<para>&note; This paragraph is automatically included from the
 testpub.xml external file.
 The entity declaration deliberately used a non-existent file
 as the system identifier. The catalog then used the declared
 public identifer to resolve to a specific location on the local
 filesystem.
</para>
]]></source>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="default"/>
 <s1 title="Default configuration">
  <p>
   A default catalog and some base entities (e.g. ISO*.pen character
   entity sets) are included in the Cocoon distribution at 
   <code>webapps/cocoon/resources/entities/</code>
   - the default catalog is automatically loaded when Cocoon starts.
  </p>

  <p>
   If you suspect problems, then you can raise the level of the
   <code>verbosity</code> property (to 2 or 3) and watch the messages going
   to standard output when Cocoon starts and operates. You would also do
   this to detect any misconfiguration of your own catalogs.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="config"/>
 <s1 title="Local configuration">
   <p>You can extend the default configuration to include local catalogs
    for site-specific requirements. This is achieved via various means.
   </p>

  <s2 title="Using cocoon.xconf">
   <p>Parameters (properties) for the resolver component can be specified
    in the <code>cocoon.xconf</code> configuration file.
    See the detailed internal notes - here is a precis.
   </p>

   <ul>
    <li><code>catalog</code>
     ... The main catalog file. Its path name is relative to the
     Cocoon context directory.
    </li>
    <li><code>local-catalog</code>
     ... The full filesystem pathname to a single local catalog file.
    </li>
    <li><code>verbosity</code>
     ... The level of messages from the resolver
     (loading catalogs, identifier resolution, etc.).
     It value may range from 0 (no messages), to 10 detailed log messages.
    </li>
   </ul>
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Using CatalogManager.properties">
   <p>An annotated <code>CatalogManager.properties</code> file is included
    with the distribution - modify it to suit your needs. You can add your
    own local catalogs using the <code>catalogs</code> property.
    (See the notes inside the properties file).
   </p>

   <p>
    The build process will automatically copy the properties file from
<code>$COCOON_HOME/webapp/resources/entities/CatalogManager.properties</code>
    to
<code>$TOMCAT_HOME/webapps/cocoon/WEB-INF/classes/CatalogManager.properties</code>
    thereby making it available to the Java classpath.
   </p>

   <p>
    If you see an error message going to STDOUT when Cocoon starts 
    (<code>Cannot find CatalogManager.properties</code>) then this means that
    the properties file is not available to the Java classpath. Note that this
    does not mean that entity resolution is disabled, rather that no local
    configuration is being effected. Therefore no local catalogs will be
    loaded and no entity resolution messages will be received (verbosity
    level is zero by default).
   </p>

   <p>
    That may truly be the intention, and not just a configuration mistake.
    You can still use <code>cocoon.xconf</code> to effect your local
    configuration.
   </p>
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Resolver directives inside your catalog file">
   <p>
    The actual "catalog" files have a powerful set of directives. 
    For example, the <strong>CATALOG</strong> directive facilitates the
    inclusion of a sub-ordinate catalog. The list of resources below will
    lead to <link href="#info">further information</link> about catalog usage.
   </p>
  </s2>

  <s2 title="Example local configuration for Simplified DocBook">
  <p>
   We use the Simplified DocBook XML DTD for some of our documentation.
   Here are the few steps that we followed to configure Cocoon to be able
   to process our XML instances.
  </p>

  <ul>
   <li>
    downloaded a recent copy of the Simplified DocBook DTD distribution
    and unpacked it at
    <code>/usr/local/sgml/docbook/simple/</code>
   </li>
   <li>
    created a catalog file at 
    <code>/usr/local/sgml/docbook/simple/sdocbook.cat</code>
    with a single entry for the Simplified DocBook XML DTD
   </li>
   <li>
    added the parameter (<code>local-catalog</code>) to the
    <code>cocoon.xconf</code>
    (using the full pathname to the <code>sdocbook.cat</code> catalog).
   </li>
  </ul>

<source><![CDATA[
-- Catalog file (sdocbook.cat) for Simplified DocBook --
-- See www.oasis-open.org/docbook/ --

-- Driver file for the Simplified DocBook XML DTD --
PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V4.1.2.5//EN"
       "sdocbook.dtd"

-- end of catalog file for Simplified DocBook --
]]></source>

  <p>
   We could similarly configure Cocoon for the full DocBook XML DTD and
   related entities. In fact, the DocBook distribution already contains a
   catalog file. We need only append the pathname to our <code>catalogs</code>
   property.
  </p>

  <p>
   There are a few important starting points for 
   <link href="#info">further information</link> about using and configuring
   the DocBook DTDs.
  </p>

  </s2>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="imp"/>
 <s1 title="Implementation notes">
  <p>
   The SAX <code>Parser</code> interface provides an <code>entityResolver</code>
   hook to allow an application to resolve the external entities. The Sun
   Microsystems Java code "<code>com.sun.resolver</code>" provides a
   <strong>Catalog Resolver</strong>. This is incorporated into Cocoon via
   <code>org.apache.cocoon.components.resolver</code> 
  </p>

  <p>
   <link href="#default">Default configuration</link> is achieved via
   <code>org.apache.cocoon.components.resolver.ResolverImpl.java</code> 
   which initialises the catalog resolver and loads a default system catalog.
   The <code>ResolverImpl.java</code> enables <link href="#config">local
   configuration</link> by applying properties from the
   <code>CatalogManager.properties</code> file and then further configuration
   from <code>cocoon.xconf</code> parameters.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="dev"/>
 <s1 title="Development notes">

  <p>
   Assistance is required with the following outstanding development issues ...
  </p>

  <ul>
   <li>5) ? What other default entities need to be shipped with the Cocoon
    distribution? We already have some character entity sets (ISO*.pen).
    Probably also need the documentation DTDs.
   </li>
   <li>7)
   </li>
  </ul>

  <p>
   Some core Cocoon FIXME notes can be now be addressed by catalog ...
  </p>

  <ul>
   <li>the first FIXME note in document-1.0.dtd re how to include
    entities without hardwiring
   </li>
   <li>there are various other hard-coded pathnames to XML resources
   </li>
   <li>this needs further investigation after basic catalog support is
    fully settled
   </li>
  </ul>

 </s1>

 <anchor id="notes"/>
 <s1 title="Other notes">

  <ul>
   <li>OASIS Catalogs (TR 9401:1995 Entity Management) are plain-text files 
    with a simple delimited format. There is also a new standard being
    developed for XML Catalogs, using an xml-based structured plain-text file
    (gee :-). Links to both standards are provided below. Both catalog formats
    can be currently used with this entity resolver. However, the latter 
    standard is not yet settled. OASIS TR9401 catalogs will suffice.
   </li>
   <li>There has been a recent flood of XML tools - unfortunately, many do not
    implement entity resolution (other than by brute-force retrieval), so
    those tools are crippled and cannot be used for serious XML processing.
    Please ensure that you choose 
    <link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/cover/">proper XML tools</link>
    for the preparation and validation of your XML instance documents.
   </li>
   <li>The default catalog that is shipped with the Cocoon distribution is
    deliberately basic. You will need to supplement it with your own catalog
    devised to suit your particular needs.
   </li>
  </ul>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="summ"/>
 <s1 title="Summary">
  <p>
   Most XML documents that we would want to serve with Cocoon are already
   in existence in another information system. The XML document instances have
   a declaration of their DTD Document Type Definition as an external file.
   This external DTD also includes entity sets such as ISOnum, ISOlat1, etc.
   Also the DTD declaration has a Formal Public Identifier and a System
   Identifier which points to a remote URL. These XML instance documents cannot
   be altered to make workaround solutions like
   <code>../dtd/document-1.0.dtd</code>
  </p>

  <p>
   Entity management is effected by providing a standards-based mechanism to
   resolve public identifiers and system identifiers to local filenames or
   other identifiers or even to other remote network resources. So references
   to external DTDs, sets of character entities such as mathematical symbols,
   fragments of XML documents, complete sub-documents, non-xml data chunks
   (like images), etc. can all be centrally managed and resolved locally.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="info"/>
 <s1 title="Further information">
  <p>
   Here are some links to documents which extol entity management:
  </p>

  <ul>
   <li><link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/entity/">OASIS Entity
    Resolution Technical Committee</link> - see especially the
    <link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/specs/a401.html">specification for
    OASIS Catalogs</link> (TR 9401:1995 Entity Management)
    and the 
    <link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/committees/entity/spec.html">specification for XML Catalogs</link>
   </li>
   <li><link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/cover/topics.html#entities">SGML/XML Special Topics: Entity Sets and Entity Management</link>
    at the
    <link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/cover/">XML Cover Pages</link></li>
   <li><link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/cover/topics.html#fpi-fsi">SGML/XML
    Special Topics: Catalogs, Formal Public Identifiers, Formal System
    Identifiers</link>
    at the
    <link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/cover/">XML Cover Pages</link></li>
   <li>Arbortext column by Norman Walsh
    <link href="http://www.arbortext.com/Think_Tank/think_tank.html">Standard
    Deviations from Norm</link>
    <br/> - Issue Three: 
    <link href="http://www.arbortext.com/Think_Tank/XML_Resources/Issue_Three/issue_three.html">If You Can Name It, You Can Claim It!</link></li>
   <li>
    <link href="http://www.sun.com/xml/developers/resolver/">XML Entity and
     URI Resolvers Java classes</link> (from Sun Microsystems) and evolution
     of the Arbortext article.
   </li>
   <li>XML-Deviant article 2000-11-29
    <link href="http://www.xml.com/pub/a/2000/11/29/deviant.html">What's in
     a Name?</link></li>
   <li><link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/">DocBook</link>:
     <link href="http://www.docbook.org/">The Definitive Guide</link>
     - Section 2.3 Public Identifiers, System Identifiers, and Catalog Files
   </li>
   <li>OASIS is the <link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/">official
    home</link> of the DocBook DTDs
    (see also <link href="http://docbook.sourceforge.net/">DocBook Open
    Repository</link> project at SourceForge)
   </li>
   <li>Organization for the Advancement of Structured Information Standards
    (<link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/">OASIS</link>)</li>
  </ul>
 </s1>

 </body>
</document>
