<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Views</title>
  <version>0.1</version> 
  <type>Overview document</type> 
  <authors>
    <person name="Christian Haul" email="haul@apache.org"/> 
    <person name="Bernhard Huber" email="berni_huber@a1.net"/> 
  </authors> 
 </header> 
 <body>
  <s1 title="The Views">
   <p>
    Apache Cocoon provides "views" to resource.
    Defining a pipeline in a sitemap specifies the different stages
    of processing a resource. 
    A view defines an exit point in the pipeline processing.
   </p>
   <p>
    Views are yet another sitemap component. 
    Unlike the rest, they
    are othogonal to the resource and pipeline definitions. 
    In the following I will not distinguish between resources and pipelines
    because their differences are not relevant here. So, when I talk
    about pipelines the said is valid for resources as well.
   </p>
   <p>
    Basically, views let you specify exit points of your pipelines
    that are taken whenever a particular view is requested. The
    processing continues with the definitions in the requested view. The
    advantage over selectors that could achieve the same is, that these
    exit points are not necessarily declared for each pipeline
    individually, but once per sitemap.
   </p>

   <s2 title="Motivation">
    <p>
     Implementing a semantic search feature is the main motivation
     to offer views in Apache Cocoon.
    </p>
    <p>
     A sitemap defines the URI space of a Cocoon application.
     Apache Cocoon offers a fairly sophisticated URI space mapping mechanism.
     Defining pipelines in a sitemap you define this mapping.
     It's generally a mistake to map a file system 
     (or a directory server, or a database repository) one-2-one
     with the URI space, since it leads to easily broken links and potential
     security issues. 
    </p>
    <p>
     Browsers requests resources of this URI space. 
     The response of a browser request is easy reenderable intended for presenting
     to a human being. It may be augmented with navigation controls, and advertisment.
     <br/>
     An indexer of a search engines requests resources of this URI space, too.
     In contrast to a browser an indexer is interested in the
     bare content of a resource.
    </p>
    <p>
     Views can access the original content of a resource.
     
     For example, you can now index a document resource, 
     requesting the "content" view of the resource lacking the aggregation 
     with navigation controls, and advertisments.
     
     You can now index the text inside a logo, if you are given the SVG content 
     that generated the raster image. 
     You can index the PDF content without having to implement a PDF parser since you
     request the "content" view of the resource obtaining an easily
     parsable XML file.
    </p>
   </s2>

   <s2 title="Defining A View">
    <p>
     You declare a view in sitemap. The definition of a view
     may define further processing steps. You are not allowed to
     define a generator step for a view, as the content of a view
     is xml content of a view's exit point.
     The most simple view just serialzes the xml content to xml.
    </p>
    <p>
     A view element is identified by its name, and its label. You
     specify the name of a view by the attribute name, and it label either
     by the attribute from-label, or by the attribute from-position.
     The following list explains the attributes in more detail.
    </p>
    <ul>
     <li>
      The attribute name specifies the name of view. Each view must have a unique name.
      If you request a view you have to specify the view name.
     </li>
     <li>
       The attribute from-label defines a label name of a pipeline exit point. 
       You can choose any name you like, as a label name, except "first", and "last".
     </li>
     <li>
       The attribute from-position may have only following values "first", and "last".
       The special label "first" is the pipeline exit point after the generator
       processing stage. 
       The special label "last" is the pipeline exit point
       right before the serializer processing stage.
       The labels "first", and "last" are set by the sitemanager automatically.
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
     The following example is a simple resource view, just serializing
     the xml content of the view's exit point.
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<map:views>
 <map:view name="content" from-label="content">
 <map:serialize type="xml"/>
</map:view>
    ]]></source>
    <p>
     The next example performs an xslt transformation
     before serializing to xml.
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<map:views>
 <map:view name="dublin-core" from-label="dublin-core">
 <map:transform src="stylesheets/document2dubline-core.xsl"/>
 <map:serialize type="xml"/>
</map:view>
    ]]></source>
    <p>
     The last example defines a view specifying the position-from attribute "last",
     and serializing to pdf, for a pdf-aware only indexer, or archiver.
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
<map:views>
 <map:view name="full-document-content" from-position="last">
 <map:transform src="stylesheets/document2fo.xsl"/>
 <map:serialize type="fo2pdf"/>
</map:view>
    ]]></source>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="Placing Labels">
    <p>
     You place labels to define a pipeline exit point.
     A pipeline exit point may be shared by more than a single.
    </p>
    <p>
     Defining a pipeline exit point you have to add an attribute 
     "label" to an sitemap element. Following sitemap elements are label aware:
    </p>
    <table>
     <tr><th>Sitemap Element</th><th>Description</th></tr>
     <tr>
      <td>map:generator</td>
      <td>
       A generator element is allowed to have a label, 
       eg. <code><![CDATA[<map:generator name="foo" src="bar" label="content"/>]]></code>.
       The xml content produced by the generator is passed to the requested view.
       Moreover requesting a "first" view has the same effect as labelling the first
       generator of pipeline.
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>map:generate</td>
      <td>
       A generate element is allowed to have a label attribute, 
       eg. <code><![CDATA[<map:generate type="foo" label="content"/>]]></code>.
       The xml content produced by the generator is passed to the requested view.
       Moreover requesting a "first" view has the same effect as labelling the first
       generator of pipeline.
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>map:transformer</td>
      <td>
       A transformer element is allowed to have a label attribute,
       eg. <code><![CDATA[<map:transformer name="foo" src="bar" label="augmented-content"/>]]></code>.
       The xml content produced by the transformer is passed to the requested view.
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>map:transform</td>
      <td>
       A transform element is allowed to have a label attribute,
       eg. <code><![CDATA[<map:transform type="foo" label="augmented-content"/>]]></code>.
       The xml content produced by the transformer is passed to the requested view.
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>map:aggregate</td>
      <td>
       An aggregte element is allowed to have a label attribute,
       eg. <code><![CDATA[<map:aggregate element="foo" label="all-news"/>]]></code>.
       The xml content produced by the aggregate is passed to the requested view.
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>map:part</td>
      <td>
       A part element of an aggregate element is allowed to have a label attribute.
       eg. <code><![CDATA[<map:part src="foo" label="news-only"/>]]></code>.
       The xml content produced by the part only is passed to the requested view.
      </td>
     </tr>
    </table>
    
    <p>
     A label attribute may hold 1 or more label names, separated by comma or blank,
     eg. <code><![CDATA[<map:generate src="foo" label="label1, label2"/>]]></code>.
    </p>
   </s2>
   
   <s2 title="Placing Labels Summary">
    <p>
     As described above you have a wide range of choice for placing labels.
     You may even place labels to part elements, and to pipelines 
     being the source of a labelled part element. The following paragraphs 
     summarizes the some of the hot features.
    </p>
    <p>
     You can use more that one label-value (label="content,link rdf")
     separated by comma or blank.
    </p>
    <p>
     The aggregate element can have a label attribute which acts
     as on a generator, or transformer (all part elements are collected).
    </p>
    <p>
     Part elements can have a label attribute. In this case only
     those parts are collected which corresponds to the requested view.
    </p>
    <p>
     If you refer to sources via the cocoon:/ protocol the requested view
     will be propagated.
    </p>

    <note>
     The element label is deprecated, and being not supported anymore.
     Thus you have to rewrite your sitemap if you are using 
     <code><![CDATA[<map:label name="foobar"/>]]></code>.
    </note>
    <p>
     Rewrite your sitemap if you were using label elements, moving the label name
     up to the previous xml producer.
     For example rewrite your sitemap:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
...
<map:generate src="foo"/>
<map:transform type="bar"/>
<map:label name="mylabel"/>
<map:serialize/>
...
    ]]></source>
    <p>
     Having this sitemap:
    </p>
    <source><![CDATA[
...
<map:generate src="foo"/>
<map:transform type="bar" label="mylabel"/>
<map:serialize/>
...
    ]]></source>
   </s2>
   <s2 title="View Processing"> 
    <p>
     The samples sitemap contains two view definitions. One of them
     looks like the excerpt below.
    </p>
 
    <source><![CDATA[
<map:views>
 <map:view name="content" from-label="content">
 <map:serialize type="xml"/>
</map:view>
    ]]></source>
 
    <p>
     It only defines what processing steps should be taken, after some
     exit point labelled "content" is reached. In all this case just a 
     serializer is used to further process the document.
    </p>
   </s2>
   
   <s2 title="Exit Points">
    <p>
     A look at the pipelines reveals no label "content". But a closer
     look at the defined components show this:
    </p>

    <source><![CDATA[
<map:components>

 <map:generators default="file">
  <map:generator name="file"        
                 src="org.apache.cocoon.generation.FileGenerator"
                 label="content"/>
  <map:generator name="directory"   
                 src="org.apache.cocoon.generation.DirectoryGenerator"
                 label="content"/>
  <map:generator name="serverpages" 
                 src="org.apache.cocoon.generation.ServerPagesGenerator"
                 label="content"/>
  ...
    ]]></source>

    <p>
     Here a number of generators are declared, each one has a label
     attribute. Now, everytime one of these generators is used in a
     pipeline, an exit point "content" is generated, just after the
     generator has been executed.
    </p>
  
    <p>
     This is not limited to generators but every sitemap component can
     be augmented with a view label.
    </p>
    
    <p>
     Two special labels exist: "first" and "last". These are
     automatically declared for every pipeline, after the first component
     and after the last respectively. This is used by the second view in
     the samples sitemap.
    </p>

    <source><![CDATA[
<map:view name="links" from-position="last">
 <map:serialize type="links"/>
</map:view>
    ]]></source>

    <p>
     There is also another way to specify these exit points:
     <code>&lt;map:label name="mylabel"&gt;</code>. Such a tag can be
     embedded in a pipeline at any place.
    </p>
   </s2>
  
   <s2 title="Requesting A View">
    <p>
     The current way for Cocoon to access views is fixed as a special URI
     query parameter <code>cocoon-view</code>.
    </p>
    <p>
     For example querying the view <code>content</code> of the page:
    </p>
    <source>
http://localhost:8080/cocoon/documents/index.html
    </source>
    <p>
     You use following URL:
    </p>
    <source>
http://localhost:8080/cocoon/documents/index.html?cocoon-view=content
    </source>
    <p>
     Suggestions for further accessing views are:
    </p>
    <ul>
     <li>
      React on a "variant" HTTP header (nothing cocoon specific since the
      concept could be impelemented later on by other publishing frameworks).
     </li>
     <li>
      React on URI extension: for example <code>http://host/path/file.view</code>,
      that is something that can be done by configuring the sitemaps manually.
      (where <code>http://host/path/index</code> is the default resource,
      and <code>index.content</code> is the XML view of the content).
     </li>
    </ul>
   </s2>
   <note>
    Since views are orthogonal to pipelines, keep in mind to
    remove any unwanted view from a deployed application.
   </note>
  </s1>
</body>
</document>
