<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>XSP Logicsheet Guide</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Christopher Painter-Wakefield" email="paint007@mc.duke.edu"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>

<s1 title="Introduction">
  <p>This document is intended as an introduction and brief tutorial to using and
  creating Apache Cocoon XSP logicsheets. It is assumed that the reader has a working
  knowledge of XML and XSLT, and has worked through at least the basic XSP examples
  supplied with Cocoon.  Although this is not intended as a tutorial for XSP 
  specifically, much of the material may be helpful in gaining a fuller understanding
  of XSP.</p>
</s1>

<s1 title="Taglibs and logicsheets">
  <p>There is some confusion over the terms "taglib" and "logicsheet".  Many people
  will use these terms interchangeably.  The term "taglib" comes from JSP, which 
  inspired XSP.  An XSP logicsheet is a "tag library" in the sense that it defines
  a set of custom XML tags which can be used within an XSP program to insert whole
  blocks of code into the file.  Cocoon comes with several pre-defined "taglibs",
  such as the request taglib.  Using the request taglib, you can insert the following
  tag into your XSP code to obtain the HTTP request parameter named "fruit" (e.g., if
  your URL looks something like "http://myserver.org/index.xml?fruit=apple", the value
  of "fruit" is "apple"):</p>
  <source><![CDATA[<request:get-parameter name="fruit"/>]]></source>

  <p>We will discuss how to use Cocoon's pre-defined taglibs in a later section.  The
  important thing to understand is that all taglibs are defined by a logicsheet.  A
  logicsheet, as we will see, is a special kind of XSL stylesheet, whose output is an
  XSP file.</p>
</s1>

<s1 title="Hello World!">
  <p>We'll start with some simple <code>Hello, World!</code> examples, starting with
  a simple HTML file, and extending it using Cocoon technologies until we have a
  working (if trivial) example of XSP using a custom logicsheet.</p>

<s2 title="Simple HTML Example">
  <p>All of the examples in this section will produce HTML output 
  essentially equivalent to this:</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<html>
  <body>
    <h1>Hello, world!</h1>
  </body>
</html>
]]></source>
</s2>

  <p>I did say these would be simple examples, didn't I?</p>

<s2 title="Simple XML/XSL Example">
  <p>Here's a simple XML file:</p>
  
<source>
<strong>greeting.xml</strong>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>

<greeting>Hello, world!</greeting>
]]></source>

  <p>...and here's the XSL stylesheet that will transform it into an HTML file
  similar to the one we started this section with:</p>

<source>
<strong>greeting.xsl</strong>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" version="1.0">

<xsl:template match="/">
  <html>
    <body>
      <h1>
        <xsl:value-of select="greeting"/>
      </h1>
    </body>
  </html>
</xsl:template>

</xsl:stylesheet>
]]></source>

  <p>So far, nothing exciting.  The input XML has a single element, &lt;greeting>,
  whose text contents gets spit out in HTML.  The contents of our particular XML
  file's greeting is, predictably, "Hello, World!"  The point of showing you this
  is that, as we elaborate our example by adding Java code through XSP, and later
  with a custom logicsheet, we will continue to use the same stylesheet to format
  our final output.  So, the input XML will generally look much like the XML file
  in this most recent trivial example.</p>
</s2>

<s2 title="Simple XSP Example">
  <p>Next, we continue in our trivial vein by using trivial Java code to make an
  XSP program, whose output will mimic that of our XML file above.  The output
  of this file is transformed to HTML by the same XSL stylesheet as above:</p>

<source>
<strong>greeting2.xml</strong>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>

<xsp:page
  xmlns:xsp="http://www.apache.org/1999/XSP/Core"
>
  <xsp:logic>
    // this could be arbitrarily complex Java code, JDBC queries, etc.
    String msg = "Hello, world!";
  </xsp:logic>

  <greeting>
    <xsp:expr>msg</xsp:expr>
  </greeting>

</xsp:page>
]]></source>
</s2>

<s2 title="Simple XSP Logicsheet Example">

  <p>Now we are ready to present our final trivial example, using a custom
  logicsheet.  There are two files shown below.  The first is an XSP file
  that uses a custom logicsheet, logicsheet.greeting.xsl, which is the second
  file shown below.</p>

<source>
<strong>greeting3.xml</strong>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>

<xsp:page
  xmlns:xsp="http://www.apache.org/1999/XSP/Core"
  xmlns:greeting="http://duke.edu/tutorial/greeting"
>
  <greeting>
    <greeting:hello-world/>
  </greeting>

</xsp:page>
]]></source>


<source>
<strong>logicsheet.greeting.xsl</strong>
<![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<xsl:stylesheet
  xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform"
  xmlns:xsp="http://www.apache.org/1999/XSP/Core"
  xmlns:greeting="http://duke.edu/tutorial/greeting"
  version="1.0">

<xsl:template match="xsp:page">
 <xsl:copy>
  <xsl:apply-templates select="@*"/>
  <xsl:apply-templates/>
 </xsl:copy>
</xsl:template>

<xsl:template match="greeting:hello-world">
  <!-- more complex XSLT is possible here as well -->
  <xsp:logic>
    // this could be arbitrarily complex Java code, JDBC queries, etc.
    String msg = "Hello, world!";
  </xsp:logic>
  <xsp:expr>msg</xsp:expr>
</xsl:template>

<!-- This template simply copies stuff that doesn't match other -->
<!-- templates and applies templates to any children.           -->
<xsl:template match="@*|node()" priority="-1">
 <xsl:copy>
  <xsl:apply-templates select="@*|node()"/>
 </xsl:copy>
</xsl:template>

</xsl:stylesheet>
]]></source>

  <p>There are several things to note about these two files.  First, note
  that we inform the XSP processor that it should apply our custom logicsheet
  using the processing instruction</p>
  <source><![CDATA[<?xml-logicsheet href="logicsheet.greeting.xsl"?>]]></source>

  <p>There are other ways to associate a logicsheet with an XSP file, which we'll
  discuss later.  Next, note that our logicsheet defines a new namespace, 
  <strong>greeting:</strong>, which must be declared in both files using the same URI:</p>
  <source><![CDATA[xmlns:greeting="http://duke.edu/tutorial/greeting"]]></source>

  <p>Note that the URI is completely arbitrary.  I've chosen to construct my
  namespace URI's by using my institution's web address (http://duke.edu/)
  followed by the project name (tutorial) and namespace name (greeting).  
  You may use any scheme you wish for your namespace URI's; however, the URI
  declared in the logicsheet <strong>must</strong> match the URI declared in the
  XSP which uses the logicsheet.</p>

  <p>Finally, note that our logicsheet is merely an XSL stylesheet.  It transforms
  one XML file into another.  What makes it a logicsheet is that it can be applied
  not just to any XML file, but specifically to an XSP file, and the end result of
  its transformation is another XSP file.  If you were to apply the logicsheet in
  this example to the XML file in this example as just a stylesheet (with no XSP
  processing), you would end up with something like the following (compare to our 
  earlier XSP example):</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?cocoon-process type="xsp"?>
<xsp:page 
  xmlns:greeting="http://duke.edu/tutorial/greeting" 
  xmlns:xsp="http://www.apache.org/1999/XSP/Core"
>
  <greeting>
    <xsp:logic>
      // this could be arbitrarily complex Java code, JDBC queries, etc.
      String msg = &quot;Hello, world!&quot;;
    </xsp:logic>
    <xsp:expr>msg</xsp:expr>
  </greeting>
</xsp:page>
]]></source>
</s2>

</s1>

<s1 title="Using Logicsheets (Taglibs)">
  <p>There are two ways to apply a logicsheet, once you have written it.
  First, as in the previous examples, you can tell XSP explicitly what
  logicsheets to apply, using the &lt;?xml-logicsheet?> processing instruction
  along with the usual &lt;?cocoon-process?> instruction that tells 
  Cocoon to use XSP:</p>
<source><![CDATA[
<?cocoon-process type="xsp"?>
<?xml-logicsheet href="logicsheet.greeting.xsl"?>]]>
</source>

  <p>There is another way to apply a logicsheet, which doesn't require a
  processing instruction for each file that uses the logicsheet.  The
  second way to use a logicsheet depends on whether you are using Cocoon 1
  or Cocoon 2.
  For Cocoon 1, a logicsheet's namespace may be declared in the 
  cocoon.properties file.  These declarations take the form</p>
<source>processor.xsp.logicsheet.namespace-name.language = URL to file</source>

  <p>Cocoon's pre-defined logicsheets are already declared in this file.  For
  instance, the declaration of the request taglib is the following:</p>
<source>
processor.xsp.logicsheet.request.java  
  = resource://org/apache/cocoon/processor/xsp/library/java/request.xsl
</source>
  <p>This line associates the <strong>request:</strong> namespace with the logicsheet
  named in the URL.  This URL points to a file that is stored in the cocoon.jar.
  To use the request taglib, you must declare the request namespace in your XSP 
  file:</p>
<source><![CDATA[
...
<xsp:page
  xmlns:xsp="http://www.apache.org/1999/XSP/Core"
  xmlns:request="http://www.apache.org/1999/XSP/Request"
>
...
]]></source>

  <p>Note that you should <strong>not</strong> try to apply the request taglib
  using the &lt;?xml-logicsheet?> processing instruction, as this will result in
  the logicsheet being applied twice.</p>

  <p>You can add your own logicsheets to the cocoon.properties file using the same
  syntax.  The only trick is constructing an appropriate URL.  If we wanted to declare
  our <strong>greeting:</strong> namespace and logicsheet from the Hello, World! example 
  above, and if the logicsheet were stored (on a UNIX filesystem) in the location
  /cocoon/logicsheets/logicsheet.greeting.xsl, we'd add this line to cocoon.properties:</p>
<source>
processor.xsp.logicsheet.greeting.java 
  = file:///cocoon/logicsheets/logicsheet.greeting.xsl
</source>

  <p>There are some very important differences between using the &lt;?xml-logicsheet?> 
  processing instruction vs. the cocoon.properties entry to apply a logicsheet.
  Using cocoon.properties, any time the logicsheet changes, it is necessary to 
  restart Cocoon.  If you instead use the processing instruction, Cocoon will detect
  modifications to your logicsheet, and recompile your XSP programs accordingly.
  Also, if you need to explicitly control the order in which your logicsheets are
  applied, you need to use the processing instruction.  Logicsheets will be applied
  in the order in which they appear in processing instructions in your source file.</p>

  <p>Whichever method you use, the most important thing to remember is that you must
  declare, in your XSP program, the namespace for a logicsheet using the same URI as
  in the logicsheet itself.</p>

</s1>

<s1 title="Logicsheet Development Tips">
  <s2 title="Development Practices">
  <p>Developing Logicsheets can be a frustrating mental exercise, as it requires you
  to understand and keep in mind the complex coordination of several different 
  technologies: XML, XSLT, XSP, and Java.  A bad assumption in any of these areas
  can lead to an hour of debugging.  Following a few simple practices can reduce the
  frustration and make logicsheet programming less difficult:</p>
  <dl>
    <dt>Small Increments</dt>
    <dd>As with any software development, it is much easier to debug a small amount
    of code than a large amount of code.  XSP is no different, except that the 
    complexity of a large amount of code is multiplied by the number of different
    technologies.  So, write a tiny bit of code and get it working, or start with a
    simple piece of code that is already working.  Make small changes, and get each
    change working before making the next.</dd>
    <dt>Prototype New Ideas</dt>
    <dd>Before trying something you haven't done before (e.g., a new XPath expression,
    a new Java syntax), prototype it in a simple environment where you can easily see
    the results of your code.  It is more difficult to debug your changes if the output
    is filtered through multiple stylesheets and rendered into HTML.  So instead, write
    a small XSP that you can use to test your code fragment and see the resulting XML.</dd>
    <dt>Use the Source</dt>
    <dd>After transforming your XSP code with your logicsheet, the XSP processor writes
    the resulting Java code to a file in your repository.  The repository is in a
    directory specified in cocoon.properties.  Make a shortcut to your repository
    directory and go there often.  Read the code that resulted from application of your
    stylesheet.  This lets you debug the Java code as Java code, absent from all of the
    XML/XSL complications.  It also lets you see exactly the results of XSLT transformation
    using your logicsheet.</dd>
    <dt>Steal Code</dt>
    <dd>The authors of the logicsheets distributed with Cocoon have already solved
    numerous problems that you may encounter.  Read their code (it is in the source
    tree) and borrow from it liberally.  Reading this code is also a good way to
    gain insight into logicsheet design.</dd>
  </dl>
  </s2> 

  <s2 title="Standard Templates">
    <p>As we discussed earlier, a logicsheet is just an XSLT stylesheet which transforms
    one XSP source file into another.  Since we are always expecting to act on an XSP 
    source file, and there is the possibility that other logicsheets may also be acting
    on the same file (either before or after our logicsheet), there are a few templates
    which are more or less required in any logicsheet.  The templates below were all
    pulled from the taglib logicsheets distributed with Cocoon.</p>
    <p>The first of these is simply a template to copy anything you don't directly act
    upon yourself.  You probably have a template similar to this in most of your
    stylesheets already.</p>
<source><![CDATA[
<xsl:template match="@*|node()" priority="-1">
  <xsl:copy>
    <xsl:apply-templates select="@*|node()"/>
  </xsl:copy>
</xsl:template>
]]></source>

    <p>If your code requires any Java imports, or if you want to declare methods or
    variables at the class level, you will need to have a way to add elements to the
    &lt;xsp:page> element that is at the root of the source file.  Here is a template
    to let you do that (from esql.xsl):</p>
<source><![CDATA[
<xsl:template match="xsp:page">
  <xsp:page>
    <xsl:apply-templates select="@*"/>
    <xsp:structure>
      // you can put &lt;xsp:include> statements in here to import Java classes
    </xsp:structure>
    <xsp:logic>
      // put class-level variable declarations and methods here
    </xsp:logic>
  </xsp:page>
</xsl:template>
]]></source>
 
    <p>Frequently, you may also need to declare variables or perform initialization
    that needs to occur before any of the code in your custom tags.  You could, of
    course, require that the users of your logicsheet use one particular tag before
    using any other, and then put your declarations and initializations in the template
    matching that one tag.  This may not be the best solution, however, and may be
    a source of confusion.  Instead, the following template can be used to insert
    code inside the populateDocument() method, after the standard XSP code (such as
    declaration of the request and response variables), but before any user code
    from the source XSP file (including code inserted by your custom tags). The
    complex XPath expression here just says "match on any child elements of &lt;xsp:page
    which don't themselves begin with 'xsp:'".  Since the &lt;xsp:page> element always
    has a single element which isn't in the xsp: namespace, this will be matched once
    and only once.</p>
<source><![CDATA[
<xsl:template match="xsp:page/*[not(starts-with(name(.), 'xsp:'))]">
 <xsl:copy>
  <xsl:apply-templates select="@*"/>
  <xsp:logic>
    // This code ends up inside populateDocument() before any user code
  </xsp:logic>
  <xsl:apply-templates/>
 </xsl:copy>
</xsl:template> 
]]></source>

  </s2>

  <s2 title="Logicsheets Using Logicsheets">
    <p>Since software tends to build on other software, you will probably find
    yourself wanting to write logicsheets which make use of other logicsheets,
    particularly the logicsheets provided with Cocoon.  This is very possible.
    When using one logicsheet inside another, the most important thing to remember
    is that you must declare the namespace for the second logicsheet not only in
    the first logicsheet, but also in any XSP program that uses the first logicsheet,
    even if it doesn't directly reference any of the tags in the second logicsheet.</p>
  </s2>
</s1>


</body>

</document>
