<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>

  <header>
    <title>Session tracking with Cocoon</title>
    <subtitle>Introduction, Installation and Example</subtitle>
    <version>0.1</version>
    <type>Technical Document</type>
    <authors>
      <person name="J&ouml;rg Prante" email="joerg@7val.com"/>
    </authors>
    <abstract>
    This document explains what Apache Cocoon provides to support session tracking.
    Session tracking is an important feature for web server frameworks
    because HTTP and related protocols are stateless,
    but sometimes we need stateful information about visitors of a Cocoon site.
    For a more precise analysis of a web site, the tracking of visitors
    should work independent of the visitor's browser and of the visitor's decision
    whether we enabled cookies or not. Last not least, Cocoon should not
    be dependant of the method the servlet engine prefers to generate session IDs.
    In this document, it is described step by step what has to be done to enable
    Cocoon for session management.
    </abstract>
  </header>

  <body>
    <s1 title="Introduction">
      <s2 title="Goal">
        <p>
         Maintaining state is a common problem for web server frameworks
         because HTTP is a stateless protocol. There are many solutions known
         to obtain stateful information. Client-side storage of state information
         like the usage of cookies will not be discussed here, since this depends
         heavily on the client's browser. Since Cocoon is a server-side framework,
         storing visitor information at the server side will give full access
         to the list of all visitors, to what they have done, and what they are
         doing.
         </p>
         <p>Please always think a little while if you really want to set up
         session management. Less scalability and performance is the dark
         side of keeping user sessions at the server-side. Each user session consumes
         memory, disk, and CPU, and it is always recommended that you be careful to
         system resources before wasting it.
         </p>
         <p>
         If you decided to set up session tracking, Cocoon offers you:
         </p>
          <ul>
            <li>creation of new session IDs</li>
            <li>full session control by the underlying Servlet API 2.2 servlet engine</li>
            <li>cookie- and URI-based session management</li>
            <li>automatic link rewrite if you like your XSP pages to be URI-session-aware</li>
          </ul>
         </s2>


        <s2 title="The session:encode-url template">

        <p>
        To enable Cocoon for URI-based session IDs, an XSP template with the name
        <code>session:encode-url</code> will do this for you. It uses the
        <code>encodeURL</code> method from the Servlet API which encodes
        an URL in a way that a session ID is being attached. Consult your
        servlet engine documentation for information about what the <code>encodeURL</code>
        method returns. For example, the Tomcat
        engine adds a string <code>;jsession=</code> followed by an MD5 hash
        to the URL, but only if the client's browser does not accept cookies.
        </p>

        <p>Here is the fragment for the <code>session:encode-url</code> from session.xsl:</p>

<source><![CDATA[
<!-- encode an URL with the session ID -->
<xsl:template match="session:encode-url">
  <xsl:variable name="href">
      "<xsl:value-of select="@href"/>"
  </xsl:variable>

  <xsp:element name="a">
    <xsp:attribute name="href">
      <xsp:expr>
        response.encodeURL(String.valueOf(<xsl:copy-of select="$href"/>))
      </xsp:expr>
    </xsp:attribute>
    <xsl:value-of select="."/>
  </xsp:element>

</xsl:template>
]]></source>

         <p>
         As you might wonder, the XSP template constructs a HTML tag <code>&lt;a&gt;</code> with an
         attribute <code>href</code> which is enough for most of the cases.
         Other methods, like XLink, are planned to be supported at a later time when
         final W3C recommendations are out.
         </p>

         </s2>

         <s2 title="Creating new sessions">
         <p>
         The best place of a web site where new sessions should be created is the entry point
         where all or most of the visitors step in. After creating the session, or
         retrieving an old session, the visitor is redirected to a start page.
         In Cocoon, you must edit your sitemap in order to
         specify this interesting point of session creation.
         The <code>map-redirect-to</code>
         has an extra attribute <code>session</code>, which can be set to <code>true</code>
         or <code>false</code>. The former will generate a new session ID if needed
         by invoking the Servlet API method <code>session = request.getSession(true)</code>,
         while the latter ignores session ID handling.
         </p>

         <p>
         How can Cocoon recognize URIs with appended session IDs? The answer is:
         Cocoon can match a wildcard against your sessionized pages and keeps happy.
         So please do not forget to append an asterisk '*' to your patterns in the pipelines.
         </p>

         <p>
         This fragment from <code>sitemap.xsl</code> shows how you can add a
         <code>map:redirect-to</code> to
         your Cocoon framework with session handling at the root URL for your
         web application:
         </p>

<source><![CDATA[

 <map:pipelines>
  <map:pipeline>

   <map:match pattern="">
     <map:redirect-to session="true" uri="welcome"/>
   </map:match>

   <map:match pattern="welcome*">
    <map:generate type="file" src="site/welcome.xml"/>
    <map:transform src="stylesheets/welcome.xsl"/>
    <map:serialize/>
   </map:match>

   <map:match pattern="**.xsp*">
    <map:generate type="serverpages" src="site/{1}.xsp"/>
    <map:transform src="stylesheets/dynamic-page2html.xsl"/>
    <map:serialize/>
   </map:match>
]]></source>
               </s2>
            </s1>

            <s1 title="Example">
              <s2 title="A simple XSP page with session ID">

              <p>
              Here you can see the source of an XSP example of how the
              session feature can be used.
              The example is located in a file named <code>sessionpage.xsp</code>
              and it displays the received session ID together with a rewritten
              link to the page itself. Depending on your browser settings,
              you will see nothing (because your browser prefers crunching cookies)
              or a session ID is encoded into the URL. After clicking on the
              link named "Follow me!", the session ID is taken into the URL, and
              the session tracking is established.
              </p>

<source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<xsp:page
   language="java"
   xmlns:xsp="http://apache.org/xsp"
   xmlns:session="http://apache.org/xsp/session/2.0"
   xmlns:xsp-request="http://apache.org/xsp/request/2.0"
>

<!-- a simple session page by J&ouml;rg Prante <joerg@7val.com> -->

<page>
  <title>A Simple URI-based Session Example</title>
  <content>
    <para> <xsp-request:get-uri as="xml"/> </para>
    <para> Session ID = <session:get-id as="xml"/> </para>
    <para>
      Encode URL Test =
      <session:encode-url href="sessionpage.xsp">Follow me!</session:encode-url>
    </para>
  </content>
</page>

</xsp:page>
]]></source>

      <p>
      If you have been successful with installing the session feature and
      the example file, the following HTML output will be generated by
      Cocoon from the above <code>sessionpage.xsp</code> example, which shows
      how the rewritten link looks like. Please don't ask
      why the session ID in the generated link is different from yours.
      </p>

<source><![CDATA[
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC
    "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.0//EN"
    "http://www.w3.org/TR/WD-html-in-xml/DTD/xhtml1-strict.dtd">
<html><head><title>
     A Simple URI Session Example
  </title></head><body vlink="blue" link="blue" alink="red" bgcolor="white">

  <h2 style="color: navy; text-align: center">
     A Simple URI Session Example
  </h2>

  <content>

  <p align="left"><i>
     <b xmlns:xsp-response="http://apache.org/xsp/response/2.0"
        xmlns:xsp-request="http://apache.org/xsp/request/2.0">sessionpage.xsp</b>
  </i></p>

  <p align="left"><i>
     Session ID =
     <session:id>F3E9575442D1899760A0B231D0042281</session:id>
  </i></p>

  <p align="left"><i>
    Encode URL Test =
    <a href="sessionpage.xsp;jsessionid=F3E9575442D1899760A0B231D0042281">Follow me!</a>
  </i></p>
  </content>

</body></html>
]]></source>

         </s2>
      </s1>

      <s1 title="Log analysis of sessions">

      <p>
        To be done.
      </p>

      </s1>

</body>
</document>
