<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE changes PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Changes V1.0//EN" "dtd/changes-v10.dtd">

<!--
  History of Cocoon changes
  $Id: changes.xml,v 1.84 2002/01/30 17:59:40 froehlich Exp $
-->

<changes title="History of Changes">

 <devs>
  <!-- in strict alphabetical order -->
  <person name="Donald Ball" email="balld@apache.org" id="DB"/>
  <person name="Ross Burton" email="rossb@apache.org" id="RB"/>
  <person name="David Crossley" email="crossley@apache.org" id="DC"/>
  <person name="Gerhard Froehlich" email="g-froehlich@gmx.de" id="GF"/>
  <person name="Pierpaolo Fumagalli" email="pier@apache.org" id="PF"/>
  <person name="Vadim Gritsenko" email="vgritsenko@apache.org" id="VG"/>
  <person name="Christian Haul" email="haul@apache.org" id="CH"/>
  <person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org" id="BL"/>
  <person name="Stefano Mazzocchi" email="stefano@apache.org" id="SM"/>
  <person name="Giacomo Pati" email="Giacomo.Pati@pwr.ch" id="GP"/>
  <person name="Ovidiu Predescu" email="ovidiu@cup.hp.com" id="OP"/>
  <person name="Gianugo Rabellino" email="gianugo@apache.org" id="GR"/>
  <person name="Ricardo Rocha" email="ricardo@apache.org" id="RR"/>
  <person name="Paul Russell" email="prussell@apache.org" id="PR"/>
  <person name="Davanum Srinivas" email="dims@yahoo.com" id="DM"/>
  <person name="Sylvain Wallez" email="sylvain@apache.org" id="SW"/>
  <person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org" id="CZ"/>
 </devs>

 <release version="2.0.1" date="January 31 2002">
  <action dev="SW" type="update" due-to="Stephan Michels" due-to-email="stephan@vern.chem.tu-berlin.de">
    The FragmentExtractorTransformer is now configurable to extract any fragment
    identified by an element name and namespace URI, and no more limited to
    SVG images only.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="fix">
    XSP engine now correctly works with dynamically generated sources
    with last modification date of 0, and it is correctly reloaded on Cocoon
    reload.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="update">
    Logicsheets are resolved using instance of url factory source resolver 
    (URLFactorySourceResolver), and not the current request resolver (which
    is temporary object).
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="update">
    Improve Lucene indexing. Only one Lucene document is created for one 
    Cocoon resource. Document consists from 'body' field with all the text,
    'element' field for every &lt;element&gt;, and 'element@attribute' for 
    every attribute of the &lt;element&gt;.
  </action>
  <action dev="GF" type="fix">
   Fixed performance issues in the Store implementation:
   (1) removed the FilesystemQueueImpl, one thread less now, (2) changed swapping 
   alghorithm in the MRUMemoryStore towards less serialization, (3) Cache entries
   will be saved to the filesystem, when the System is shutdown cleanly, (4) fixed
   bug submitted by Peter Hargreaves [pdh@totalise.co.uk] in StoreJanitor
   (GC hangs in endless loop).
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="update">
    Serializers do not write namespace attributes for prefixes starting with
    xml anymore (these are reserved by XML spec).
  </action>
  <action dev="GF" type="update">
   Removed Event Cache and Stream Cache. For all possible Caching Piplines there
   is only one Store implementation behind.
  </action>
  <action dev="GF" type="update">
   Added new log targets. (1) access.log, (2) core.log, (3) error.log and
   (4) sitemap.log.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="update">
    Perform substitution in the sitemap only when it is required (improves
    performace).
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="add">
    Additions to sitemap syntax: (1) allow all elements at root level, not 
    only matchers, (2) perform some validation checks, (3) perform attribute
    substitution on all attributes except @type and @label.
  </action>
  <action dev="DC" type="add">
    Added &quot;List of Docs&quot; which automatically generates a list
    of all Cocoon documentation by aggregating each xdocs/**/book.xml
  </action>
  <action dev="DC" type="fix" fixes-bug="5060">
    The Catalog Entity Resolver is now fully operational on all platforms
    in both the webapp context and the commandline context of build docs.
    The verbosity level is now set low - if you want to see messages, then
    raise the verbosity via cocoon.xconf or CatalogManager.properties
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Separated the jars into core and optional. For compiling only the
    core jars are necessary. However, the sample webapp still needs some
    optional jars.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="add">
    Added matchers: 
    RegexpHeaderMatcher, RegexpRequestAttributeMatcher,
    RegexpRequestParameterMatcher, RegexpSessionAttributeMatcher,
    RequestAttributeMatcher, SessionAttributeMatcher,
    WildcardHostMatcher, WildcardRequestAttributeMatcher.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="fix" fixes-bug="5791">
    Address issue about how RegexpURIMatcher matches the "" pattern.
    Because it is so different from WildcardURIMatcher, the "" pattern
    is rewritten as "^$" which matches an empty string.  The event is
    logged, along with the hint that if you really want to match
    everything, the pattern ".*" works as advertised.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="update">
    Fix command line generation so that a broken link was not a fatal
    error, and processing will continue after the link is reported as
    bad.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="add">
    Add ability to serialize all broken links to a file when running in
    command line mode.  This helps debug sites.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="update">
    Rename some of the matchers/serializers (new added, old deprecated):
    RequestSelector to RequestParameterSelector,
    RequestParamMatcher to RequestParameterMatcher,
    WildcardParameterValueMatcher to WildcardRequestParameterMatcher,
    RegexpTargetHostMatcher to RegexpHostMatcher.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="update">
    Wap serializer renamed to wml serializer in the sitemap shipped with
    Cocoon, to be consistent with the names of other serializers.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    FilterTransformer is now Cacheable.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Added CACHE_VALIDITY singleton object to NOPCacheValidity and changed all
    components to use constant instead of creating new instances each time.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="fix">
    Fix lifecycle related bugs in i18n transformer. Now transformers handles
    only lifecycle of resource bundle factory, which handles lifecycle of all
    resource bundles.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Added special lifecycle interface for Cocoon components: RequestLifecycle.   
    A component marked by this interface has the lifecycle of one request,
    so looking up the role twice during the same request results in the same
    component.
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="update">
    The "namespace-prefixes" feature is no more set on parsers. It can be set if
    needed in the configuration.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="add">
    Added ability to use XPath expressions to query XML:DB collections using
    XML:DB pseudo protocol. URL should be in form:
    xmldb:dbxml://host:port/db/collection/#/xpath
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="add">
    Enabled XML:DB support (generators and pseudo protocol) by default.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="fix" fixes-bug="4239">
    JSPEngine returns result in UTF-8 charset.
  </action>
  <action dev="CH" type="add">
    Changed invokation syntax of sitemap resources. Now &lt;call resource/&gt;
    is used instead of &lt;redirect-to resource/&gt;. Affects only resources,
    other redirections still use "old" syntax. New syntax does not take "target"
    attribute but allows to set arbitrary parameters by using
    &lt;map-parameter/&gt; Always creates new map while old syntax only did
    when "target" was present. Old syntax still available but deprecated.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="fix" due-to="Eisert, Wolfram" due-to-email="Wolfram.Eisert@Dresdner-Bank.com">
    XSP page were called twice if used as a source of XSLT stylesheet due to multiple calls to 
    Source.getInputSource() in XSLProcessorImpl.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="update">
    Changed default upload directory from "image-dir" to "upload-dir".
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="add" due-to="MIYABE Tatsuhiko" due-to-email="miyabe@jzf.co.jp">
    RequestGenerator accepts container-encoding and form-encoding parameters.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Added support for configurable URLFactories.
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="fix">
    Made the cache work again by updating cocoon.roles, sitemap.roles and making EventPipeline
    and StreamPipeline implement Recomposable instead of just Composable.
  </action>
  <action dev="GR" type="add">
    Added the XML:DB pseudo protocol
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="add">
    Status generator outputs a detailed description of what's in the cache. Patch submitted by
    Sebastien Koechlin [skoechlin@ivision.fr]
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Applied patch adding advanced error handling to SQLTransformer plus escape-string element
    from Peter Seiderer [Peter.Seiderer@ciselant.de]
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    The JaxpParser is now poolable and configurable.
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="update">
    The sitemap engine is now a regular component available through Processor.ROLE. This allows
    alternative implementations of Processors (e.g. interpreted sitemap, flowmap, statemap) to
    be plugged through cocoon.xconf. Note : to ensure compatibility with existing cocoon.xconf
    files, the shorthand for the Processor role is "sitemap".
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Added support for configurable SourceFactories.
    Patch submitted by Gianugo Rabellino [gianugo@rabellino.it].
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Added RTF serialization of XSL-FO documents (requires jfor).
    Patch submitted by Bertrand Delacretaz [bdelacretaz@codeconsult.ch].
    Applied patch for the SQLTransformer to output namespaces for the
    generated elements. Patch submitted by Per-Olof Nor謠[pelle@alma.nu].
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="add">
   New ServerPagesAction and associated "action" and "capture" logicsheets
   that allow actions to be written in XSP and parts of the generated XML
   to be captured in XMLFragment or DOM objects.
  </action>
 </release>
 <release version="2.0" date="November 29, 2001">
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Restructured build system. A new ant task (SitemapToolTask) adds entries
    of optional components to the sitemap. Warnings for not available
    optional components are printed out.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="update">
    Made the concept of views work as proposed in the original proposal. There
    is now the possibility to attach a label attribute with multiple values separated
    by blanks or commas to the following elements: map:generator, map:transformer,
    map:generate, map:transform, map:aggregate and map:part.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Applied patch for session-info for TraxTransformer from J&ouml;rn Heid
    [heid@fh-heilbronn.de].
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Applied patch for the SQLTransformer to output namespaces for the
    generated elements. Patch submitted by Per-Olof Nor謠[pelle@alma.nu].
  </action>
  <action dev="OP" type="update">
    Applied patch for incremental XSLT processing from J&ouml;rn Heid
    [heid@fh-heilbronn.de].
  </action>
 </release>
 <release version="2.0rc2" date="November 7, 2001">
  <action dev="SW" type="add">
    Deprecation of CodeFactory in preparation of the tree traversal implementation of the sitemap.
    All factory-based matchers have been rewritten using the new PreparableMatcher interface, and
    all factory-based selectors have been rewritten as regular implementations of Selector.
    For patterns whose syntax uses '{' like regexp, sitemap substitution can be avoided by escaping the
    brace character (example : "pat\{2}ern" will match "pattern").
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="fix">
    Reduce exception nesting in case of sitemap setup errors, and display all nested exceptions
    in the error page (avoids searching the logs for the failure cause).
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="update">
    Added attribute management methods to environment Context and its implementations.
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="update">
    Updated TraxTransformer and XSLTProcessor to allow simultaneous use of several
    TRAX processors (e.g. xalan and saxon) in a controlled way. 
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Updated session handling of commandline interface and fixed
    parameter handling.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Fixed missing prefix in elements generated by the directory and image
    directory generator.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
   Throw exception for internal requests instead of using the error handler and
   fixed component handling in subsitemaps when invoked internally. Components only
   defined in a subsitemap were not found as for internal requests the parent
   component manager was used.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    When Cocoon is reloaded, the logkit configuration is now also reloading. 
    This enables changing the logkit settings during runtime.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    The documentation build system now uses Cocoon itself to generate the
    html documentation.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Applied NPE fix in certain conditions in ServerPagesGenerator.
    Submitted by: Ovidiu Predescu [ovidiu@cup.hp.com] 
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Applied NPE fix for MRUMemoryStore Submitted by: Ovidiu Predescu [ovidiu@cup.hp.com] 
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Fixed (hopefully) dependency to the http environment in StreamGenerator.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Optional setting of the lexical-handler for XMLReader. This patch allows to use 
    Crimson instead of Xerces. Submitted by: Ovidiu Predescu [ovidiu@cup.hp.com] 
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Added xml compiler and interpreter to cocoon.xconf 
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Applied Patch for entity catalogs: accept parameters from xconf.
    Submitted by: David Crossley [crossley@indexgeo.com.au] 
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Applied fix for missing "User-Agent" header in BrowserSelectorFactory.
    Submitted by: Joerg Henne [j.henne@levigo.de] 
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Enhanced Command Line Interface by adding background attribute to ExtendedXLinkPipe
    and fixing bugs: "mailto:" and "news:" are now ignored for traversing and links
    containing anchors are handled properly
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
    Applied patch for default value support for RequestParamAction.
    Submitted by: Sergio Carvalho [sergio.carvalho@acm.org] 
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Applied fix for a bug in the WriteDOMSessionTransformer for handling xml documents
    with namespaces correctly. Submitted by: Greg Weinger [gweinger@itmedicine.net] 
  </action>
 </release>
 <release version="2.0rc1" date="September 24, 2001">
  <action dev="SW" type="add">
   New "capture" logicsheet that allows parts of XSP-generated XML to be captured
   as XMLFragment or DOM objects.
  </action>
   <action dev="GP" type="add">
   Added LogKit management functionality.
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="add">
   Removed ThreadSafe from the Action interfaces : the decision to be ThreadSafe
   is left to each implementation. Consequently, existing actions now explictly
   implement ThreadSafe.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
   Redesigned the handling of the cocoon: protocol. Removed the pushURI
   and popURI methods. It is now possible to load cocoon: resources
   parallel in several tasks.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="fix" fixes-bug="2737">
   Fixed package name generation for subsitemap components and external components.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="add">
   Added ability to specify custom 404 error page for pipelines using
   map:handle-errors element with attribute type="404".
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="fix">
   Catch NoClassDefFoundError and throw ResourceNotFoundException
   if XSP was requested with different case.
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="add">
   New log formatter outputs the caller class and request URI in the log file. 
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
   Added patch by Stuart Roebuck (stuart.roebuck@adolos.com)
   fixing the byte handling of the ImageDirectoryGenerator.
  </action>
  <action dev="DM" type="add">
   Added capability to resolve external XML entities using an entity resolver.
   See the documentation for "Entity Catalogs".
  </action>
 </release>
 <release version="2.0b2" date="July 23, 2001">
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    When a resource is not found (ResourceNotFoundException) the
    servlet sets only the status 404 and doesn't write to the output.    
  </action>
  <action dev="SW" type="add">
    In http environment, reset the response if it hasn't been committed
    before executing the handle-errors pipeline.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Added reloading of jar files. When cocoon is reloaded by specifying
    cocoon-reload parameter, the class-path is new build and used.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Added caching of cocoon: urls.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Redirects are handled when the cocoon: url points to a redirect in 
    the sitemaps.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="fix">
    Fixed proper setting of content length for pdf and images.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="fix">
    Fixed parsing and reporting of Java compilation errors using Javac
    and Jikes compilers.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="add" due-to="John Morrison" due-to-email="John.Morrison@uk.experian.com">
    Added documentation on libraries used in Cocoon.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Redesigned the source handling and added the source handler
    and source factory components.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Added the cocoon: protocol to access pipelines. cocoon:/ resolves
    to the current sitemap and cocoon:// to the root sitemap.
  </action>
  <action dev="VG" type="fix">
    Offline site generation now allows recursive links and
    works for site of any complexity (limited by capabilities of your
    filesystem).
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Removed XInclude/CIncludeSAXConnectors and added LoggingSAXConnector.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Added CIncludeTransformer.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="fix" fixes-bug="2182">
    Fixed the sub-sitemap issue experienced after a code merge
    between 2.0 and 2.1
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="add">
    Added the automatic announcement generation utility from
    Avalon.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="fix" fixes-bug="2172">
    Fixed typo that created an element &lt;xsp-request:get-user/&gt;
    instead of &lt;xsp-request:get-host/&gt; in XSPRequestHelper.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="fix" fixes-bug="2166">
    Made sure the _static_ classes did not inherit from each other,
    and made all calls to XSPObjectHelper that handled XML elements
    explicitly call with URI and PREFIX as parameters to the methods.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="fix" fixes-bug="2142">
    Applied fix to URLFactoryImpl donated by wangtun@staff.yam.com.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="add">
    Added support for fine-grained pool size control for Excalibur Component
    Architecture.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="fix">
    Fixed component release errors in ContentAggregator (thanks to Vadim
    Gritsenko for the patch).  Also fixed potential race conditions in
    the ComponentManager architecture in Avalon Excalibur.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="add">
   Integrated new StreamGenerator from Kinga Dziembowski &lt;kingadziembowska@msn.com&gt;
   Documentation is available in the webapp/docs/samples/stream/ReadMeAdd.txt (not yet converted to xdocs)
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
   Fixed ClassCastException in CommandLineEnvironment.
   Added Redirector interface to the CommandLineEnvironment to avoid class cast exceptions
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
   Fixed NPE in browser detection.
   Applied patch to the BrowserImpl. from Ovidiu Predescu (ovidiu@cup.hp.com). It
   fixes a NPE if the browser is not described.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
   The TraxTransformer resolves now the uri used inside a stylesheet (e.g. xsl:include).
   Applied the patch from Rick Tessner (rick@myra.com).
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
   SQLTransformer is now recycled properly.
   Applied patch from Ovidiu Predescu (ovidiu@cup.hp.com).
  </action>
 </release>
 <release version="Cocoon 2.0b1" date="June 7, 2001">
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
   Removed setContentHandler and setLexicalHandler from the XMLProducer interface.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
   The sitemap components now use the new SourceResolver to resolve
   resources instead of the old EntityResolver approach.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="add">
   Added a internal-only attribute to the map:pipeline element to protect them
   from being accessed by normal user request. The only way to access them by
   use of the src attribute of the map:part element or the xinclude:href of
   the XIncludeSAXConnector which implements transparent xinclude capability
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="add">
   Added a prefix attribute to both map:aggregate and map:part to have a
   namespace prefix available.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="add">
   Added an optional strip-root attribute to the map:part element of the
   map:aggregate element to indicate that the aggregator should strip off
   the root element of the aggregated content. The values can be "yes" or "true"
   to strip off and anything else to not.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="update">
   Made element attribute of map:part element in map:aggregate element optional
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="add">
   Also added substitution for test/pattern attribute.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="add">
   Implementation of content aggregation at sitemap level.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="add">
   Enable a parallel calling path into the sitemap for internal requests
   of resource.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="fix">
   Added missing methods on CommandLineRequest.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="update">
   Finished cleanup of the environment. We are now as independant of
   the javax.servlet package as possible.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
   Creating wrappers for Session and Cookie.
   The creation of these wrapper classes allow us to be independent
   of the javax.servlet classes.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Added reload-method and check-reload configuration attributes for
    the sitemap to allow asynchron/synchron sitemap reloading.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Added initial caching algorithm for StreamPipelines. The caching system
    is pluggable and offers caching of the whole response.
  </action>
  <action dev="CZ" type="add">
    Added initial caching algorithm for EventPipelines. The caching system
    is pluggable and includes caching of generators and transformers.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="remove">
    Moved ComponentManagement infrastructure to Avalon where more eyes
    can keep it working well, and it can benefit more people.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="update">
    Decoupled the RoleUtils class from the component management system.
    Implemented RoleInfo proposed by Ricardo Rocha
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="update">
    Split up ResourcePipeline into the Component EventPipeline and StreamPipeline
    and put them in the components package.
    it.
  </action>
  <action dev="RB" type="update">
    Added a TranscoderFactory for Batik, and updated the SVG Serializer to use
    it.
  </action>
  <action dev="PR" type="add">
    Added support for SAXConnectors. This is the first stage in the
    implementation of content aggregation. SAXConnectors could also
    be used for profiling and pipeline logging.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="add">
    Added form to database Actions.  Using these Actions, you can quickly
    generate a webapp that functions in _very_ little time.
  </action>
  <action dev="DM" type="update">
    Added command line code generation and compilation of XSP's and the Sitemap.
  </action>
  <action dev="DM" type="update">
    Eliminated dependency on Xalan. Updated sitemap.xsl and the Extension functions to
    work both on Xalan and SAXON. SAXON should work from version 6.2.2 onwards.
  </action>
  <action dev="DM" type="update">
    Eliminated dependency on Xerces for the serializers by using TRaX Serializers.
  </action>
 </release>
 <release version="Cocoon 2.0a3" date="March 2001">
  <action dev="BL" type="update">
    Made Cocoon load classpath independent of Servlet Engine Classpath
    Attribute.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="update">
    Changed the Xerces Specific code in the parser to JAXP 1.1 code.
    The JAXP 1.1 code will work with any compliant parser.  Unfortunately
    we still need Xerces for the serializers.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="update">
    Put meat on the Action Framework for the ManageEmployees form.
  </action>
  <action dev="RB" type="update"> 
   SVG serializer now uses Batik.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="add">
    I did a first stab at importing the util logicsheet from Cocoon 1.8.1.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="add">
    I added some simple forms that make use of the xsp-request and esql
    logicsheets.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="update">
    Clean up a lot of classloader issues.  RepositoryClassLoader is quicker and
    more stable accross installations.  ClassUtils takes care of getting resources.
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="update">
    Updated avalonapi to implement hierarchical logging, and added many more
    log entries to get a handle on where the problems lay.
  </action>
  <action dev="DB" type="add">
   added esql logicsheet to c2
  </action>
  <action dev="DB" type="fix">
   patched xsp generator to use proper namespace for automatic text elements
  </action>
  <action dev="BL" type="update">
    Updated Cocoon to be Avalon 3.0a4 compliant.  Introduced ComponentManager and
    ComponentSelector patterns correctly in code.  Updated sitemap to create
    Configuration trees directly.
  </action>
  <action dev="RB" type="add"> 
   Added a more complete SVG serializer.
  </action>
  <action dev="SM" type="update">
   Distribution cleanup and creation of a decent live demo, also to test the new sitemap.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="update">
   Major update to implement the new compiled sitemap subsystem.
  </action>
  <action dev="DB" type="update">
   Patched XSLTFilter to pass request parameters into stylesheet like cocoon1
  </action>
  <action dev="DB" type="add">
   Added ImageDirectoryGenerator - this oughta be pluggable though, so other file types can have extra attributes added easily
  </action>
  <action dev="SM" type="add"> 
   Improved the samples and the webapp sitemap.
  </action>
  <action dev="SM" type="update"> 
   Cleaned build system in order to be friendly to ASF-wide bcocoonuild procedures.
  </action>
  <action dev="SM" type="update"> 
   Updated installation section (JServ no longer supported).
  </action>
  <action dev="SM" type="update"> 
   Updated Xerces and FOP to latest versions.
  </action>
  <action dev="SM" type="fix"> 
   Patched for final SAX2 compatibility.
  </action>
  <action dev="SM" type="update" due-to="Sven K&uuml;nzler" due-to-email="svenk@tzi.org"> 
   Improved installation documentation.
  </action>
  <action dev="DB" type="add" due-to="Zvi" due-to-email="thezvi@ifrance.com">
   Patched SQLFilter so VJ++ was happy
  </action>
  <action dev="DB" type="add">
   Officially added XincludeFilter
  </action>
  <action dev="DB" type="add">
   Officially added SQLFilter
  </action>
  <action dev="SM" type="add" due-to="Sebastien Sahuc" due-to-email="ssahuc@imediation.com"> 
   Fixed order of filters that was backwards.
  </action>
  <action dev="GP" type="add">
   Fixed typo in DirectoryGenerator.
  </action>
  <action dev="SM" type="add">
   Distribution cleanup, early documentation.
  </action>
  <action dev="PF" type="add">
   Initial code implementation.
  </action>
 </release>

</changes>
