<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Contribution to Apache Cocoon</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Robin Green" email="greenrd@hotmail.com"/>
   <person name="Stefano Mazzocchi" email="stefano@apache.org"/> 
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>

 <s1 title="Introduction">

  <p>
   The Apache Cocoon Project is an <link href="http://www.opensource.org/">Open Source</link>
   volunteer project under the auspices of the
   <link href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation (ASF)</link>,
   and, in harmony with the Apache webserver itself, it is released under
   a very open license.
   This means there are many ways to contribute to the project - either
   with direct participation (coding, documenting, answering questions,
   proposing ideas, reporting bugs, suggesting bug-fixes, etc..) or by resource
   donations (money, time, publicity, hardware, software, conference
   presentations, speeches, etc...).
  </p>
  <p>
   To begin with, we suggest you to subscribe to the
   <link href="mail-lists.html">Cocoon mailing lists</link>
   (follow the link for information on how to subscribe and to access the mail
   list archives). Listen-in for a while, to hear how others make contibutions.
  </p>

  <p>You can get your local working copy of the
   <link href="http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/xml-cocoon2/">latest and
   greatest code</link> (which you find in the xml-cocoon2 module in
   the cvs.apache.org CVS code repository, or from the
   <link href="http://xml.apache.org/from-cvs/xml-cocoon2/">CVS snapshots</link>).
   Review the <link href="todo.html">todo</link> list, choose a task
   (or perhaps you have noticed something that needs patching). Make the
   changes, do the testing, generate a patch, and post to the cocoon-dev
   mailing list. (Do not worry - the process is easy and explained below.)
  </p>

  <p>
   Document writers are usually the most wanted people so if
   you like to help but you're not familiar with the innermost technical details, don't worry:
   we have work for you!
  </p>
  <p>
   For financial support in particular, the Cocoon Project and the ASF in general
   is closely collaborating with the <link href="http://www.sourcexchange.com">Collab.net
   SourceXchange</link> program that will provide a legal, solid and
   well-established resource for money collecting to fund software production
   under the open source flag. Please, feel free to contact directly
   the ASF President and Collab.net co-founder <link href="mailto:brian@collab.net">Brian
   Behlendorf</link> for more information on how to contribute financially to the
   advancement of this project.
  </p>

 </s1>

 <s1 title="Help Wanted Here">
  <p>
   The rest of this document is mainly about
   contributing new or improved code and/or documentation, but we would also be glad to have
   extra help in any of the following areas:
  </p>
  <ul>
   <li>Answering questions on the <code>cocoon-users</code> mailing list - there is often a problem of
    having too many questioners and not enough experts to respond to all the questions.</li>
   <li>Testing Cocoon (especially its less-frequently-used features) on various configurations
    and reporting back.</li>
   <li>Debugging - producing reproduceable test cases and/or finding causes of bugs. Some known bugs are informally listed on
    <link href="todo.html">To Do</link>, and some are recorded in Bugzilla
    (see <link href="#procedure">explanation below</link>).</li>
   <li>Specifying/analysing/designing new features for Cocoon - and beyond. (If you wish to get involved
    with this, please join <code>cocoon-dev@xml.apache.org</code>
    (you may also want to join <code>xsp-dev@xml.apache.org</code>), install and try out Cocoon
    and read some of the <link href="mail-lists.html">mail archives</link>.
    You should have a strong "fluency" in XML technologies, Java and a basic understanding of
    the Cocoon architecture - don't just say "it should have XYZ" without reading anything first -
    because chances are, someone's already thought of that feature!)</li>
   <li>Packaging easy-to-install packages (such as RPMs) for the myriad of possible configurations out
    there. (The Cocoon project does not maintain anything but the basic <code>.zip</code> and
    <code>.tar.gz</code> packages, but anyone is welcome to build their own specific packages and
    announce them on <code>cocoon-users</code>)</li>
   <li>... and there is just one other thing - don't forget to tell everyone who asks, how great Cocoon is! ;-)
    The more people that know about and start to use Cocoon, the larger the pool of
    potential contributors there will be
    - so, please, help us by placing the Cocoon logo somewhere in your
    site to indicate that you are using and supporting the Cocoon Project.
   </li>
  </ul>
 
  <p>
   Thank you very much. 
  </p>
  <figure src="images/cocoon2-small.jpg" alt="Powered by Cocoon"
          width="111" height="39"/>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="Contributions of Code and Documentation">
  <p>We are starting to use an informal system for accepting contributions to Cocoon.
   The process varies depending on whether the contribution is a modification (i.e. patch)
   or a fairly standalone item, and whether you have commit access (committers have been
   granted access by a vote of confidence, so they are assumed to be trustworthy enough
   to make changes directly in CVS. If you submit many good patches, you may be 
   nominated as a committer yourself!)</p>

  <p>If your contribution requires changing more than a few lines of Cocoon (code or
   documentation), then it counts as a <strong>patch</strong>. If you have a patch and
   would like to see it incorporated into the Cocoon distribution, take note of the Licensing
   Requirements listed below, and then read the section 
   <link href="#procedure">Procedure for Raising Development Issues</link>
  </p>

  <p>Otherwise (that is, if it does not require patching or you are not particularly interested in
   having it included in the main distribution), your code and/or
   documentation can be listed on the 
   <link href="3rdparty.html">Third-Party Contributions</link> page.
   The rationale for this split is that core patches may fix important issues, and may 
   require timely attention if they are not to go
   out-of-date and become useless, but other contributions can simply be downloaded and
   applied by users who wish to use them.
  </p>

  <p>A typical contribution (not a patch) may go through the following stages:</p>

  <ol>
   <li>Posted to cocoon-users with a URL to download it from.</li>
   <li>Listed on 3rdparty.html by a maintainer. [No requirements, other than relevance (at the moment).]</li>
   <li>Inclusion into the <code>contrib</code> directory,
    which is for 3rd-party contributions that have been tested, but are not necessarily
    mature enough or general enough for the main distribution. [Must be tested at least as
    specified below. See also Licensing Requirements below.]</li>
   <li>Inclusion into the main distribution. [Committers must be confident that it should work properly in 
    most/all environments, it must be documented as appropriate, and it must be considered sufficiently
    useful and general to go into Cocoon. See also  Licensing Requirements below].</li>
  </ol>
  
  <s2 title="Testing Requirements for Cocoon Contrib and Distribution">
   <p>All new code should be tested under at least the following servlet engines:</p>
   <ul>
    <li>Apache Tomcat 3.2.2</li>
   </ul>
   <p>It should also be tested on the following platforms:</p>
   <ul>
    <li>A Windows operating system</li>
    <li>A UNIX-type operating system</li>
    <li>At least JDK version 1.2.x</li>
   </ul>
   <p>And obviously, it should be tested against the current CVS snapshot of Cocoon!</p>

   <p>This testing is designed to iron out the most common kinds of incompatibility
    problems (Servlet >2.2 requirements; platform-dependent assumptions; JDK >1.2 code).
    These requirements are, of course, open to review and discussion. Note that
    the contributor is not required to do the testing - indeed it is probably better
    if someone else tests it, because the contributor might be tempted to do less
    than thorough testing!</p>
 </s2>

 <s2 title="Documentation Requirements for Cocoon Distribution">
  <p>All new features (processor, logicsheets, config options etc.) should be documented
   appropriately (in XML or in <code>cocoon.xconf</code> in the case of config options).</p>

  <p>Use something like <code>xdocs/index.xml</code> as a rough guide, add
   the new page(s) to <code>xdocs/site-book.xml</code> and <code>xdocs/docs-book.xml</code>,
   and type <code>build.sh docs</code> or <code>build.bat docs</code> to test the
   documentation build.
  </p>
 </s2>

 <s2 title="Licensing Requirements for the Cocoon Distribution">
  <p>To avoid legal problems, the Apache Project Management Committee (PMC) have agreed on
   a policy for under what licensing code can be accepted into Apache projects:</p>
  <ul>
   <li>Source code files must be under the Apache license and must have copyright assigned to
    the Apache Software Foundation.</li>
   <li>Jar files need only be released under a license that permits free redistribution
    and does not cover new files added to the jar/library (so the GPL and LGPL are not allowed,
    but MPL and Apache licenses are, for example).</li>
  </ul>
  <p><strong>By submitting a patch, you signify your understanding and acceptance of these
   conditions</strong> - like most open source projects, 
   we do not have the resources nor the inclination to obtain signed statements from all
   contributors!</p>

  <p><strong>Note:</strong> Since the <code>contrib/</code> directory of Cocoon CVS contains
   third-party. completely optional extensions, one of the above requirements is relaxed.
   Code in the contrib directory does not have to have its copyright assigned to the ASF
   - but it must still be released under the Apache license.</p>
 </s2>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="cvshowto"/>
 <s1 title="CVS Usage Precis">
  <p>An overview of how to use CVS to participate in Cocoon development.
   Do not be afraid - you cannot accidently destroy the actual code repository,
   because you are working with a local copy as an anonymous user. Therefore,
   you do not have the system permissions to change anything. You can only 
   update your local repository and compare your revisions with the real
   repository.
  </p>

  <p>
   (Further general CVS usage information is at
   <link href="http://www.cvshome.org/">www.cvshome.org</link> and your local
   <code>info cvs</code> pages or <code>man cvs</code> pages or user
   documentation.) 
  </p>

  <p>
   Let us lead by example. We will show you how to establish your local
   repository, how to keep it up-to-date, and how to generate the differences
   to create a patch. (The commands are for Linux.)
  </p>

 <s2 title="How to Establish your Local Repository">

  <p>
   This will checkout the current copy of the master cvs repository and
   download it to your local disk. It will create a sub-directory called
   <code>xml-cocoon2</code>
  </p>

  <ol>
   <li><code>cd /usr/local/cvs</code></li>
   <li><code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic login</code></li>
   <li>... use this password: <code>anoncvs</code></li>
   <li><code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic \</code>
    <br/><code>checkout xml-cocoon2</code></li>
   <li><code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic logout</code></li>
   <li><code>cd xml-cocoon2</code></li>
  </ol>

  <p>
   You now have the HEAD branch of the current development cvs repository
   for Cocoon on your local system. Go ahead and build and deploy as
   usual. Make some changes, re-build, and see the effect.
  </p>
 </s2>

 <s2 title="How to Keep it Up-to-date">

  <p>
   Every so often you should synchronise your local copy with the master
   repository. Note that this definitely does not mean that your changes
   will be applied to the master. Exactly the opposite will happen - updates
   from the remote master version are merged into your local repository.
   New items are automatically added to yours, and changed ones are refreshed.
   If someone else happened to have submitted patches for the same files while
   you were away, then changes will be merged with your copy and you will be
   warned of any conflicts. Easy and automatic ...
  </p>

  <ol>
   <li><code>cd /usr/local/cvs</code></li>
   <li><code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic login</code></li>
   <li><code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic \</code>
    <br/><code>update -d -P xml-cocoon2</code></li>
   <li><strong>... pay attention to the update messages</strong></li>
   <li><code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic logout</code></li>
  </ol>
 </s2>

 <s2 title="How to Generate Differences">

  <p>
   To contribute your modifications, you need to produce a plain-text file
   containing the differences between the master copy and yours. You will send
   this, along with an explanation of why it is required, to the 
   <code>cocoon-dev</code> mailing list. One of the authorised
   maintainers of the repository will review the patch and then apply it to the
   relevant branch.
  </p>

  <p>
   We will assume that you are adding some tips to this document
   <code>xdocs/contrib.xml</code>
  </p>

  <ol>
   <li>Make the desired changes in your local repository, build, test it
       thoroughly</li>
   <li><code>cd /usr/local/cvs/xml-cocoon2/xdocs</code></li>
   <li><code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic login</code></li>
   <li><code>cvs diff -u contrib.xml > $WORK/cocoon/contrib.xml.diff</code></li>
   <li><code>cvs -d :pserver:anoncvs@cvs.apache.org:/home/cvspublic logout</code></li>
  </ol>
 </s2>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="ssh"/>
 <s1 title="CVS Committer with Secure Shell access">
  <p>After a developer has consistently provided contributions (code,
   documentation and discussion), then the rest of the cocoon-dev community
   may vote to grant this developer commit access to CVS.
  </p>

  <p>You will need secure access to the repository to be able to commit
   patches. Here are some resources that help to get your machine configured
   to use the repository over SSH.
  </p>

  <ul>
   <li><link href="http://cvsbook.red-bean.com/">The CVS Book</link></li>
   <li><link href="http://www.cvshome.org/">www.cvshome.org</link></li>
   <li><link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/cvsindex.html"></link>
    - See the bottom of the page for links to tips for UNIX and Windows.
    Even if you are on UNIX, the Windows page will also help.</li>
  </ul>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="procedure"/>
 <s1 title="Procedure for Raising Development Issues">
  <p>
   There are two methods for discussing development and submitting patches.
   So that everyone can be productive, it is important to know which method
   is appropriate for a certain situation and how to go about it without
   confusion. This section explains when to use the 
   <code>cocoon-dev</code> <link href="mail-lists.html">mailing list</link>
   and when to use
   <link href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/">Bugzilla</link>
   (the Apache Bug Database).
  </p>

  <p>
   Research your topic thoroughly before beginning to discuss a new
   development issue. Search and browse through the email archives - your
   issue may have been discussed before. Prepare your post clearly and
   concisely.
  </p>

  <p>
   Most issues will be discovered, resolved, and then patched quickly
   via the <code>cocoon-dev</code> mailing list. Larger issues, and ones that
   are not yet fully understood or are hard to solve, are destined for
   Bugzilla.
  </p>

  <p>
   Experienced developers use Bugzilla directly, as they are very sure
   when they have found a bug and when not. However, less experienced users
   should first discuss it on the user or developer mailing list (as
   appropriate). Impatient people always enter everything into Bugzilla
   without caring if it is a bug of Cocoon or their own
   installation/configuration mistake - please do not do this.
  </p>

  <p>
   As a rule-of-thumb, discuss an issue on the <code>cocoon-dev</code>
   mailing list first to work out any details.
   After it is confirmed to be worthwhile, and you are clear about it,
   then submit the bug description via Bugzilla.
  </p>

  <p>
   When you are sure about your proposed patch, then please submit it
   via Bugzilla, rather than as email to <code>cocoon-dev</code>.
   Be sure to add [PATCH] to the summary line, as this enables the automatic
   patch alert system to keep track of it. If you do not follow this procedure,
   then unfortunately your patch may be over-looked.
  </p>

  <p>
   When posting discussion topics to the <code>cocoon-dev</code> list,
   then please be patient.
   Perhaps you do not get any answer on your first reply, so just post
   it again until you get one. (But please not every hour - allow a few
   days for the list to deal with it.) Do not be impatient - remember that
   the whole world is busy, not just you. Bear in mind that other countries
   will have holidays at different times to your country and that they are
   in different time zones. You might also consider re-writing your initial
   posting - perhaps it was not clear enough
   and the readers' eyes glazed over.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <anchor id="tips"/>
 <s1 title="Contribution Notes and Tips">
  <p>
   This is a collection of tips for contributing to the project in a manner
   that is productive for all parties.
  </p>

  <ul>
   <li>
    Every contribution is worthwhile. Even if the ensuing discussion
    proves it to be off-beam, then it may jog ideas for other people.
   </li>
   <li>
    Use sensible and concise email subject headings. Search engines, and
    humans trying to browse a voluminous list, will respond favourably to a
    descriptive title.
   </li>
   <li>Start new threads with new Subject for new topics, rather than
    re-using the previous Subject line.
   </li>
   <li>Keep each topic focussed. If some new topic arises then start a new
    discussion. This leaves the original topic to continue un-cluttered.
   </li>
   <li>Whenever you decide to start a new topic, then start with a fresh
    new email message window. Do not use the &quot;Reply to&quot; button,
    because threaded mail-readers get confused (they utilise the 
    <code>In-reply-to</code> header). If so, then your new topic will get
    lost in the previous thread and go un-answered.
   </li>
   <li>
    Prepend your email subject line with a marker when that is appropriate,
    e.g. <code>[Vote]</code>, <code>[Proposal]</code>, 
    <code>[RT]</code> (Random Thought which quickly blossom into research
    topics :-), <code>[STATUS]</code> (development status of a certain
    facility).
   </li>
   <li>
    When making changes to XML documentation, or any XML document for that
    matter, use a 
    <link href="http://www.oasis-open.org/cover/">validating parser</link>
    (one that is tried and true is
    <link href="http://openjade.sourceforge.net/">OpenSP/onsgmls</link>).
    This procedure will detect errors without having to go through the whole
    <code>build docs</code> process to find them. Do not expect Cocoon
    or the build system to detect the validation errors for you - they can
    do it, but that is not their purpose. (Anyway, onsgmls validation error
    messages are more informative.)
   </li>
   <li>
    Remember that most people are participating in development on a
    volunteer basis and in their "spare time". These enthusiasts will attempt
    to respond to issues. It may take a little while to get your answers.
   </li>
   <li>
    Research your topic thoroughly before beginning to discuss a new
    development issue. Search and browse through the email archives - your
    issue may have been discussed before. Do not just perceive a problem and
    then rush out with a question - instead, delve.
   </li>
   <li>
    Try to at least offer a partial solution and not just a problem statement.
   </li>
   <li>
    Take the time to clearly explain your issue and write a concise email
    message. Less confusion facilitates fast and complete resolution.
   </li>
   <li>
    Do not bother to send an email reply that simply says "thanks".
    When the issue is resolved, that is the finish - end of thread.
    Reduce clutter.
   </li>
   <li>
    You would usually do any development work against the HEAD branch of CVS.
   </li>
   <li>
    When sending a patch, you usually do not need to worry about which CVS
    branch it should be applied to. The maintainers of the repository will
    decide.
   </li>
   <li>
    If an issue starts to get bogged down in list discussion, then it may
    be appropriate to go into private off-list discussion with a few interested
    other people. Spare the list from the gory details. Report a summary back
    to the list to finalise the thread.
   </li>
   <li>
    Become familiar with the mailing lists. As you browse and search, you will
    see the way other people do things. Follow the leading examples.
   </li>
  </ul>
 </s1>

</body>
</document>
