<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Mailing Lists</title>
  <authors>
   <person name="Robin Green" email="greenrd@hotmail.com"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
  <s1 title="Important Notice">

   <p><strong>IMPORTANT: Before posting a question or problem to any mailing list,
    </strong>please first look at the following resources in this order:</p>
   <ol>
    <li><connect href="faq.html">FAQs</connect></li>
    <li><link href="http://dmoz.org/Computers/Data_Formats/Markup_Languages/XML/">ODP XML links</link>
     - a wealth of general XML information.</li>
    <li><connect href="mail-archives.xml">Mailing list archives</connect> - 
     a veritable goldmine of Cocoon-specific information - if you know where to look!</li>
   </ol>

   <p><strong>IMPORTANT:</strong> Careful postings please.
    These are high-volume lists, so we all needs ways to help us all
    work smarter.
    See tips for <link href="contrib.html#tips">Contributing</link>
   </p>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Cocoon Users">
   <p><link href="mailto:cocoon-users-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link>
      <link href="mailto:cocoon-users-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org">Unsubscribe</link>
   </p>

   <p>The general Cocoon list, for problems, bug reports, asking for advice on how
    best to implement a site, comparisons with other XML frameworks, etc.
    But don't forget to look in the FAQ first, please!</p>

   <p><strong>This is not an appropriate list for general XSL questions.</strong> 
    Instead
    look at the <link href="http://dmoz.org/">ODP</link> for 
    <link href="http://dmoz.org/Computers/Data_Formats/Markup_Languages/XML/">XML/XSL links</link>
    (such as the excellent <link href="http://www.zvon.org/xxl/XSLTutorial/Books/Book1/index.html">
    XSL tutorial at Zvon.org</link>) or try the 
    <link href="http://www.mulberrytech.com/xsl/">Mulberrytech XSL list</link>.</p>

   <p><strong>This is also not an appropriate list for general Java questions.</strong>
    Instead try <link href="news:comp.lang.java.help">news:comp.lang.java.help</link>
    or <link href="http://hotdispatch.com/">http://hotdispatch.com/</link>, for
    example.</p>

   <p><strong>IMPORTANT:</strong> If you are posting about a problem you are having
    (as most people do), it will aid in finding a speedy resolution if you provide
    full configuration details (especially the <strong>Cocoon version number</strong>,
    but also your operating system, JDK version, and servlet engine), and full details
    of any errors encountered (including full error messages and stack traces).</p>

   <p>Please also have some consideration for the other users on the list - this is a
    busy list and we do not appreciate getting the exact same message posted impatiently
    several times a day/week! Doing so is only likely to make your question answered more
    slowly, or not at all, not faster.</p>

   <p>If you would like to make commercial solicitations, please ask permission from
    one of the list moderators (currently <link href="mailto:greenrd@hotmail.com">
    Robin Green</link> and <link href="mailto:pati_giacomo@yahoo.com">Giacomo Pati</link>)
    <strong>prior</strong> to doing so.</p>

   <note>This list is moderated, so the first time you post, there will be a
    delay before your post is reviewed and accepted. This is to prevent spam.</note>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Cocoon Dev">
   <p><link href="mailto:cocoon-dev-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link>
      <link href="mailto:cocoon-dev-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org">Unsubscribe</link>
   </p>

   <p>This list is for developers <strong>working on</strong> or wanting to work on
    Cocoon itself (not developers merely working <strong>with</strong> Cocoon),
    for code patches to Cocoon to be posted (please use <code>diff -u</code> format),
    and for general Cocoon questions.</p>

   <p>Note this is <strong>NOT</strong> for general Cocoon questions like "Why
    isn't Cocoon working on my machine?" - 
    please ask those sorts of questions on cocoon-users (after reading the
    FAQ first, of course).</p>

   <note>This list is moderated, so the first time you post, there will be a
    delay before your post is reviewed and accepted. This is to prevent spam.</note>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Cocoon Cvs">
   <p><link href="mailto:cocoon-cvs-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link>
      <link href="mailto:cocoon-cvs-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org">Unsubscribe</link>
   </p>

   <p>This <strong>read-only</strong> list sends out notification messages detailing
    any change made to the CVS repository where all the source code and libraries
    are stored for development purposes. The average user probably doesn't need to
    subscribe to this list.</p>

   <note>You should never post to this list at all. Only the
    CVS server should post to it.</note>

  </s1>

  <s1 title="XSP Dev">
   <p><link href="mailto:xsp-dev-subscribe@xml.apache.org">Subscribe</link>
     <link href="mailto:xsp-dev-unsubscribe@xml.apache.org">Unsubscribe</link>
   </p>

   <p>This list began life on November 2000, and was created to discuss the
    standardisation and implementation of the dynamic content language XSP,
    which is used not only in Cocoon but in other software such as AxKit.
    You are recommended to have a strong working knowledge of XSP before joining
    this list.</p>

   <p>Note this is <strong>NOT</strong> for general XSP questions like
    "Why doesn't my XSP page work?" - please ask those sorts of questions on
    the relevant list for your XSP software (e.g. cocoon-users if you're using
    Cocoon) - after checking the FAQ first of course!
   </p>
  </s1>

  <s1 title="Related Mailing Lists">

   <p>(See also <link href="http://dmoz.org/Computers/Data_Formats/Markup_Languages/XML/">
    ODP XML links</link> for related websites.)</p>
   <ul>
    <li><link href="http://www.mulberrytech.com/xsl/">Mulberrytech XSL list</link> -
      more appropriate than Cocoon Users for general XSL questions.</li>
    <li><link href="http://xml.apache.org/mail.html">XML Apache Projects</link> -
      list of mailing lists for all the projects on xml.apache.org.</li>
    <li>Some servlet engines have their own mailing lists for servlet-engine
     configuration questions, such as
     <link href="mailto:tomcat-user-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">tomcat-user</link> (note it is "user"
     and not "users").</li>
   </ul>
  </s1>
 </body>
</document>
