<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
  <header>
	 <title>Avalon for Apache Cocoon</title>
	 <version>0.2</version>
	 <type>Technical document</type>
	 <authors>
		<person name="Tom Klaasen" email="tom.klaasen@the-ecorp.com"/>
		<person name="Berin Loritsch" email="bloritsch@apache.org"/>
		<person name="Carsten Ziegeler" email="cziegeler@apache.org"/>
	 </authors>
	 <abstract>This document tries to give the basic knowledge of Avalon that is
		necessary to understand Apache Cocoon.</abstract>
  </header>
  <body>
	 <s1 title="Goal">
		<p>This document tries to give the basic knowledge of Avalon that is
		  necessary to understand Cocoon.</p>
		<p>People that are trying to understand Avalon in depth, will probably
		  not be much helped by this document. But if you want to understand Cocoon,
		  you have to have a basic grasp of Avalon. </p>
		<p>The document also contains the basic configuration steps for
               configuring Avalon components within Cocoon.</p>
		<p>Much of this document is copied and pasted from original Avalon
		  documentation. However, I hope that the fact that all things relevant for
		  Cocoon are put together in one place, will help you to understand Cocoon
		  faster.</p>
		<p>For people wishing to learn Avalon in-depth,
		  <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/developing/index.html">this is your starting
		point</link>.</p>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="Overview">
		<p>For a mission statement of Apache Avalon, please read
		  <link href="http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/index.html">the Avalon
		homepage</link>.</p>
		<p>In short, Avalon tries to take design efforts away from server-side
		  programmers by providing a framework that </p>
		<ul>
		  <li>provides basic working classes;</li>
		  <li>provides interfaces to allow different efforts to be integrated
			 more easily.</li>
		</ul>
	 </s1>
	 <s1 title="The classes and interfaces"> 
		<p>These classes and interfaces are extensively used by Cocoon:</p>
		<s2 title="ComponentManager">
		  <p><code>org.apache.avalon.framework.component.ComponentManager</code></p>
		  <p>A <code>ComponentManager</code> selects <code>Component</code>s
			 based on a role. The contract is that all the <code>Component</code>s implement
			 the differing roles and there is one <code>Component</code> per role. If you
			 need to select on of many <code>Component</code>s that implement the same role,
			 then you need to use a <code>ComponentSelector</code>. Roles are the full
			 interface name.</p>
		  <p>A role is better understood by the analogy of a play. There are many
			 different roles in a script. Any actor or actress can play any given part and
			 you get the same results (phrases said, movements made, etc.), but the exact
			 nuances of the performance is different.</p>
		  <p>The <code>Cocoon</code> class implements e.g. the
			 <code>ComponentManager</code> interface.</p>
		</s2>
		<s2 title="Composable">
		  <p><code>org.apache.avalon.framework.component.Composable</code></p>
		  <p>A <code>Composer</code> is a class that need to connect to software
			 components using a "role" abstraction, thus not depending on particular
			 implementations but on behavioral interfaces. </p>
		</s2>
		<s2 title="Component">
		  <p><code>org.apache.avalon.framework.component.Component</code></p>
		  <p>This interface identifies classes that can be used as
			 <code>Components</code> by a <code>Composer</code>. </p>
		  <p>A <code>Component</code> is the basic building block of Avalon. When
			 a class implements this interface, it allows itself to be managed by a
			 <code>ComponentManager</code> and used by an outside element called a
			 <code>Composer</code>. The <code>Composer</code> must know what type of
			 <code>Component</code> it is accessing, so it will re-cast the
			 <code>Component</code> into the type it needs. </p>
		  <p><code>Component</code>s in Cocoon are e.g. those defined in
			 <code>cocoon.xconf</code>.</p>
		</s2>
		<s2 title="Configuration">
		  <p><code>org.apache.avalon.framework.configuration.Configuration</code></p>
		  <p><code>Configuration</code> is a interface encapsulating a
			 configuration node used to retrieve configuration values. This is a "read only"
			 interface preventing applications from modifying their own configurations. The
			 contract surrounding the <code>Configuration</code> is that once it is created,
			 information never changes. The <code>Configuration</code> is built by the
			 <code>ConfigurationBuilder</code>.</p>
		</s2>
		<s2 title="Configurable">
		  <p><code>org.apache.avalon.framework.configuration.Configurable</code></p>
		  <p><code>Configurable</code> is a interface describing a component which
                  can be configured. This component gets a <code>Configuration</code>
                  object as input.</p>
		</s2>
		<s2 title="ConfigurationBuilder">
		  <p><code>org.apache.avalon.ConfigurationBuilder</code></p>
		  <p>A <code>ConfigurationBuilder</code> builds
			 <code>Configuration</code>s.</p>
		</s2>
	 </s1>
	<s1 title="Configuration">
		<p>Most available Avalon components are configured in the cocoon.xconf.</p>
		<s2 title="Pooling configuration">
			<p>Avalon now incorporates a couple of modifiers for a Component
			definition that allows you to control the number of Components
			in a pool, and how quickly it grows.  This is especially helpful
			in Cocoon where the defaults don't always work well.</p>
			<p>The magic attributes are "pool-min", "pool-max", and "pool-grow".
			The defaults are:</p>
			<ol>
				<li>pool-max: 8</li>
				<li>pool-min: 2</li>
				<li>pool-grow: pool-min  (2)</li>
			</ol>
			<p>What this means is that the pool for the default component initially
			contains 2 instances, and if demand exceeds that the pool will increase
			by two components at a time up to 8 instances.  Beyond that the pool
			turns into a factory in that new Component instances are created, but
			destroyed when they are returned.  This is a performance issue--but
			it does manage the number of instances available at one time.</p>
			<p>Please note that if
			not specified, "pool-grow" always matches "pool-min".  If not specified
			"pool-min" always equals "2".  If you specify the minimum being higher
			than the maximum, then the maximum will match the minimum, and the pool
			will be fully filled on initialization.</p>
		</s2>
	</s1>
  </body>
</document>
