<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>Extending Apache Cocoon</title>
		<version>0.1</version>
		<type>Technical document</type>
		<authors>
			<person name="Tom Klaasen" email="tom.klaasen@the-ecorp.com"/>
		</authors>
	</header>
	<body>
		<s1 title="Introduction">
			<p>If you want to extend the functionality of Apache Cocoon, it may be unclear
		  how to achieve your goal. This page tries to indicate when to write what, and
		  to give an overview of what already exists (so you don't duplicate other's
		  efforts).</p>
		</s1>
		<s1 title="When to write a Generator">
			<p>From the sitemap documentation: "A <code>Generator</code> generates
		  XML content as SAX events and initializes the pipeline processing. "</p>
			<p>Thus a <code>Generator</code> is the starting point of a pipeline: it
		  produces the first SAX events on which all other components of the pipeline are
		  triggered.</p>
			<p>You may want to write a <code>Generator</code> if you want some other
		  basis for your SAX events (maybe you want a SAX event every time the
		  temperature of your CPU changes?) However, before writing a
		  <code>Generator</code> from scratch, it may be worthwhile to have a look at
		  <link href="#xsp">XSP</link>, which can create a <code>Generator</code> for
		you.</p>
			<p>Existing <code>Generator</code>s are: </p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<code>DirectoryGenerator</code> - Generates an XML directory
			 listing.</li>
				<li>
					<code>FileGenerator</code> - Does the job of an XML parser: read an
			 XML file and outputs SAX events.</li>
				<li>
					<code>HTMLGenerator</code> - Takes an HTML URL, makes an XHTML of
			 it, and outputs the SAX events caused by this XHTML.</li>
				<li>
					<code>ImageDirectoryGenerator</code> - An extension of
			 DirectoryGenerators that adds extra attributes for image files. </li>
				<li>
					<code>PhpGenerator</code> - Allows PHP to be used as a generator.
			 Builds upon the PHP servlet functionality. Overrides the output method in
			 order to pipe the results into SAX events.</li>
				<li>
					<code>RequestGenerator</code> - [FIXME: This looks like just
			 outputing the request headers, the request parameters and the configuration
			 parameters. But I don't see any use of it (besides debugging and
			 demonstration). Are there other situations in which you might want to use
			 this?]</li>
				<li>
					<code>ServerPagesGenerator</code> - Makes a <code>Generator</code>
			 at compile time, based on the <code>src</code> file you define in the sitemap.
			 This one is responsible for making your XSP pages work.</li>
				<li>
					<code>StatusGenerator</code> - Generates an XML representation of
			 the current status of Cocoon. This can be considered "for administration use",
			 i.e. your application probably won't deal with this one.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>All these classes are in the <code>org.apache.cocoon.generation</code>
		  package. In the same package, you find following helper classes and
		  interfaces:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<code>Generator</code> - The interface you have to implement if you
			 want to write a <code>Generator</code>.</li>
				<li>
					<code>AbstractGenerator</code> - Extend this one for easier
			 building of your own <code>Generator</code>.</li>
				<li>
					<code>AbstractServerPage</code> - [FIXME: This seems to be intended
			 as basis for the <code>ServerPagesGenerator</code>, but it seems to be obsolete
			 now?]</li>
				<li>
					<code>ComposerGenerator</code> - Can be used as base class if you
			 want your <code>Generator</code> to be an <link href="avalon.html">Avalon
		Composer</link>.</li>
				<li>
					<code>ServletGenerator</code> - If you want to generate servlets.
		  This is the base class for the <code>ServerPagesGenerator</code>.</li>
			</ul>
		</s1>
		<s1 title="When to write a Transformer">
			<p>Let's start again from the sitemap documentation: "A
		  <code>Transformer</code> transforms SAX events in SAX events." In other words,
		  a <code>Transformer</code> outputs SAX events based on SAX events it
		  receives.</p>
			<p>You can imagine a <code>Transformer</code> doing many things, from
		  XSLT processing over database querying to sending mail (and much further, of
		  course).</p>
			<p>These <code>Transformer</code>s are standard available:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<code>LogTransformer</code> - This is a class that can be plugged
			 into a pipeline to print the SAX events which passes through this
			 <code>Transformer</code> in a readable form to a file. This
			 <code>Transformer</code>'s main purpose is debugging.</li>
				<li>
					<code>SQLTransformer</code> - Can be used for querying a SQL
			 database.</li>
				<li>
					<code>XalanTransformer</code> - Probably the most intuitive
			 <code>Transformer</code>: it applies an XSL sheet to the SAX events it
			 receives. It uses Xalan in the process.</li>
				<li>
					<code>XIncludeTransformer</code> - To include other XML documents
			 in your "XML document" (which at transformation time exists in SAX
			 events).</li>
				<li>
					<code>XTTransformer</code> - The same as
			 <code>XalanTransformer</code>, but this one uses XT.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>All these classes can be found in
		  <code>org.apache.cocoon.transformation</code>, along with these helper classes
		  and interfaces:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<code>Transformer</code> - The interface each Transformer has to
			 implement.</li>
				<li>
					<code>AbstractTransformer</code> - A helper base class for
			 implementing a <code>Transformer</code>.</li>
				<li>
					<code>AbstractDOMTransformer</code> - An Abstract DOM Transformer
			 (helper base class), for use when a transformer needs a DOM-based view of the
			 document.</li>
			</ul>
		</s1>
		<s1 title="When to write a Serializer">
			<p>No need for re-inventing the wheel, so let's start again with the
		  sitemap documentation: "A <code>Serializer</code> transforms SAX events in
		  binary or char streams for final client consumption." A <code>Serializer</code>
		  is always the last step in a pipeline, and gives the client its final result:
		  an HTML page, a nice PNG picture, a sound stream, or maybe just an XML
		  document.</p>
			<p>You should write a <code>Serializer</code> if you want to serve a  client with some format that hasn't been provided yet.</p>
			<p>Existing <code>Serializer</code>s:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<code>FOPSerializer</code>- Make PDF files.</li>
				<li>
					<code>HTMLSerializer</code> - Generate an HTML document.</li>
				<li>
					<code>LinkSerializer</code>- Show the targets of the links in the document.</li>
				<li>
					<code>SVGSerializer</code>- To construct an SVG.</li>
				<li>
					<code>TextSerializer</code> - Generate a text document.</li>
				<li>
					<code>XMLSerializer</code> - Generate an XML document.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>Again, these can be found in the package <code>org.apache.cocoon.serialization</code>. And this package also includes following interfaces and helper classes:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<code>Serializer</code> - The interface every <code>Serializer</code> has to implement.</li>
				<li>
					<code>AbstractTextSerializer</code> - Use this as base for your <code>Serializer</code> if you want to output a character stream.</li>
				<li>
					<code>AbstractSerializer</code> - A more general base class.</li>
			</ul>
		</s1>
		<s1 title="About Action">
			<p>[FIXME: We have to wait until we can see what is going to happen here. Also, I wonder if this belongs here or should deserve a separate page.]</p>
			<p>The Action part will be used for making Cocoon able to react on form input. This will make Cocoon no longer a simple basis for web publishing, but will make it apt for web interaction as well.</p>
		</s1>
		<s1 title="About XSP">
			<anchor id="xsp"/>
			<p>XSP stands for "eXtensible Server Pages". It is the idea to program <code>Generator</code>s by means of XML. The basic idea is to put XML tags like <code><![CDATA[<xsp:logic>]]></code> in your XML file, with in those tags Java code.</p>
			<note>This is not the proper way to use XSP's. I just mentioned them here so you wouldn't forget their existence. Look to the <link href="../userdocs/xsp/xsp.html">XSP page</link> for more information.</note>
		</s1>
	</body>
</document>
