<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document>

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <title>The Manager Component</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Introduction">

  <p>The <strong>Manager</strong> element represents the <em>session
  manager</em> that will be used to create and maintain HTTP sessions
  as requested by the associated web application.</p>

  <p>A Manager element MAY be nested inside a
  <a href="context.html">Context</a> component.  If it is not included,
  a default Manager configuration will be created automatically, which
  is sufficient for most requirements.</p>

</section>


<section name="Attributes">

  <subsection name="Common Attributes">

    <p>All implementations of <strong>Manager</strong>
    support the following attributes:</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="className" required="false">
        <p>Java class name of the implementation to use.  This class must
        implement the <code>org.apache.catalina.Manager</code> interface.
        If not specified, the standard value (defined below) will be used.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="distributable" required="false">
        <p>Set to <code>true</code> to ask the session manager to enforce
        the restrictions described in the Servlet Specification on
        distributable applications (primarily, this would mean that all
        session attributes must implement <code>java.io.Serializable</code>).
        Set to <code>false</code> (the default) to not enforce these
        restrictions.</p>

        <p><strong>NOTE</strong> - The value for this property is inherited
        automatically based on the presence or absence of the
        <code>&lt;distributable&gt;</code> element in the web application
        deployment descriptor (<code>/WEB-INF/web.xml</code>).</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="maxInactiveInterval" required="false">
        <p>The default maximum inactive interval (in minutes) for Sessions
        created by this Manager.  If not specified, the default value is
        sixty (60) minutes.</p>

        <p><strong>NOTE</strong> - The value for this property is inherited
        automatically if you specify a <code>&lt;session-timeout&gt;</code>
        element in the web application deployment descriptor
        (<code>/WEB-INF/web.xml</code>).</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>

  </subsection>


  <subsection name="Standard Implementation">

    <p>The standard implementation of <strong>Manager</strong> is
    <strong>org.apache.catalina.session.StandardManager</strong>.
    It supports the following additional attributes (in addition to the
    common attributes listed above):</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="algorithm" required="false">
        <p>Name of the <em>Message Digest</em> algorithm used to calculate
        session identifiers produced by this Manager.  This value must
        be supported by the <code>java.security.MessageDigest</code> class.
        If not specified, the default value is "MD5".</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="checkInterval" required="false">
        <p>The number of seconds between checks for expired sessions
        for this manager.  The default value is 60 seconds.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="debug" required="false">
        <p>The level of debugging detail logged by this <strong>Engine</strong>
        to the associated <a href="logger.html">Logger</a>.  Higher numbers
        generate more detailed output.  If not specified, the default
        debugging detail level is zero (0).</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="entropy" required="false">
        <p>A String value that is utilized when seeding the random number
        generator used to create session identifiers for this Manager.
        If not specified, a semi-useful value is calculated, but a long
        String value should be specified in security-conscious
        environments.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="maxActiveSessions" required="false">
        <p>The maximum number of active sessions that will be created by
        this Manager, or -1 (the default) for no limit.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="pathname" required="false">
        <p>Absolute or relative (to the work directory for this Context)
        pathname of the file in which session state will be preserved
        across application restarts, if possible.  The default is
        "SESSIONS.ser".  See <a href="#Restart Persistence">Restart
        Persistence</a> for more information.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="randomClass" required="false">
        <p>Java class name of the <code>java.util.Random</code>
        implementation class to use.  If not specified, the default value is
        <code>java.security.SecureRandom</code>.</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>

  </subsection>


</section>


<section name="Nested Components">

  <p>No components may be nested inside a <strong>Manager</strong> element.</p>

</section>


<section name="Special Features">


  <subsection name="Restart Persistence">

    <p>Whenver Catalina is shut down normally and restarted, or when an
    application reload is triggered, the standard Manager implementation
    will attempt to serialize all currently active sessions to a disk
    file located via the <code>pathname</code> attribute.  All such saved
    sessions will then be deserialized and activated (assuming they have
    not expired in the mean time) when the application reload is completed.</p>

    <p>In order to successfully restore the state of session attributes,
    all such attributes MUST implement the <code>java.io.Serializable</code>
    interface.  You MAY cause the Manager to enforce this restriction by
    including the <code>&lt;distributable&gt;</code> element in your web
    application deployment descriptor (<code>/WEB-INF/web.xml</code>).</p>

  </subsection>

</section>


</body>


</document>
