<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document>

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <title>The Realm Component</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Introduction">

  <p>A <strong>Realm</strong> element represents a "database" of usernames,
  passwords, and <em>roles</em> (similar to Unix <em>groups</em>) assigned
  to those users.  Different implementations of Realm allow Catalina to be
  integrated into environments where such authentication information is already
  being created and maintained, and then utilize that information to implement
  <em>Container Managed Security</em> as described in the Servlet
  Specification.</p>

  <p>You may nest a Realm inside any Catalina container
  <a href="engine.html">Engine</a>, <a href="host.html">Host</a>, or
  <a href="context.html">Context</a>).  In addition, Realms associated with
  an Engine or a Host are automatically inherited by lower-level
  containers, unless explicitly overridden.</p>

  <p>For more in-depth information about container managed security in web
  applications, see <strong>FIXME - link to "Container Managed Security Guide"
  in the application developer's section</strong>.  For more in-depth
  information about configuing and using the standard Realm component
  implementations, see <strong>FIXME - link to "Realm Configuration HOW-TO"
  in the administrator's section</strong>.</p>

    <blockquote><em>
    <p>The description below uses the variable name $CATALINA_HOME
    to refer to the directory into which you have installed Tomcat 4,
    and is the base directory against which most relative paths are
    resolved.  However, if you have configured Tomcat 4 for multiple
    instances by setting a CATALINA_BASE directory, you should use
    $CATALINA_BASE instead of $CATALINA_HOME for each of these
    references.</p>
    </em></blockquote>

</section>


<section name="Attributes">

  <subsection name="Common Attributes">

    <p>All implementations of <strong>Realm</strong>
    support the following attributes:</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="className" required="true">
        <p>Java class name of the implementation to use.  This class must
        implement the <code>org.apache.catalina.Realm</code> interface.</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>

  </subsection>


  <subsection name="Standard Implementation">

    <p>Unlike most Catalina components, there are several standard
    <strong>Realm</strong> implementations available.  As a result,
    the <code>className</code> attribute MUST be used to select the
    implementation you wish to use.</p>

    <h3>JDBC Database Realm (org.apache.catalina.realm.JDBCRealm)</h3>

    <p>The <strong>JDBC Database Realm</strong> connects Catalina to
    a relational database, accessed through an appropriate JDBC driver,
    to perform lookups of usernames, passwords, and their associated
    roles.  Because the lookup is done each time that it is required,
    changes to the database will be immediately reflected in the
    information used to authenticate new logins.</p>

    <p>A rich set of additional attributes lets you configure the required
    connection to the underlying database, as well as the table and
    column names used to retrieve the required information:</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="connectionName" required="true">
        <p>The database username to use when establishing the JDBC
        connection.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="connectionPassword" required="true">
        <p>The database password to use when establishing the JDBC
        connection.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="connectionURL" required="true">
        <p>The connection URL to be passed to the JDBC driver when
        establishing a database connection.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="digest" required="false">
        <p>The name of the <code>MessageDigest</code> algorithm used
        to encode user passwords stored in the database.  If not specified,
        user passwords are assumed to be stored in clear-text.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="driverName" required="true">
        <p>Fully qualified Java class name of the JDBC driver to be
        used to connect to the authentication database.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="roleNameCol" required="true">
        <p>Name of the column, in the "user roles" table, which contains
        a role name assigned to the corresponding user.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="userCredCol" required="true">
        <p>Name of the column, in the "users" table, which contains
        the user's credentials (i.e. password(.  If a value for the
        <code>digest</code> attribute is specified, this component
        will assume that the passwords have been encoded with the
        specified algorithm.  Otherwise, they will be assumed to be
        in clear text.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="userNameCol" required="true">
        <p>Name of the column, in the "users" and "user roles" table,
        that contains the user's username.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="userRoleTable" required="true">
        <p>Name of the "user roles" table, which must contain columns
        named by the <code>userNameCol</code> and <code>roleNameCol</code>
        attributes.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="userTable" required="true">
        <p>Name of the "users" table, which must contain columns named
        by the <code>userNameCol</code> and <code>userCredCol</code>
        attributes.</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>

    <p>See <strong>FIXME - Nested pointer into HOW-TO</strong> for more
    information on setting up container managed security using the
    JDBC Database Realm component.</p>


    <h3>JNDI Directory Realm (org.apache.catalina.realm.JNDIRealm)</h3>


    <p>The <strong>JNDI Directory Realm</strong> connects Catalina to
    an LDAP Directory, accessed through an appropriate JNDI driver,
    to perform lookups of usernames, passwords, and their associated
    roles.  Because the lookup is done each time that it is required,
    changes to the directory will be immediately reflected in the
    information used to authenticate new logins.</p>

    <p>A rich set of additional attributes lets you configure the required
    connection to the underlying directory, as well as the element and
    attribute names used to retrieve the required information:</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="connectionName" required="true">
        <p>The directory username to use when establishing the JNDI
        connection.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="connectionPassword" required="true">
        <p>The directory password to use when establishing the JNDI
        connection.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="connectionURL" required="true">
        <p>The connection URL to be passed to the JNDI driver when
        establishing a connection to the directory.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="contextFactory" required="false">
        <p>Fully qualified Java class name of the factory class used
        to acquire our JNDI <code>InitialContext</code>.  By default,
        assumes that the standard JNDI LDAP provider will be utilized.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="roleBase" required="true">
        <p>The base directory element for performing role searches.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="roleName" required="true">
        <p>The name of the directory attribute to retrieve when selecting
        the assigned roles for a user.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="roleSearch" required="true">
        <p>The LDAP search expression to use when selecting roles for a
        particular user, with <code>{0}</code> marking where the actual
        username should be inserted.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="roleSubtree" required="true">
        <p>Set to <code>true</code> to search subtrees of the elements
        selected by the <code>roleSearch</code> search expression.  Set
        to <code>false</code> to not search subtrees.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="userPassword" required="true">
        <p>Name of the LDAP element containing the user's password.</p>
      </attribute>

      <attribute name="userPattern" required="true">
        <p>The LDAP search expression to use when retrieving the attributes
        of a particular user, with <code>{0}</code> marking where the
        actual username should be inserted.</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>

    <p>See <strong>FIXME - Nested pointer into HOW-TO</strong> for more
    information on setting up container managed security using the
    JNDI Directory Realm component.</p>


    <h3>Memory Based Realm (org.apache.catalina.realm.MemoryRealm)</h3>

    <p>The <strong>Memory Based Realm</strong> is a simple Realm implementation
    that reads user information from an XML format, and represents it as a
    collection of Java objects in memory.  This implementation is intended
    solely to get up and running with container managed security - it is NOT
    intended for production use.  As such, there are no mechanisms for
    updating the in-memory collection of users when the content of the
    underlying data file is changed.</p>

    <p>The Memory Based Realm implementation supports the following
    additional attributes:</p>

    <attributes>

      <attribute name="pathname" required="false">
        <p>Absolute or relative (to $CATALINA_HOME) pathname to the XML file
        containing our user information.  See below for details on the
        XML element format required.  If no pathname is specified, the
        default value is <code>conf/tomcat-users.xml</code>.</p>
      </attribute>

    </attributes>

    <p>The XML document referenced by the <code>pathname</code> attribute must
    conform to the following requirements:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>The root (outer) element must be <code>&lt;tomcat-users&gt;</code>.
        </li>
    <li>Each authorized user must be represented by a single XML element
        <code>&lt;user&gt;</code>, nested inside the root element.</li>
    <li>Each <code>&lt;user&gt;</code> element must have the following
        attributes:
        <ul>
        <li><strong>name</strong> - Username of this user (must be unique
            within this file).</li>
        <li><strong>password</strong> - Password of this user (in
            clear text).</li>
        <li><strong>roles</strong> - Comma-delimited list of the role names
            assigned to this user.</li>
        </ul></li>
    </ul>

    <p>See <strong>FIXME - Nested pointer into HOW-TO</strong> for more
    information on setting up container managed security using the
    Memory Based Realm component.</p>


  </subsection>


</section>


<section name="Nested Components">

  <p>No components may be nested inside a <strong>Realm</strong> element.</p>

</section>


<section name="Special Features">

  <p>See <a href="host.html">Single Sign On</a> for information about
  configuring Single Sign On support for a virtual host.</p>

</section>


</body>


</document>
