<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document>

  &project;

  <properties>
    <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
    <title>The WARP Connector</title>
  </properties>

<body>


<section name="Introduction">

  <p>The <strong>WARP Connector</strong> element represents a
  <strong>Connector</strong> component that communicates with a web
  connector via the <code>WARP</code> protocol.  This is used for cases
  where you wish to invisibly integrate Tomcat 4 into an existing (or new)
  Apache installation, and you want Apache to handle the static content
  contained in the web application, and/or utilize Apache's SSL
  processing.  In many application environments, this will result in
  better overall performance than running your applications under
  Tomcat stand-alone using the
  <a href="http11.html">HTTP/1.1 Connector</a>.  However, the only way
  to know for sure whether it will provide better performance for
  <strong>your</strong> application is to try it both ways.</p>

  <p><strong>FIXME</strong> - general description of what happens at server
  startup time when you have the WARP Connector configured.</p>

</section>


<section name="Attributes">

  <subsection name="Common Attributes">

  <p>All implementations of <strong>Connector</strong>
  support the following attributes:</p>

  <attributes>

    <attribute name="className" required="true">
      <p>Java class name of the implementation to use.  This class must
      implement the <code>org.apache.catalina.Connector</code> interface.
      You must specify the standard value defined below.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="enableLookups" required="false">
      <p>Set to <code>true</code> if you want calls to
      <code>request.getRemoteHost()</code> to perform DNS lookups in
      order to return the actual host name of the remote client.  Set
      to <code>false</code> to skip the DNS lookup and return the IP
      address in String form instead (thereby improving performance).
      By default, DNS lookups are enabled.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="redirectPort" required="false">
      <p>If this <strong>Connector</strong> is supporting non-SSL
      requests, and a request is received for which a matching
      <code>&lt;security-constraint&gt;</code> requires SSL transport,
      Catalina will automatically redirect the request to the port
      number specified here.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="scheme" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to the name of the protocol you wish to have
      returned by calls to <code>request.getScheme()</code>.  For
      example, you would set this attribute to "<code>https</code>"
      for an SSL Connector.  The default value is "<code>http</code>".
      See <a href="#SSL Support">SSL Support</a> for more information.</p>
    </attribute>

    <attribute name="secure" required="false">
      <p>Set this attribute to <code>true</code> if you wish to have
      calls to <code>request.isSecure()</code> to return <code>true</code>
      for requests received by this Connector (you would want this on an
      SSL Connector).  The default value is <code>false</code>.</p>
    </attribute>

  </attributes>

  <p><strong>FIXME</strong> - Update the above descriptions for anything
  that the WARP Connector delegates to Apache.</p>

  </subsection>

  <subsection name="Standard Implementation">

  <p>The standard implementation of <strong>WARP Connector</strong> is
  <strong>org.apache.catalina.connector.warp.WarpConnector</strong>.
  It supports the following additional attributes (in addition to the
  common attributes listed above):</p>

  <attributes/>

  <p><strong>FIXME</strong> - Document any additional configuration attributes
  supported by the WARP connector.</p>

  </subsection>

</section>


<section name="Nested Components">

  <p><strong>FIXME</strong> - Document any use of a nested <code>Factory</code>
  element for communicating with <code>mod_webapp</code> over SSL.</p>

</section>


<section name="Special Features">

  <p><strong>FIXME</strong> - Document any special features supported by the
  WARP Connector.</p>

</section>


</body>

</document>
