<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
 <header>
  <title>Entity Catalogs - the Entity Resolver</title>
  <subtitle>Planning Documentation</subtitle>
  <authors>
   <person name="David Crossley" email="crossley@apache.org"/>
  </authors>
 </header>

 <body>
 <s1 title="Overview">

  <p>The entity resolution capability is recently implemented at the Cocoon
   level. However, this capability is required for all XML Apache projects.
   So its base implementation should be moved to Avalon Excalibur.
  </p>

  <p>Everytime that an XML parser is used, it needs to have the resolver
   attached via the <code>setEntityResolver()</code> method.
  </p>

  <p>Cocoon and other projects need to be able to configure the resolver to
   specify additional catalogs and to set the verbosity level for the log
   messages.
  </p>

  <p>For background see the main Cocoon documentation for
   <link href="../userdocs/concepts/catalog.html">Entity Catalogs</link>.
  </p>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="Current implementation with Cocoon">

 <s2 title="Configuration">
  <ul>
   <li><code>cocoon.roles</code> defines role for Resolver</li>
   <li><code>cocoon.xconf</code> set parameters for Resolver</li>
   <li><code>CatalogManager.properties</code> additional config method</li>
  </ul>
 </s2>

 <s2 title="Components">
  <ul>
   <li><code>src/org/apache/cocoon/components/resolver/ResolverImpl.java</code>
    implements the Sun &quot;XML Entity and URI Resolvers&quot;
    <ul>
     <li>Gets a new CatalogResolver() which reads the default
      <code>CatalogManager.properties</code> to set some properties for
      local site config and load some local catalogs</li>
     <li>Applies any parameters that may have been specified in cocoon.xconf
      (e.g. verbosity)</li>
     <li>Loads the Cocoon system catalog (which resolves all the DTDs
      and entity sets that are used by Cocoon)</li>
     <li>Loads any additional local catalogs that may have been specified in
      <code>cocoon.xconf</code></li>
     <li>Allows the application to resolve external entities via resolveEntity().</li>
    </ul>
   </li>
   <li><code>setEntityResolver()</code> for any parser that is used ... JaxpParser, XercesParser, PoolJaxpParser, XSLTProcessorImpl, (are there others?)</li>
   <li></li>
  </ul>
 </s2>

 <s2 title="Default Entities and Catalogs">
  <ul>
   <li><code>webapp/resources/entities/</code> holds all of the DTDs and
    character entity sets currently used by Cocoon. These would also form a
    base for any userland application (they can configure their own additional
    entities).
   </li>
   <li>There are historical copies of all entities at
    <code>documentation/xdocs/dtd/</code> (this is the default location
    declared as <code>systemId</code> in each XML document). An open issue is
    whether to leave them there as a belt-and-braces mechanism, or to rely
    completely on the entity resolver.</li>
   <li>The Cocoon system catalog is an OASIS plain-text catalog declaring
    all of the necessary entities
    <code>webapp/resources/entities/catalog</code>
   </li>
  </ul>

 </s2>
 </s1>

 <s1 title="Moving to Avalon">

<note>TODO: describe overview of issues.</note>

 </s1>

 <s1 title="Other Notes">
  <p> cocoon-dev 2001-11-09 (Identifying Components for Avalon)
... It would be reasonable for there to be an ExcaliburResolver,
and a CocoonResolver that both extend the same interface.
In fact, it would be reasonable for the CocoonResolver to
extend the ExcaliburResolver.
  </p>

  <p>The term &quot;resolver&quot; is used in many different ways by Cocoon.
   So perhaps a better name would be CocoonEntityResolver or CocoonCatalogResolver.
  </p>

  <p>Which other Apache projects are using the DTDs that are in Cocoon CVS?
   Some will need to move to Excalibur, Cocoon-specific ones will remain.
  </p>

 </s1>

 <s1 title="Some useful discussion threads">

  <ul>
   <li>Cocoon distribution + Resolver Resolution ? (avalon-dev 2001-11-12)
    discusses licencing issues and moving to Avalon</li>
  </ul>
 </s1>

 </body>
</document>
