<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
	<header>
		<title>The SVG Serializer</title>
		<authors>
			<person name="Ross Burton" email="rossb@apache.org"/>
		</authors>
	</header>
	
	<body>
		<s1 title="SVG Serializer">
			<s2 title="Introduction">
				<p>
					The SVG Serializer is an advanced serializer which accepts
					valid Scalable Vector Graphic documents (currently to the
					2000-08-02 Candidate Recommendation specification) and
					renders it to an image which is served just like any other
					document in Cocoon.
				</p>
				<p>
					Why would you want to do this? Well, charts can be produced from the
					same data which generates tables, graphical images with text labels
					all following a standard theme can be generated or normal pages can be
					beautified.
				</p>
				<note>
					For examples of this serializer, see the Cocoon welcome
					page in the distribution (<code>[cocoon
					root]/welcome</code>).
				</note>
				<p>
					So how does this serializer work?
				</p>
				<ol>
					<li>Parse and validate SVG document</li>
					<li>Call Batik's <code>Transcoder</code> to encode this image as an image file, and return it to the user.</li>
				</ol>
			</s2>

			<s2 title="Usage">
				<p>The best way to explain how this serializer works is to show some examples.</p>
				<s3 title="Basic Example">
					<p>This is a basic example of the serializer.</p>
					<source><![CDATA[
<map:serializers>
  <map:serializer>
    <map:serializer name="svg2jpeg" mime-type="image/jpeg" 
                    src="org.apache.cocoon.serialization.SVGSerializer">
      <parameter name="transcoder" 
                 value="org.apache.batik.transcoder.image.JPEGTranscoder"/>
  </map:serializer>
<map:serializers>
...
<map:pipeline>
  <map:match pattern="sample.jpeg">
    <map:generate type="file" src="sample.svg"/> 
    <map:serialize type="svg2jpeg"/>
  </map:match>	
</map:pipeline>
						]]></source>
					<p>
						When the resource <code>sample.jpeg</code> is requested, a SAX event
						stream is generated from the file <code>sample.svg</code>, which is
						serialized using the <code>svg2jpeg</code> serializer. This
						serializer is configured to use a specific transcoder. The MIME type
						is specified so that Cocoon can tell the client which type the
						document is. It can be seen that in general the use of this
						serializer is identical to that of the other serializers.
					</p>
				</s3>

				<s3 title="Advanced Example">
					<p>This is a more advanced sample of using the SVG Serializer.</p>
					<source><![CDATA[
<map:serializers>
  <map:serializer>
    <map:serializer name="svg2jpeg" mime-type="image/jpeg" 
                    src="org.apache.cocoon.serialization.SVGSerializer">
      <parameter name="transcoder" 
                 value="org.apache.batik.transcoder.image.JPEGTranscoder"/>
      <parameter name="background_color" type="color" value="#00FF00"/>
  </map:serializer>
<map:serializers>
...
<map:pipeline>
  <map:match pattern="sample.jpeg">
    <map:generate type="file" src="sample.svg"/> 
    <map:serialize type="svg2jpeg"/>
  </map:match>	
</map:pipeline>
						]]></source>
					<p>
						In this example another parameter is given to the serializer,
						<code>background_color</code>. This parameter is passed to the
						transcoder. The <code>type</code> argument specifies the type of
						data to convert the <code>value</code> to. In this example the
						string "#00FF00" is converted to a <code>Color</code> object, which
						is passed to the transcoder as the background colour to
						use.
					</p>
					<p>
						For a list of the parameters available for each transcoder, refer to
						the Batik API docs.
					</p>
					<fixme author="rossb@apache.org">
						Create a document summarising the transcoder hints
					</fixme>
					<p>
						For this to work reliably with any transcoder, some magic must be
						done. First, the parameter name is transformed to upper-case and then "KEY_" is
						prepended. This is to match the internal naming scheme of the hints
						in the Batik <code>Transcoder</code> interfaces. This name is then
						looked up via Reflection to ensure it is a valid parameter on the
						specified transcoder. Then the value is converted to the type
						specified in the <code>type</code> attribute (currently supported
						types are string, float, integer, boolean and color) and passed to
						the transcoder.
					</p>
				</s3>
			</s2>
		</s1>
	</body>
</document>
