<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.0//EN" 
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.0/docbookx.dtd" []> 

<!--	
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V4.0.1//EN"
  "http://nwalsh.com/docbook/simple/4.0.1/sdocbook.dtd">
-->

<book>
<bookinfo>
  <title>Cocoon 2</title>
  <authorgroup>
    <author>
      <firstname>Stefano</firstname>
      <surname>Mazzocchi</surname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>The Apache Group</orgname>
        <address>
          <email>stefano@apache.org</email>
          <otheraddr>http://xml.apache.org</otheraddr>
        </address>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
  </authorgroup>
    <abstract>
      <title>The Apache XML Project</title>
        <para>
          This document describes the Cocoon project, and its role within the
          Apache Group's Java XML project.
        </para>
    </abstract>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>0.01</revnumber>
        <date>28 May 2000</date>
        <revremark>DocBook markup</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
</bookinfo>

<chapter>
  <title>The Cocoon Project</title>

<sect1> 
  <title>A new look</title>
  <para>
    The Cocoon Project will evidence its new course with a new logo that was
    designed by Cocoon's creator Stefano Mazzocchi. Here it is:
  </para>
  <figure>
    <title>The new Cocoon Logo</title>
    <graphic fileref="cocoon2.gif"></graphic>
  </figure>
</sect1>

<sect1>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
    The Cocoon Project has gone a long way since it's creation on January 1999.
    It started as a simple servlet for static XSL styling and became more and
    more powerful as new features were added. Unfortunately, design decisions
    made early in the project influenced its evolution. Today, some of those
    constraints that shaped the project were modified as XML standards have
    evolved and solidified. For this reason, those design decisions need to be
    reconsidered under this new light.
  </para>
  <para>
    While Cocoon started as a small step in the direction of a new web
    publishing idea based on better design patterns and reviewed estimations of
    management issues, the technology used was not mature enough for tools to
    emerge. Today, most web engineers consider XML as the key for an improved
    web model and web site managers see XML as a way to reduce costs and ease
    production.
  </para>
  <para>
    In an era where services rather than software will be key for economical
    success, a better and less expensive model for web publishing will be a
    winner, especially if based on open standards.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1> 
  <title>Passive APIs vs. Active APIs</title>
  <para>
    Web serving environments must be fast and scalable to be useful. Cocoon1
    was born as a &quot;proof of concept&quot; rather than a production
    software and had significant design restrictions based mainly on the
    availability of freely redistributable tools. Other issues were lack of
    detailed knowledge on the APIs available as well as underestimation of the
    project success, being created as a way to learn XSL rather than a full
    publishing system capable of taking care of all XML web publishing
    needs.
  </para>

  <para>
    For the above reasons, Cocoon1 was based on the DOM level 1 API which is a
    <emphasis>passive</emphasis> API and was intended mainly for client side
    operation.  This is mainly due to the fact that most DOM implementations
    require the document to reside in memory. While this is practical for small
    documents and thus good for the &quot;proof of concept&quot; stage, it is
    now considered a main design constraint for Cocoon scalability.
  </para>

  <para>
    Since the goal of Cocoon2 is the ability to process simultaneously multiple
    100Mb documents in JVM with a few Mbs of heap size, careful memory use and
    tuning of internal components is a key issue. To reach this goal, an
    improved API model was needed. This is now identified in the SAX API which
    is, unlike DOM, event based (so <emphasis>active</emphasis>, in the sense
    that its design is based the <emphasis>inversion of control</emphasis>
    principle).
  </para>

  <para>
    The event model allows document producers to trigger producing events that
    get handled in the various processing stages and get finally formatted in
    the response stream. This has significant impacts on performance and memory
    needs:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        incremental operation
      </para>
      <para>
	the response is created during document production. Client's perceived
	performance is dramatically improved since clients can start receiving
	data as soon as it is created, not after all processing stages have
	been performed. In those cases where incremental operation is not
	possible (for example, element sorting), internal buffers store the
	events until the operation can be performed.  However, even in these
	cases performance can be increased with the use of tuned memory
	structures.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        lowered memory consumption
      </para>
      <para>
	since most of the server processing required in Cocoon is incremental,
	an incremental model allows XML production events to be transformed
	directly into output events and character written on streams, thus
	avoiding the need to store them in memory.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        easier scalability
      </para>
      <para>
	reduce memory needs allow more concurrent operation to be possible,
	thus allowing the publishing system to scale as the load increases.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        more optimizable code model
      </para>
      <para>
	modern virtual machines are based on the idea of <emphasis>hot
	spots</emphasis>, code fragments that are used often and, if optimized,
	increase the process execution by far.  This new event model allows
	easier detection of hot spots since it's a method driven operation,
	rather than a memory driven one. Hot methods can be identified earlier
	and their optimization performed better.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        reduced garbage collection
      </para>
      <para>
	even the most advanced and lightweight DOM implementation require at
	least three to five times (and sometimes much more than this) more
	memory than original document size. This does not only reduce the
	scalability of the operation, but also impact overall performance by
	increasing the number of memory garbage that must be collected after
	the response in sent to the client. Even if modern virtual machines
	reduced the overhead of garbage collection, less garbage will always
	have performance and scalability impacts.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
    The above points, alone, would be enough for the Cocoon2 paradigm shift,
    even if this event based model impacts not only the general architecture of
    the publishing system but also its internal processing components such as
    XSLT processing and PDF formatting. These components will require
    substantial work and maybe design reconsideration to be able to follow a
    pure event-based model. The Cocoon Project will work closely with the other
    component projects to be able to influence their operation in this
    direction.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1> 
<title>Reactors Reconsidered</title>
  <para>
    Another design choice that should be revised is the reactor pattern that
    was introduced to allow components to be connected in more flexible way. In
    fact, opposed to the fixed pipe model used up to Cocoon 1.3.1, the reactor
    approach allows components to be dynamically connected, depending on
    reaction instructions introduced inside the documents.
  </para>

  <para>
    While this at first seemed a very advanced and highly appealing model, it
    turned out to be a very dangerous approach. The first concern is mainly
    technical: porting the reactor pattern under an event-based model requires
    limitations and tradeoffs since the generated events must be cached until a
    reaction instruction is encountered.
  </para>

  <para>
    But even if the technical difficulties are solved, a key limitation
    remains: there is no single point of management.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1> 
<title>Management Considerations</title>
  <para>
    The web was created to reduce information management costs by distributing
    them back on information owners. While this model is great for user
    communities (scientists, students, employees, or people in general) each of
    them managing small amount of personal information, it becomes impractical
    for highly centralized information systems where <emphasis>distributed
    management</emphasis> is simply not practical.
  </para>

  <para>
    While in the HTML web model the page format and URL names where the only
    necessary contracts between individuals to create a world wide web, in more
    structured information systems the number of contracts increases by a
    significant factor due to the need of coherence between the hosted
    information: common style, common design issues, common languages, server
    side logic integration, data validation, etc...
  </para>

  <para>
    It is only under this light that XML and its web model reveal their power:
    the HTML web model had too little contracts to be able to develop a
    structured and more coherent distributed information system, reason that is
    mainly imposed by the lack of good and algorithmically certain information
    indexing and knowledge seeking. Lacks that tend to degrade the quality of
    the truly distributed web in favor of more structured web sites (that based
    their improved site structure on internal contracts).
  </para>

  <para>
    The simplification and engineering of web site management is considered one
    of the most important Cocoon2 goals. This is done mainly by technologically
    imposing a reduced number of contracts and place them in a hierarchical
    shape suitable to replace current high-structure web site management
    models.
  </para>

  <para>
    The model that Cocoon2 adopts is the &quot;pyramid model of web
    contracts&quot; which is outlined in the picture below
  </para>

  <figure>
    <title>The Cocoon2 Pyramid Model of Contracts</title>
    <graphic fileref="pyramid-model.gif"></graphic>
  </figure>

  <para>
    and is composed by four different working contexts (the rectangles)
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Management
      </para>
      <para>
        the people that decide what the site should contain, how it should
        behave and how it should appear
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Content
      </para>
      <para>
	the people responsible to write, own and manage the site content. This
	context may contain several sub-contexts one for each language used to
	express page content.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Logic
      </para>
      <para>
	the people responsible for integration with dynamic content generation
	technologies and database systems.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Style
      </para>
      <para>
	the people responsible for information presentation, look &amp; feel,
	site graphics and its maintenance.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>  

  <para>
    and five contracts (the lines)
    <simplelist>
      <member>management - content</member>
      <member>management - logic</member>
      <member>management - style</member>
      <member>content - logic</member>
      <member>content - style</member>
    </simplelist>
  </para>

  <para>
    note that there is no <emphasis>logic - style</emphasis> contract. Cocoon2
    aims to provide both software and guidelines to allow you to remove such
    contract.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1> 
<title>Overlapping contexts and Chain Mapping</title>
  <para>
    The above model can be applied only if the different contexts never
    overlap, otherwise there is no chance of having a single management point.
    For example, if the W3C-recommended method to link stylesheets to XML
    documents is used, the content and style contexts overlap and it's
    impossible to change the styling behavior of the document without changing
    it. The same is true for the processing instructions used by the Cocoon1
    reactor to drive the page processing: each stage concur to determine the
    result thus increasing management and debug complexity. Another overlapping
    in context contracts is the need for URL-encoded parameters to drive the
    page output. These overlaps break the pyramid model and increase the
    management costs.
  </para>

  <para>
    In Cocoon2, the reactor pattern will be abandoned in favor of a pipeline
    mapping technique. This is based on the fact that the number of different
    contracts is limited even for big sites and grows with a rate that is
    normally much less than its size.
  </para>

  <para>
    Also, for performance reasons, Cocoon2 will try to compile everything that
    is possibly compilable (pages/XSP into producers, stylesheets into
    processors, etc...) so, in this new model, the <emphasis>processing
    chain</emphasis> that generates the page contains (in a direct executable
    form) all the information/logic that handles the requested resource to
    generate its response.
  </para>

  <para>
    This means that instead of using even-driven request-time DTD
    interpretation (done in all Cocoon1 processors), these will be either
    compiled into processors directly (XSLT stylesheet compilation) or compiled
    into producers using logicsheets and XSP which will remove totally the need
    for request-time interpretation solutions like DCP that will be removed.
  </para>

  <note>
    <para>
      Some of these features are already present in latest Cocoon 1.x releases
      but the Cocoon2 architecture will make them central to its new core
    </para>
   </note>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Sitemap</title>
  <para>
    In Cocoon2 terminology, a <emphasis>sitemap</emphasis> is the collection of
    pipeline matching informations that allow the Cocoon engine to associate
    the requested URI to the proper response-producing pipeline.
  </para>

  <para>
    The sitemap physically represents the central repository for web site
    administration, where the URI space and its handling is maintained. An
    example of the sitemap is given below:
  </para>

<programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<source>
  <sitemap>
   <process match="/press/en/*.html">
    <generator type="file" src="/docs/english/press/*.xml"/>
    <filter type="xslt">
     <parameter name="stylesheet" value="/styles/simple-press-html.xsl"/>
    </filter>
    <serializer type="html"/>
   </process>

   <process match="/press/en/*.pdf">
    <generator type="file" src="/docs/english/press/*.xml"/>
    <filter type="xslt">
     <parameter name="stylesheet" value="/styles/simple-press-pdf.xsl"/>
    </filter>
    <serializer type="pdf"/>
   </process>

   <process match="/">
    <matcher type="agent">
     <parameter name="name" value="Mozilla/5.0">
    </matcher>
    <generator type="file" src="/docs/root.xml"/>
    <filter type="xslt">
     <parameter name="stylesheet" value="/styles/fancy-XUL-view.xsl"/>
    </filter>
    <serializer type="html"/>
   </process>

   <process match="/">
    <matcher type="agent">
     <parameter name="capability" value="text/vnd.wap.wml">
    </matcher>
    <generator type="file" src="/docs/root.xml"/>
    <filter type="xslt">
     <parameter name="stylesheet" value="/styles/WAP-view.xsl"/>
    </filter>
    <serializer type="wap"/>
   </process>

   <process match="/">
    <generator type="file" src="/docs/root.xml"/>
    <filter type="xslt">
     <parameter name="stylesheet" value="/styles/normal-view.xsl"/>
    </filter>
    <serializer type="html"/>
   </process>
  </sitemap>
</source>
]]>
</programlisting>

  <note>
    <para>
      The sitemap DTD has not yet been standardized and it's not guaranteed to
      solidify until Cocoon 2.0 is out final. So, the above should be
      considered just as a preview and not a specification or even a working
      draft. For more information dig into the development mail list digests.
    </para>
  </note>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Pre-compilation, Pre-generation and Caching</title>
  <para>
    The cache system in Cocoon1 will be ported with no important design changes
    since it's very flexible and was not polluted by early design constraints
    since it appeared in later versions. The issue regards static file caching
    that, no matter what, will always be slower than direct web server caching.
  </para>

  <para>
    To be able to put most of the static part job back on the web server (where
    it belongs), Cocoon2 will greatly improve it's command line operation,
    allowing the creation of <emphasis>site makefiles</emphasis> that will
    automatically scan the web site and the source documents and will provide a
    way to <emphasis>regenerate</emphasis> the static part of a web site
    (images and tables included!) based on the same XML model used in the
    dynamic operation version.
  </para>

  <para>
    Cocoon2 will, in fact, be the integration between Cocoon1 and Stylebook.
  </para>

  <para>
    It will be up to the web server administrator to use static regeneration
    capabilities on a time basis, manually or triggered by some particular
    event (database update signal) since Cocoon2 will only provide servlet and
    command line capabilities. The nice integration is based on the fact that
    there will be no behavioral difference if the files are dynamically
    generated in Cocoon2 via the servlet operation and cached internally or
    pre-generated and served directly by the web server, as long as URI
    contracts are kept the same by the system administrator (via URL-rewriting
    or aliasing)
  </para>

  <para>
    Also, it will be possible to avoid on-fly page and stylesheet compilation
    (which make debugging harder) with command line pre-compilation hooks that
    will work like normal compilers from a developer's point of view.
  </para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Development Status</title>
  <para>
    Cocoon2 development already started, but should be considered of pre-alpha
    quality. If you dare, you might take a look at it on the
    <emphasis>xml-cocoon2</emphasis> CVS branch in the Cocoon CVS module, or,
    if you are not a CVS expert, this means typing:
  </para>

  <para>
    <command>
      cvs checkout -r xml-cocoon2 xml-cocoon
    </command>
  </para>

  <para>
    For more information on CVS access, refer to the CVS-howtos on this web
    site.
  </para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
</book>
