<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document>

    &project;

    <properties>
        <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
        <title>Manager App HOW-TO</title>
    </properties>

<body>


<section name="Introduction">

<p>In many production environments, it is very useful to have the capability
to deploy a new web application, or undeploy an existing one, without having
to shut down and restart the entire container.  In addition, you can request
an existing application to reload itself, even if you have not declared it
to be <code>reloadable</code> in the Tomcat 4 server
configuration file.</p>

<p>To support these capabilities, Tomcat 4 includes a web application
(installed by default on context path <code>/manager</code>) that supports
the following functions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Deploy a new web application, on a specified context path, from a
    specified directory or WAR file pathname.</li>
<li>List the currently deployed web applications, as well as the
    sessions that are currently active for those web apps.</li>
<li>Cause an existing application to be reloaded.</li>
<li>Undeploy an existing web application.</li>
<li>Stop an existing application (so that it becomes unavailable), but
    do not undeploy it.</li>
<li>Start a stopped application (thus making it available again).</li>
</ul>

<p>Since <code>Manager</code> is itself a web application, it interacts with
you using standard HTTP requests and responses.  However, it's "user interface"
is minimal, because it is intended to be accessed from scripts set up by the
system administrator.  For this reason, commands are given as part of the
request URI, and responses are in the form of simple text that can be easily
parsed and processed.</p>

<p>Future versions of Tomcat 4 will include administrative functionality that
is presented in (at least) the following forms:</p>
<ul>
<li>As web services, so that Tomcat administration can be easily integrated
    into remote and/or non-Java mnagement environments.</li>
<li>As a web application with a nice user interface (built on top of the
    web services processing layer) for easy Tomcat administration via a
    web browser.</li>
</ul>

</section>

<section name="Configuring Manager Application Access">

    <blockquote><em>
    <p>The description below uses the variable name $CATALINA_HOME
    to refer to the directory into which you have installed Tomcat 4,
    and is the base directory against which most relative paths are
    resolved.  However, if you have configured Tomcat 4 for multiple
    instances by setting a CATALINA_BASE directory, you should use
    $CATALINA_BASE instead of $CATALINA_HOME for each of these
    references.</p>
    </em></blockquote>

<p>It would be quite unsafe to ship Tomcat with default settings that allowed
anyone on the Internet to execute the Manager application on your server.
Therefore, the Manager application is shipped with the requirement that anyone
who attempts to use it must authenticate themselves, using a username and
password that have the role <strong>manager</strong> associated with them.
Further, there is no username in the default users file
(<conf>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/tomcat-users.xml</conf>) that is assigned this
role.  Therefore, access to the Manager application is completely disabled
by default.</p>

<p>To enable access to the Manager web application, you must either create
a new username/password combination and associate the role name
<strong>manager</strong> with it, or add the <strong>manager</strong> role
to some existing username/password combination.  Exactly where this is done
depends on which <code>Realm</code> implementation you are using:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>MemoryRealm</em> - If you have not customized your
    <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/server.xml</code> to select a different one,
    Tomcat 4 defaults to an XML-format file stored at
    <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/tomcat-users.xml</code>, which can be
    edited with any text editor.  This file contains an XML
    <code>&lt;user&gt;</code> for each individual user, which might
    look something like this:
<source>
&lt;user name="craigmcc" password="secret" roles="standard,manager"&gt;
</source>
    which defines the username and password used by this individual to
    log on, and the role names he or she is associated with.  You can
    add the <strong>manager</strong> role to the comma-delimited
    <code>roles</code> attriute for one or more existing users, and/or
    create new users with that assigned role.</li>
<li><em>JDBCRealm</em> - Your user and role information is stored in
    a database accessed via JDBC.  Add the <strong>manager</strong> role
    to one or more existing users, and/or create one or more new users
    with this role assigned, following the standard procedures for your
    environment.</li>
<li><em>JNDIRealm</em> - Your user and role information is stored in
    a directory server accessed via LDAP.  Add the <strong>manager</strong>
    role to one or more existing users, and/or create one or more new users
    with this role assigned, following the standard procedures for your
    environment.</li>
</ul>

<p>The first time you attempt to issue one of the Manager commands
described in the next section, you will be challenged to logn on, using
BASIC authentication.  The username and password you enter do not matter,
as long as they identify a valid user in the users database who possesses
the role <strong>manager</strong>.</p>

</section>


<section name="Supported Manager Commands">

<p>All commands that the Manager application knows how to process are
specified in a single request URI like this:</p>
<source>
http://{host}:{port}/manager/{command}?{parameters}
</source>
<p>where <code>{host}</code> and <code>{port}</code> represent the hostname
and port number on which Tomcat is running, <code>{command}</code>
represents the Manager command you wish to execute, and
<code>{parameters}</code> represents the query parameters
that are specific to that command.  In the illustrations below, customize
the host and port appropriately for your installation.</p>

<p>Most commands accept one or more of the following query parameters:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>path</strong> - The context path (including the leading slash)
    of the web application you are dealing with.  To select the ROOT web
    application, specify a zero-length string.  <strong>NOTE</strong> -
    It is not possible to perform administrative commands on the
    Manager application itself.</li>
<li><strong>war</strong> - URL of a web application archive (WAR) file,
    or pathname of a directory, that contains the web application.
    You can use URLs in any of the following formats:
    <ul>
    <li><strong>file:/absolute/path/to/a/directory</strong> - The absolute
        path of a directory that contains the unpacked version of a web
        application.  This directory will be attached to the context path
        you specify without any changes.</li>
    <li><strong>jar:file:/absolute/path/to/a/warfile.war!/</strong> - The
        URL to a local web application archive (WAR) file.  You can use any
        syntax that is valid for the <code>JarURLConnection</code> class
        for reference to an entire JAR file.</li>
    <li><strong>jar:http://hostname:port/path/to/a/warfile.war!/</strong> -
        You can also deploy web applications from a remote JAR file.  You can
        use any syntax that is valid for the <code>JarURLConnection</code>
        class for reference to an entire JAR file.</li>
    </ul></li>
</ul>

<p>Each command will return a response in <code>text/plain</code> format
(i.e. plain ASCII with no HTML markup), making it easy for both humans and
programs to read).  The first line of the response wil begin with either
<code>OK</code> or <code>FAIL</code>, indicating whether the requested
command was successful or not.  In the case of failure, the rest of the first
line will contain a description of the problem that was encountered.  Some
commands include additional lines of information as described below.</p>

<p><em>Internationalization Note</em> - The Manager application looks up
its message strings in resource bundles, so it is possible that the strings
have been translated for your platform.  The examples below show the English
version of the messages.</p>

<subsection name="Deploy A New Application">

<source>
http://localhost:8080/manager/install?path=/foo&amp;war=file:/path/to/foo

http://localhost:8080/manager/install?path=/bar&amp;war=jar:file:/path/to/bar.war!/
</source>

<p>Install and start a new web application, attached to the specified context
path (which must not be in use by any other web application).  The
<code>war</code> parameter specifies a URL (including the <code>file:</code>
scheme) for either a directory or a web application archive (WAR) file.
The supported syntax for a URL referring to a WAR file is described on the
Javadocs page for the <code>java.net.JarURLConnection</code> class.  Use
only URLs that refer to the entire WAR file.</p>

<p>If installation and startup is successful, you will receive a response
like this:</p>
<source>
OK - Installed application at context path /foo
</source>

<p>Otherwise, the response will start with <code>FAIL</code> and include an
error message.  Possible causes for problems include:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Application already exists at path /foo</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>The context paths for all currently running web applications must be
    unique.  Therefore, you must either undeploy the existing web application
    using this context path, or choose a different context path for the
    new one.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>Document base does not exist or is not a readable directory</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>The URL specified by the <code>war</code> parameter must identify a
    directory on this server that contains the "unpacked" version of a
    web application, or the absolute URL of a web application archive (WAR)
    file that contains this application.  Correct the value specified by
    the <code>war</code> parameter.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>Encountered exception</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>An exception was encountered trying to start the new web application.
    Check the Tomcat 4 logs for the details, but likely explanations include
    problems parsing your <code>/WEB-INF/web.xml</code> file, or missing
    classes encountered when initializing application event listeners and
    filters.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>Invalid application URL was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>The URL for the directory or web application that you specified
    was not valid.  Such URLs must start with <code>file:</code>, and URLs
    for a WAR file must end in ".war".</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>Invalid context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>The context path must start with a slash character, unless you are
    referencing the ROOT web application -- in which case the context path
    must be a zero-length string.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>No context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    The <code>path</code> parameter is required.
    </blockquote></li>
</ul>

</subsection>

<subsection name="List Currently Deployed Applications">

<source>
http://localhost:8080/manager/list
</source>

<p>List the context paths, current status (<code>running</code> or
<code>stopped</code>), and number of active sessions for all currently
deployed web applications.  A typical response immediately after starting
Tomcat might look like this:</p>
<source>
OK - Listed applications for virtual host localhost
/webdav:running:0
/examples:running:0
/manager:running:0
/:running:0
</source>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Reload An Existing Application">

<source>
http://localhost:8080/manager/reload?path=/examples
</source>

<p>Signal an existing application to shut itself down and reload.  This can
be useful when you've recompiled classes on an application that is not
configured with the <code>reloadable="true"</code> attribute in its
<code>&lt;Context&gt;</code> entry in
<code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/server.xml</code>, or when you've made other
changes (such as to <code>conf/web.xml</code>) that are not automatically
recognized by Tomcat.</p>

<p>If this command succeeds, you will see a response like this:</p>
<source>
OK - Reloaded application at context path /examples
</source>

<p>Otherwise, the response will start with <code>FAIL</code> and include an
error message.  Possible causes for problems include:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Encountered exception</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>An exception was encountered trying to restart the web application.
    Check the Tomcat 4 logs for the details.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>Invalid context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>The context path must start with a slash character, unless you are
    referencing the ROOT web application -- in which case the context path
    must be a zero-length string.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>No context exists for path /foo</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>There is no deployed application on the context path that you
    specified.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>No context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    The <code>path</code> parameter is required.
    </blockquote></li>
</ul>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Session Statistics">

<source>
http://localhost:8080/manager/sessions?path=/examples
</source>

<p>Display the default session timeout for a web application, and the
number of currently active sessions that fall within ten-minute ranges of
their actual timeout times.  For example, after restarting Tomcat and then
executing one of the JSP samples in the <code>/examples</code> web app,
you might get something like this:</p>
<source>
OK - Session information for application at context path /examples
Default maximum session inactive interval 30 minutes
30 - &lt;40 minutes:1 sessions
</source>

</subsection>


<subsection name="Start an Existing Application">

<source>
http://localhost:8080/manager/start?path=/examples
</source>

<p>Signal a stopped application to restart, and make itself available again.
Stopping and starting is useful, for example, if the database required by
your application becomes temporarily unavailable.  It is usually better to
stop the web application that relies on this database, rather than letting
users continuously encounter database exceptions.</p>

<p>If this command succeeds, you will see a response like this:</p>
<source>
OK - Started application at context path /examples
</source>

<p>Otherwise, the response will start with <code>FAIL</code> and include an
error message.  Possible causes for problems include:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Encountered exception</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>An exception was encountered trying to undeploy the web application.
    Check the Tomcat 4 logs for the details.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>Invalid context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>The context path must start with a slash character, unless you are
    referencing the ROOT web application -- in which case the context path
    must be a zero-length string.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>No context exists for path /foo</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>There is no deployed application on the context path that you
    specified.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>No context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    The <code>path</code> parameter is required.
    </blockquote></li>
</ul>

</subsection>

<subsection name="Stop an Existing Application">

<source>
http://localhost:8080/manager/stop?path=/examples
</source>

<p>Signal an existing application to make itself unavailable, but leave it
deployed.  Any request that comes in while an application is stopped will
see an HTTP error 404, and this application will show as "stopped" on a
list applications command.</p>

<p>If this command succeeds, you will see a response like this:</p>
<source>
OK - Stopped application at context path /examples
</source>

<p>Otherwise, the response will start with <code>FAIL</code> and include an
error message.  Possible causes for problems include:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Encountered exception</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>An exception was encountered trying to undeploy the web application.
    Check the Tomcat 4 logs for the details.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>Invalid context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>The context path must start with a slash character, unless you are
    referencing the ROOT web application -- in which case the context path
    must be a zero-length string.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>No context exists for path /foo</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>There is no deployed application on the context path that you
    specified.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>No context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    The <code>path</code> parameter is required.
    </blockquote></li>
</ul>

</subsection>


<subsection name="Undeploy an Existing Application">

<source>
http://localhost:8080/manager/remove?path=/examples
</source>

<p>Signal an existing application to gracefully shut itself down, and then
remove it from Tomcat (which also makes this context path available for
reuse later).</p>

<p>If this command succeeds, you will see a response like this:</p>
<source>
OK - Removed application at context path /examples
</source>

<p>Otherwise, the response will start with <code>FAIL</code> and include an
error message.  Possible causes for problems include:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Encountered exception</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>An exception was encountered trying to undeploy the web application.
    Check the Tomcat 4 logs for the details.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>Invalid context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>The context path must start with a slash character, unless you are
    referencing the ROOT web application -- in which case the context path
    must be a zero-length string.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>No context exists for path /foo</em>
    <blockquote>
    <p>There is no deployed application on the context path that you
    specified.</p>
    </blockquote></li>
<li><em>No context path was specified</em>
    <blockquote>
    The <code>path</code> parameter is required.
    </blockquote></li>
</ul>

</subsection>

</section>


</body>

</document>
