<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE document [
  <!ENTITY project SYSTEM "project.xml">
]>
<document>

    &project;

    <properties>
        <author email="craigmcc@apache.org">Craig R. McClanahan</author>
        <title>Realm Configuration HOW-TO</title>
    </properties>

<body>


<section name="Quick Start">

<p>This document describes how to configure Tomcat to support <em>container
managed security</em>, by connecting to an existing "database" of usernames,
passwords, and user roles.  You only need to care about this if you are using
a web application that includes one or more
<code>&lt;security-constraint&gt;</code> elements, and a
<code>&lt;login-config&gt;</code> element defining how users are required
to authenticate themselves.  If you are not utilizing these features, you can
safely skip this document.</p>

<p>For fundamental background information about container managed security,
see the <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/download.html">Servlet
Specification (Version 2.3)</a>, Section 12.  For a more introductory level
document for web application developers as well as administrators, see
(<strong>FIXME</strong> - link to backgrounder on container managed security
to be provided).</p>

<p>For information about utilizing the <em>Single Sign On</em> feature of
Tomcat 4 (allowing a user to authenticate themselves once across the entire
set of web applications associated with a virtual host), see
<a href="config/host.html#Single Sign On">here</a>.</p>

</section>


<section name="Overview">


<subsection name="What is a Realm?">

<p>A <strong>Realm</strong> is a "database" of usernames and passwords that
identify valid users of a web application (or set of web applications), plus
an enumeration of the list of <em>roles</em> associated with each valid user.
You can think of roles as similar to <em>groups</em> in Unix-like operating
systems, because access to specific web application resources is granted to
all users possessing a particular role (rather than enumerating the list of
associated usernames).  A particular user can have any number of roles
associated with their username.</p>

<p>Although the Servlet Specification describes a portable mechanism for
applications to <em>declare</em> their security requirements (in the
<code>web.xml</code> deployment descriptor), there is no portable API
defining the interface between a servlet container and the associated user
and role information.  In many cases, however, it is desireable to "connect"
a servlet container to some existing authentication database or mechanism
that already exists in the production environment.  Therefore, Tomcat 4
defines a Java interface (<code>org.apache.catalina.Realm</code>) that
can be implemented by "plug in" components to establish this connection.
Three standard plug-ins are provided, supporting connection to three different
sources of authentication information:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#JDBCRealm">JDBCRealm</a> - Accesses authentication information
    stored in a relational database, accessed via a JDBC driver.</li>
<li><a href="#JNDIRealm">JNDIRealm</a> - Accesses authentication information
    stored in an LDAP based directory server, accessed via a JNDI provider.
    </li>
<li><a href="#MemoryRealm">MemoryRealm</a> - Accesses authentication
    information stored in an in-memory object collection, which is initialized
    from an XML document (<code>conf/tomcat-users.xml</code>).</li>
</ul>

<p>It is also possible to write your own <code>Realm</code> implementation,
and integrate it with Tomcat 4.  However, doing this is beyond the scope of
this document.  See (<strong>FIXME</strong> - reference to developer stuff)
for more information.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection name="Configuring a Realm">

<p>Before getting into the details of the standard Realm implementations, it is
important to understand, in general terms, how a Realm is configured.  In
general, you will be adding an XML element to your <code>conf/server.xml</code>
configuration file, that looks something like this:</p>

<source>
&lt;Realm className="... class name for this implementation"
       ... other attributes for this implementation .../&gt;
</source>

<p>The <code>&lt;Realm&gt;</code> element can be nested inside one of three
different elements, which has a direct impact on the "scope" of that Realm
(i.e. which web applications will share the same authentication information):
</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Inside an &lt;Engine&gt; element</em> - This Realm will be shared
    across ALL web applications on ALL virtual hosts, UNLESS it is overridden
    by a Realm element nested inside a subordinate <code>&lt;Host&gt;</code>
    or <code>&lt;Context&gt;</code> element.</li>
<li><em>Inside a &lt;Host&gt; element</em> - This Realm will be shared across
    ALL web applications for THIS virtual host, UNLESS it is overridden
    by a Realm element nested inside a subordinate <code>&lt;Context&gt;</code>
    element.</li>
<li><em>Inside a &lt;Context&gt; element</em> - This Realm will be used ONLY
    for THIS web application.</li>
</ul>


</subsection>


</section>


<section name="Standard Realm Implementations">


<subsection name="JDBCRealm">

<h3>Introduction</h3>

<p><strong>JDBCRealm</strong> is an implementation of the Tomcat 4
<code>Realm</code> interface that looks up users in a relational database
accessed via a JDBC driver.  There is substantial configuration flexibility
that lets you adapt to existing table and column names, as long as your
database structure conforms to the following requirements:</p>
<ul>
<li>There must be a table, referenced below as the <em>users</em> table,
    that contains one row for every valid user that this <code>Realm</code>
    should recognize.</li>
<li>The <em>users</em> table must contain at least two columns (it may
    contain more if your existing applications required it):
    <ul>
    <li>Username to be recognized by Tomcat when the user logs in.</li>
    <li>Password to be recognized by Tomcat when the user logs in.
        This value may in cleartext or digested - see below for more
        information.</li>
    </ul></li>
<li>There must be a table, referenced below as the <em>user roles</em> table,
    that contains one row for every valid role that is assigned to a
    particular user.  It is legal for a user to have zero, one, or more than
    one valid role.</li>
<li>The <em>user roles</em> table must contain at least two columns (it may
    contain more if your existing applications required it):
    <ul>
    <li>Username to be recognized by Tomcat (same value as is specified
        in the <em>users</em> table).</li>
    <li>Role name of a valid role associated with this user.</li>
    </ul></li>
</ul>

<h3>Quick Start</h3>

<p>To set up Tomcat to use JDBCRealm, you will need to follow these steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>If you have not yet done so, create tables and columns in your database
    that conform to the requirements described above.</li>
<li>Configure a database username and password for use by Tomcat, that has
    at least read only access to the tables described above.  (Tomcat will
    never attempt to write to these tables.)</li>
<li>Place a copy of the JDBC driver you will be using inside the
    <code>$CATALINA_HOME/server/lib</code> directory (if you do not need it
    visible to web applications) or <code>$CATALINA_HOME/common/lib</code>
    (if it will be used both by Tomcat 4 <em>and</em> by your apps).
    Note that <strong>only</strong> JAR files are recognized!</li>
<li>Set up a <code>&lt;Realm&gt;</code> element, as described below, in your
    <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/server.xml</code> file.</li>
<li>Restart Tomcat 4 if it is already running.</li>
</ol>

<h3>Realm Element Attributes</h3>

<p>To configure JDBCRealm, you will create a <code>&lt;Realm&gt;</code>
element and nest it in your <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/server.xml</code> file,
as described <a href="#Configuring a Realm">above</a>.  The following
attributes are supported by this implementation:</p>

<attributes>

  <attribute name="className" required="true">
    <p>The fully qualified Java class name of this Realm implementation.
    You <strong>MUST</strong> specify the value
    "<code>org.apache.catalina.realm.JDBCRealm</code>" here.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="connectionName" required="true">
    <p>The database username used to establish a JDBC connection.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="connectionPassword" required="true">
    <p>The database password used to establish a JDBC connection.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="connectionURL" required="true">
    <p>The database URL used to establish a JDBC connection.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="debug" required="false">
    <p>The level of debugging detail logged by this Realm
    to the associated <a href="config/logger.html">Logger</a>.  Higher numbers
    generate more detailed output.  If not specified, the default
    debugging detail level is zero (0).</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="digest" required="false">
    <p>The digest algorithm used to store passwords in non-plaintext formats.
    Valid values are those accepted for the algorithm name by the
    <code>java.security.MessageDigest</code> class.  See
    <a href="#Digested Passwords">Digested Passwords</a> for more
    information.  If not specified, passwords are stored in clear text.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="driverName" required="true">
    <p>The fully qualified Java class name of the JDBC driver to be used.
    Consult the documentation for your JDBC driver for the appropriate
    value.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="roleNameCol" required="true">
    <p>The name of the column, in the <em>user roles</em> table, that
    contains the name of a role assigned to this user.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="userCredCol" required="true">
    <p>The name of the column, in the <em>users</em> table, that contains
    the password for this user (either in clear text, or digested if the
    <code>digest</code> attribute is set).</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="userNameCol" required="true">
    <p>The name of the column, in the <em>users</em> and <em>user roles</em>
    tables, that contains the username of this user.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="userRoleTable" required="true">
    <p>The name of the table that contains one row for each <em>role</em>
    assigned to a particular <em>username</em>.  This table must include at
    least the columns named by the <code>userNameCol</code> and
    <code>roleNameCol</code> attributes.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="userTable" required="true">
    <p>The name of the table that contains one row for each <em>username</em>
    to be recognized by Tomcat.  This table must include at least the columns
    named by the <code>userNameCol</code> and <code>userCredCol</code>
    attributes.</p>
  </attribute>

</attributes>

<h3>Example</h3>

<p>An example SQL script to create the needed tables might look something
like this (adapt the syntax as required for your particular database):</p>
<source>
create table users (
  user_name         varchar(15) not null primary key,
  user_pass         varchar(15) not null
);

create table user_roles (
  user_name         varchar(15) not null,
  role_name         varchar(15) not null,
  primary key (user_name, role_name)
);
</source>

<p>Example <code>Realm</code> elements are included (commented out) in the
default <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/server.xml</code> file.  Here's an example
for using a MySQL database called "authority", configured with the tables
described above, and accessed with username "dbuser" and password "dbpass":</p>
<source>
&lt;Realm className="org.apache.catalina.realm.JDBCRealm" debug="99"
      driverName="org.gjt.mm.mysql.Driver"
   connectionURL="jdbc:mysql://localhost/authority?user=dbuser;password=dbpass"
       userTable="users" userNameCol="user_name" userCredCol="user_pass"
   userRoleTable="user_roles" roleNameCol="role_name"/&gt;
</source>

<h3>Additional Notes</h3>

<p>JDBCRealm operates according to the following rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>When a user attempts to access a protected resource for the first time,
    Tomcat 4 will call the <code>authenticate()</code> method of this
    <code>Realm</code>.  Thus, any changes you have made to the database
    directly (new users, changed passwords or roles, etc.) will be immediately
    reflected.</li>
<li>Once a user has been authenticated, the user (and his or her associated
    roles) are cached within Tomcat for the duration of the user's login.
    (For FORM-based authentication, that means until the session times out or
    is invalidated; for BASIC authentication, that means until the user
    closes their browser).  Any changes to the database information for an
    already authenticated user will <strong>not</strong> be reflected until
    the next time that user logs on again.</li>
<li>Administering the information in the <em>users</em> and <em>user roles</em>
    table is the responsibility of your own applications.  Tomcat does not
    provide any built-in capabilities to maintain users and roles.</li>
<li>Debugging and exception messages logged by this <code>Realm</code> will
    be recorded by the <code>Logger</code> that is associated with our
    surrounding <code>Context</code>, <code>Host</code>, or
    <code>Engine</code>.  By default, the corresponding Logger will create a
    log file in the <code>$CATALINA_HOME/logs</code> directory.</li>
</ul>

</subsection>


<subsection name="JNDIRealm">

<h3>Introduction</h3>

<p><strong>JNDIRealm</strong> is an implementation of the Tomcat 4
<code>Realm</code> interface that looks up users in a directory server
accessed by a JNDI provider (typically, the standard LDAP provider that
is available with the JNDI API classes).  There is substantial configuration
flexibility that lets you adapt to the existing schema inside your directory
server, as long as it conforms to the following requirements:</p>
<ul>
<li>Each user that can be authenticated is represented by an individual
    element in the top level <code>DirContext</code> that is accessed
    via the <code>connectionURL</code> attribute.</li>
<li>The <em>user</em> element must have the following characteristics:
    <ul>
    <li>The distinguished name (<code>dn</code>) attribute of this element
        contains the username that is presented for authentication.</li>
    <li>There must be an attribute (identified by the <code>userPassword</code>
        attribute of our <code>Realm</code> element) that contains the user's
        password, either in clear text or digested (see below for more info).
        </li>
    </ul></li>
<li>Each group of users that has been assigned a particular role is
    represented by an individual element in the top level
    <code>DirContext</code> that is accessed via the
    <code>connectionURL</code> attribute.</li>
<li>The <em>user group</em> element must have the following characteristics:
    <ul>
    <li>The set of all possible groups of interest can be selected by an LDAP
        search pattern configured by the <code>roleSearch</code> attribute
        of our <code>Realm</code> element.</li>
    <li>The <code>roleSearch</code> pattern optionally includes pattern
        replacements "{0}" for the distinguished name, and/or "{1} for the
        username, of the authenticated user for which roles will be
        retrieved.</li>
    <li>The <code>roleBase</code> attribute can be set to the element that
        is the base of the search for matching roles.  If not specified,
        the entire directory context will be searched.</li>
    <li>The <code>roleSubtree</code> attribute can be set to <code>true</code>
        if you wish to search the entire subtree of the directory context.
        The default value of <code>false</code> requests a search of only the
        current level.</li>
    <li>The element includes an attribute (whose name is configured by the
        <code>roleName</code> attribute of our <code>Realm</code> element)
        containing the name of the role represented by this element.</li>
    </ul></li>
<li>There must be an administrator username and password that Tomcat can
    use to establish a connection to the directory server, with at least
    read-only access to the information described above.  A future
    version of Tomcat will support an option to use the user's username and
    password to attempt this connection.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Quick Start</h3>

<p>To set up Tomcat to use JNDIRealm, you will need to follow these steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>Make sure your directory server is configured with a schema that matches
    the requirements listed above.</li>
<li>Configure a username and password for use by Tomcat, that has
    at least read only access to the information described above.  (Tomcat will
    never attempt to modify this information.)</li>
<li>Place a copy of the JNDI driver you will be using (typically
    <code>ldap.jar</code> available with JNDI) inside the
    <code>$CATALINA_HOME/server/lib</code> directory (if you do not need it
    visible to web applications) or <code>$CATALINA_HOME/common/lib</code>
    (if it will be used both by Tomcat 4 <em>and</em> by your apps).</li>
<li>Set up a <code>&lt;Realm&gt;</code> element, as described below, in your
    <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/server.xml</code> file.</li>
<li>Restart Tomcat 4 if it is already running.</li>
</ol>

<h3>Realm Element Attributes</h3>

<p>To configure JNDIRealm, you will create a <code>&lt;Realm&gt;</code>
element and nest it in your <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/server.xml</code> file,
as described <a href="#Configuring a Realm">above</a>.  The following
attributes are supported by this implementation:</p>

<attributes>

  <attribute name="className" required="true">
    <p>The fully qualified Java class name of this Realm implementation.
    You <strong>MUST</strong> specify the value
    "<code>org.apache.catalina.realm.JDBCRealm</code>" here.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="connectionName" required="true">
    <p>The directory server username used to establish a JNDI connection.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="connectionPassword" required="true">
    <p>The directory server password used to establish a JNDI connection.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="connectionURL" required="true">
    <p>The directory server URL used to establish a JNDI connection.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="contextFactory" required="false">
    <p>The fully qualified Java class name of the JNDI context factory to be
    used for this connection.  By default, the standard JNDI LDAP provider
    is used (<code>com.sun.jndi.ldap.LdapCtxFactory</code>).</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="debug" required="false">
    <p>The level of debugging detail logged by this Realm
    to the associated <a href="config/logger.html">Logger</a>.  Higher numbers
    generate more detailed output.  If not specified, the default
    debugging detail level is zero (0).</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="digest" required="false">
    <p>The digest algorithm used to store passwords in non-plaintext formats.
    Valid values are those accepted for the algorithm name by the
    <code>java.security.MessageDigest</code> class.  See
    <a href="#Digested Passwords">Digested Passwords</a> for more
    information.  If not specified, passwords are stored in clear text.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="roleBase" required="false">
    <p>The base element for role searches.  If not specified, the top level
    element in the directory context will be used.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="roleName" required="true">
    <p>The name of the directory server attribute containing the role name.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="roleSearch" required="true">
    <p>An LDAP search pattern for selecting roles in this Realm, following the
    syntax supported by the <code>java.text.MessageFormat</code> class.  Use
    <code>{0}</code> to substitute in the distinguished name of the user you
    want roles for, and/or <code>{1}</code> to substitute in the username of
    the user you want roles for.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="roleSubtree" required="false">
    <p>Set to <code>true</code> if you want role searches to search subtrees
    of the element selected by <code>roleBase</code>.  The default value of
    <code>false</code> causes only the top level element to be searched.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="userPassword" required="true">
    <p>The name of the directory server attribute (in the user element) that
    contains the cleartext or digested user password (depending on the setting
    of the <code>digest</code> attribute).</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="userPattern" required="true">
    <p>An LDAP search pattern for selecting users in this Realm, following the
    syntax supported by the <code>java.text.MessageFormat</code> class.  Use
    <code>{0}</code> to substitute in the distinguished name of the user you
    want to select.</p>
  </attribute>

</attributes>

<h3>Example</h3>

<p>Creation of the appropriate schema in your directory server is beyond the
scope of this document, because it is unique to each directory server
implementation.  In the examples below, we will assume that you are using a
distribution of the OpenLDAP directory server (version 2.0.11 or later), which
can be downloaded from
<a href="http://www.openldap.org">http://www.openldap.org</a>.  Assume that
your <code>slapd.conf</code> file contains the following settings
(among others):</p>
<source>
database ldbm
suffix dc="mycompany",dc="com"
rootdn "cn=Manager,dc=mycompany,dc=com"
rootpw secret
</source>

<p>These settings help us identify values for the values to be specified for
<code>connectionName</code>, and <code>connectionPassword</code>, and we
will assume for <code>connectionURL</code> that the directory server runs on
the same machine as Tomcat.  See
<a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jndi/docs.html">http://java.sun.com/products/jndi/docs.html</a>
for more information about configuring and using the JNDI LDAP provider.</p>

<p>Next, assume that this directory server has been populated with elements
as shown below (in LDIF format), which define the same users and roles
as the default <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/tomcat-users.xml</code> does for
MemoryRealm:</p>
<source>
# Define a user named 'tomcat'
dn: cn=tomcat,dc=mycompany,dc=com
cn: tomcat
userPassword: tomcat
sn: Tomcat User
objectClass: person

# Define a user named 'role1'
dn: cn=role1,dc=mycompany,dc=com
cn: role1
userPassword: tomcat
sn: Role1 User
objectClass: person

# Define a user named 'both'
dn: cn=both,dc=mycompany,dc=com
cn: both
userPassword: tomcat
sn: Both User
objectClass: person

# Define an entry to base role searches on
dn: dc=roles,dc=mycompany,dc=com
cn: roles
objectClass: person
sn: Roles Entry

# Define all members of the 'tomcat' role
dn: cn=tomcat,dc=roles,dc=mycompany,dc=com
cn: tomcat
objectClass: groupOfUniqueNames
uniqueMember: cn=tomcat,dc=mycompany,dc=com
uniqueMember: cn=both,dc=mycompany,dc=com

# Define all members of the 'role1' role
dn: cn=role1,dc=roles,dc=mycompany,dc=com
cn: role1
objectClass: groupOfUniqueNames
uniqueMember: cn=role1,dc=mycompany,dc=com
uniqueMember: cn=both,dc=mycompany,dc=com
</source>

<p>An example <code>Realm</code> element for the OpenLDAP directory server
configured as described above might look like this:</p>
<source>
&lt;Realm   className="org.apache.catalina.realm.JNDIRealm" debug="99"
    connectionName="cn=Manager,dc=mycompany,dc=com"
connectionPassword="secret"
     connectionURL="ldap://localhost:389"
          roleBase="dc=roles,dc=mcclan,dc=net"
          roleName="cn"
        roleSearch="(uniqueMember={0})"
       roleSubtree="false"
      userPassword="userPassword"
       userPattern="cn={0},dc=mycompany,dc=com"
/&gt;
</source>

<h3>Additional Notes</h3>

<p>JNDIRealm operates according to the following rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>When a user attempts to access a protected resource for the first time,
    Tomcat 4 will call the <code>authenticate()</code> method of this
    <code>Realm</code>.  Thus, any changes you have made to the database
    directly (new users, changed passwords or roles, etc.) will be immediately
    reflected.</li>
<li>Once a user has been authenticated, the user (and his or her associated
    roles) are cached within Tomcat for the duration of the user's login.
    (For FORM-based authentication, that means until the session times out or
    is invalidated; for BASIC authentication, that means until the user
    closes their browser).  Any changes to the database information for an
    already authenticated user will <strong>not</strong> be reflected until
    the next time that user logs on again.</li>
<li>Administering the information in the directory server
    is the responsibility of your own applications.  Tomcat does not
    provide any built-in capabilities to maintain users and roles.</li>
<li>Debugging and exception messages logged by this <code>Realm</code> will
    be recorded by the <code>Logger</code> that is associated with our
    surrounding <code>Context</code>, <code>Host</code>, or
    <code>Engine</code>.  By default, the corresponding Logger will create a
    log file in the <code>$CATALINA_HOME/logs</code> directory.</li>
</ul>

</subsection>


<subsection name="MemoryRealm">

<h3>Introduction</h3>

<p><strong>MemoryRealm</strong> is a simple demonstration implementation of the
Tomcat 4 <code>Realm</code> interface.  It is not designed for production use.
At startup time, MemoryRealm loads information about all users, and their
corresponding roles, from an XML document (by default, this document is loaded from <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/tomcat-users.xml</code>).  Changes to the data
in this file are not recognized until Tomcat is restarted.</p>

<h3>Realm Element Attributes</h3>

<p>To configure MemoryRealm, you will create a <code>&lt;Realm&gt;</code>
element and nest it in your <code>$CATALINA_HOME/conf/server.xml</code> file,
as described <a href="#Configuring a Realm">above</a>.  The following
attributes are supported by this implementation:</p>

<attributes>

  <attribute name="className" required="true">
    <p>The fully qualified Java class name of this Realm implementation.
    You <strong>MUST</strong> specify the value
    "<code>org.apache.catalina.realm.MemoryRealm</code>" here.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="debug" required="false">
    <p>The level of debugging detail logged by this Realm
    to the associated <a href="config/logger.html">Logger</a>.  Higher numbers
    generate more detailed output.  If not specified, the default
    debugging detail level is zero (0).</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="digest" required="false">
    <p>The digest algorithm used to store passwords in non-plaintext formats.
    Valid values are those accepted for the algorithm name by the
    <code>java.security.MessageDigest</code> class.  See
    <a href="#Digested Passwords">Digested Passwords</a> for more
    information.  If not specified, passwords are stored in clear text.</p>
  </attribute>

  <attribute name="pathname" required="false">
    <p>Absolute or relative (to $CATALINA_HOME) pathname of the XML document
    containing our valid usernames, passwords, and roles.  See below for more
    information on the format of this file.  If not specified, the value
    <code>conf/tomcat-users.xml</code> is used.</p>
  </attribute>

</attributes>

<h3>User File Format</h3>

<p>The users file (by default, <code>conf/tomcat-users.xml</code> must be an
XML document, with a root element <code>&lt;tomcat-users&gt;</code>.  Nested
inside the root element will be a <code>&lt;user&gt;</code> element for each
valid user, consisting of the following attributes:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>name</strong> - Username this user must log on with.</li>
<li><strong>password</strong> - Password this user must log on with (in
    clear text if the <code>digest</code> attribute was not set on the
    <code>&lt;Realm&gt;</code> element, or digested appropriately as
    described <a href="#Digested Passwords">here</a> otherwise).</li>
<li><strong>roles</strong> - Comma-delimited list of the role names
    associated with this user.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Example</h3>

<p>The default installation of Tomcat 4 is configured with a MemoryRealm
nested inside the <code>&lt;Engine&gt;</code> element, so that it applies
to all virtual hosts and web applications.  The default contents of the
<code>conf/tomcat-users.xml</code> file is:</p>
<source>
&lt;tomcat-users&gt;
  &lt;user name="tomcat" password="tomcat" roles="tomcat" /&gt;
  &lt;user name="role1"  password="tomcat" roles="role1"  /&gt;
  &lt;user name="both"   password="tomcat" roles="tomcat,role1" /&gt;
&lt;/tomcat-users&gt;
</source>

<h3>Additional Notes</h3>

<p>MemoryRealm operates according to the following rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>When Tomcat first starts up, it loads all defined users and their
    associated information from the users file.  Changes to the data in
    this file will <strong>not</strong> be recognized until Tomcat is
    restarted.</li>
<li>When a user attempts to access a protected resource for the first time,
    Tomcat 4 will call the <code>authenticate()</code> method of this
    <code>Realm</code>.</li>
<li>Once a user has been authenticated, the user (and his or her associated
    roles) are cached within Tomcat for the duration of the user's login.
    (For FORM-based authentication, that means until the session times out or
    is invalidated; for BASIC authentication, that means until the user
    closes their browser).</li>
<li>Administering the information in the users file is the responsibility
    of your application.  Tomcat does not
    provide any built-in capabilities to maintain users and roles.</li>
<li>Debugging and exception messages logged by this <code>Realm</code> will
    be recorded by the <code>Logger</code> that is associated with our
    surrounding <code>Context</code>, <code>Host</code>, or
    <code>Engine</code>.  By default, the corresponding Logger will create a
    log file in the <code>$CATALINA_HOME/logs</code> directory.</li>
</ul>


</subsection>


</section>


<section name="Common Features">


<subsection name="Digested Passwords">

<p>For each of the standard <code>Realm</code> implementations, the user's
password (by default) is stored in clear text.  In many environments, this is
undesireable because casual observers of the authentication data can collect
enough information to log on successfully, and impersonate other users.
To avoid this problem, the standard implementations support the concept of
<em>digesting</em> user passwords.  This causes the stored version of the
passwords to be encoded (in a form that is not easily reversible), but that
the <code>Realm</code> implementation can still utilize for authentication.</p>

<p>Digested passwords are selected by specifying the <code>digest</code>
attribute on your <code>&lt;Realm&gt;</code> element.  The value for this
attribute must be one of the digest algorithms supported by the
<code>java.security.MessageDigest</code> class (SHA, MD2, or MD5).  When you
select this option, the contents of the password that is stored in the
<code>Realm</code> must be the cleartext version of the password, as digested
by the specified algorithm.</p>

<p>When the <code>authenticate()</code> method of the Realm is called, the
(cleartext) password specified by the user is itself digested by the same
algorithm, and the result is compared with the value returned by the
<code>Realm</code>.  An equal match implies that the cleartext version of the
original password is the same as the one presented by the user, so that this
user should be authorized.</p>

<p>To calculate the digested value of a cleartext password, two convenience
techniques are supported:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you are writing an application that needs to calculate digested
    passowrds dynamically, call the static <code>Digest()</code> method of the
    <code>org.apache.catalina.realm.RealmBase</code> class, passing the
    cleartext password and the digest algorithm name as arguments.  This
    method will return the digested password.</li>
<li>If you want to execute a command line utility to calculate the digested
    password, simply execute
<source>
java org.apache.catalina.realm.RealmBase \
    -a {algorithm} {cleartext-password}
</source>
    and the digested version of this cleartext password will be returned to
    standard output.</li>
</ul>

<p>To use either of the above techniques, the
<code>$CATALINA_HOME/server/lib/catalina.jar</code> file will need to be
on your class path to make the <code>RealmBase</code> class available.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection name="Example Application">

<p>The example application shipped with Tomcat 4 includes an area that is
protected by a security constraint, utilizing form-based login.  To access it,
point your browser at
<a href="http://localhost:8080/examples/jsp/security/protected/">http://localhost:8080/examples/jsp/security/protected/</a>
and log on with one of the usernames and passwords described for the default
<a href="#MemoryRealm">MemoryRealm</a>.</p>

</subsection>


<subsection name="Manager Application">

<p>If you wish to use the <a href="manager-howto.html">Manager Application</a>
to deploy and undeploy applications in a running Tomcat 4 installation, you
MUST add the "manager" role to at least one username in your selected Realm
implementation.  This is because the manager web application itself uses a
security constraint that requires role "manager" to access ANY request URI
within that application.</p>

<p>For security reasons, no username in the default Realm (i.e. using
<code>conf/tomcat-users.xml</code> is assigned the "manager" role.  Therfore,
no one will be able to utilize the features of this application until the
Tomcat administrator specifically assigns this role to one or more users.</p>

</subsection>


</section>


</body>

</document>
