<?xml version="1.0"?>

<page>

 <title>The Java Apache Project News</title>
 <author>Stefano Mazzocchi</author>
 <version>$Id: java_apache_org.xml,v 1.1 2002/01/03 12:31:41 giacomo Exp $</version>
  
 <newscolumn>
  <news>
   <title>Avalon 3.0 alpha released!</title>
   <link>http://java.apache.org/framework</link>
   <date>11 Oct 2000</date>
   <content>
     Avalon 3.0. This is the latest release of the Apache Server Framework. It includes
     security pattern enforcement, and improved deployment and enhanced classloading.
     Documentation has been completely renewed. 
   </content>
  </news>
  <news>
   <title>Java Apache Mail Enterprise Server (JAMES) 1.1 Released!</title>
   <link>http://java.apache.org/james</link>
   <date>27 Jul 2000</date>
   <content>
     JAMES 1.1 is the second release of a 100% pure Java Mail Server which implements our
     Mailet (similar to Servlet) technology to provide a powerful mail based application
     server. It is based on the Avalon server framework.  
   </content>
  </news>
  <news>
   <title>Apache JServ 1.1.2 Released!</title>
   <link>http://java.apache.org/jserv</link>
   <date>17 Jun 2000</date>
   <content>
     Apache JServ 1.1.2 has been released. This version fixes some minor bugs. Please see
     the change log for details.
   </content>
  </news>
  <news>
   <title>Apache Jetspeed 1.2b1 Released!</title>
   <link>http://java.apache.org/jetspeed</link>
   <date>15 Jun 2000</date>
   <content>
     Apache Jetspeed 1.2b1 has been released. This version provides an implementation of
     iCalendar (RFC 2445), Portal Structure Markup Language (PSML) and numerous
     performance improvements.  
   </content>
  </news>
 </newscolumn>
 
 <statuscolumn>
 
  <project>
   <title>Apache JServ</title>
   <link>http://java.apache.org/jserv</link>
   
   <release>
    <version>1.1.2</version>
    <status type="available">Released</status>
    <comment>
      This new generation comes with: major performance improvements,  improved
      installation and documentation, tons of bug fixes, and much more. 
    </comment>
   </release>
  </project>
 
  <project>
   <title>Apache Avalon Framework</title>
   <link>http://java.apache.org/framework</link>
   
   <release>
    <version>3.0a3</version>
    <status type="available">Released</status>
    <comment>
      The Avalon project is an effort to create, design, develop and maintain a
      common framework for server applications written using the Java language. This
      framework will not be a standalone product, but will allow existing and yet to
      be created server applications to fit into a common platform and to share code,
      design and human resources. 
    </comment>
   </release>
  </project>
 
  <project>
   <title>Apache JMeter</title>
   <link>http://java.apache.org/jmeter</link>
   
   <release>
    <version>1.4</version>
    <status type="available">Released</status>
    <comment>
      The 100% pure, swing enabled, Java URL profiler/analyzer to test your server
      performance, your servlet performance, to stress your servlets with heavy
      multi-threading concurrent requests and much more...
    </comment>
   </release>
  </project>  
 </statuscolumn>
 
 <legal>
   Sun, Sun Microsystems, Solaris, Java, JavaSoft, are trademarks or registered
   trademarks of Sun Microsystems, Inc. UNIX is a registered trademark in the
   United States and other countries, exclusively licensed through X/Open Company,
   Ltd. Windows, WinNT and Win32 are registered trademark of Microsoft Corp. All other
   product names mentioned herein and throughout the entire web site are trademarks
   of their respective owners.
 </legal>
 
</page>
