<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.0//EN" "../../dtd/document-v10.dtd">

<document>
<header>
<title>SQL Transformer</title>
		<version>0.9</version>
<authors>
  <person name="Sven Beauprez" email="Sven.Beauprez@the-ecorp.com"/>
  <person name="Davanum Srinivas" email="dims@yahoo.com"/>
</authors>
</header>
<body>


<s1 title="Introduction">
<p>
The purpose of the SQLTransformer is to query a database and translate the 
result to XML. To retrieve the information from the database, you are not 
restricted to use simple SQL statements (eg select, insert, update), it is also 
possible to use stored procedures. In combination with other transformers (eg 
FilterTransformer), this one can be very powerful.
</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Name : sql</li>
				<li>Class: org.apache.cocoon.transformation.SQLTransformer</li>
				<li>Cacheable: no.</li>
			</ul>
</s1>

<s1 title="Basic functionality">
<p>
To be able to query a database, we need XML that describes exactly what we want 
to do. The general structure of this input XML is as follows:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <page xmlns:sql="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
        <execute-query xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0"> 
          <query>
          <!-- here comes the SQL statement or stored procedure -->
          </query>
        </execute-query>
      </page>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
Nothing prevents you from putting other XML around the page element. If you do, 
it will stay untouched. The format of the SQL statement or the stored procedure 
is exactly the same as if you would call it directly from java with a prepared 
statement or a callable statement.
</p>
<p>
The query element has the following optional attributes:
</p>
<ol>
<li>
name:
Naming a query implicates naming the corresponding rowset (see below).
When you have a sequence of queries you want to execute, it can be handy give 
them a name. To process the retrieved data of a certain query, you can use 
another transformer to check the name of the rowset and to execute the necessary 
business logic on it.
<br/>
usage: &lt;query name="myName"&gt;
</li>
<li>
isstoredprocedure:
When you want to use stored procedures, you have to explicitly add this 
attribute to the query element. By default, the transformer assumes that you 
want to execute a SQL statement.
<br/>
usage: &lt;query isstoredprocedure="true"&gt;

</li>
</ol>
<p>
Here is an example of how the input XML might look like:
</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <page xmlns:sql="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">

       <title>Hello</title>
       <content>
        <para>This is my first Cocoon page filled with sql data!</para>

        <execute-query xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0"> 
         <query name="department">
              select id,name from department_table 
         </query>
        </execute-query>
       </content>
      </page>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
You can use the file generator to retrieve the XML from the filesystem.
To invoke the SQLTransformer you have to add following to the sitemap:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <map:transform type="sql">
        <map:parameter name="use-connection" value="personnel"/>
        <map:parameter name="show-nr-of-rows" value="true"/> 
      </map:transform>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
The "use-connection" parameter defines which connection, defined under the 
datasources element in cocoon.xconf, the SQLTransformer has to use to retrieve 
the data.
</p>
<p>
The 'show-nr-of-rows' instructs the transformer to count the number of rows in 
the resultset explicitly and to set the result as attribute to the rowset 
element. This attribute is only useful in combination with an sql statement, 
not with stored procedures. If a stored procedure returns a resultset and you 
want to know how many rows it contains, you have to count the  number of rows in 
another transformer or your stored procedure has to return it also (last 
solution is the best one)
</p>
<p>
The output XML will look as follows:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <page xmlns:sql="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
       <title>Hello</title>
       <content>
        <para>This is my first Cocoon page filled with sql data!</para>
        <rowset nrofrows="2" name="department" 
      xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
          <row>
            <id>1</id>
            <name>Programmers</name>
          </row>
          <row>
            <id>2</id>
            <name>Loungers</name>
          </row>
        </rowset>
       </content>
      </page>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
If you use this in combination with the "simple-sql2html" XSL stylesheet, 
</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <map:transform src="stylesheets/simple-sql2html.xsl"/>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
you will get a more visually attractive page.
</p>
<p>
See below for a more in depth example with stored procedures.
</p>
<p>
By now you should be able to use the SQLTransformer, but there are some more 
options you might find useful...
</p>

</s1>

<s1 title="Advanced functionality">
<s2 title="Substitution">
<p>
Sometimes you need more information before you can execute a query, eg. the name 
of the user that is currently logged on your site. This information is only 
available at runtime and hence can only be substituted in the query when 
available.
</p>
<p>
To pass this information to the SQL statement, the input XML has to look like 
this:
</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <page xmlns:sql="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
        <execute-query xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0"> 
          <query>
           select id,name from employee_table where name = '<substitute-value 
      sql:name="username"/>'
          </query>
        </execute-query>
      </page>
     ]]>
    </source>
<p>
The substitution is done by the SQLTransformer before it executes the query 
(before it calls the method prepareStatement!). For this, the transformer has to 
be given the necessary values via the sitemap (as parameter):
</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <map:transform type="sql">
        <map:parameter name="use-connection" value="personnel"/>
        <map:parameter name="show-nr-of-rows" value="true"/> 
        <map:parameter name="username" value="Stefano Mazzocchi"/>
      </map:transform>
     ]]>
    </source>
<p>
Whenever the transformer encounters a 'substitute-value' element for which the 
attribute 'name' contains the value 'username', it will replace this element 
with the value 'Stefano Mazzocchi' (without the single quotes!).
</p>
<p>
The output XML will be as follow:
</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <page xmlns:sql="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
        <rowset nrofrows="1" xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
          <row>
            <id>2</id>
            <name>Stefano Mazzocchi</name>
          </row>
        </rowset>
      </page>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
It is also possible to use substitution in combination with stored procedures.
</p>
</s2>

<s2 title="Ancestors">
<p>
This functionality is best described by a simple example.
</p>
<p>
Take following input XML:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <page xmlns:sql="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
        <execute-query xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0"> 
         <query name="department" >
              select id,name from department_table
         </query>
         <execute-query>
          <query name="employee">
           select id,name from employee_table where department_id = 
<ancestor-value 
      sql:name="id" sql:level="1"/>
          </query>
         </execute-query>
        </execute-query>
      </page>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
The first query will retrieve all id's and name's from the department_table 
table. For each id that comes from the department_table, the second query, in 
which the 'ancestor-value' element will be replaced by the id, will be executed.
The above example will be transformed to the following XML:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <page xmlns:sql="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
        <rowset nrofrows="2" name="department" 
      xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
          <row>
            <id>1</id>
            <name>Programmers</name>
            <rowset nrofrows="2" name="employee">
              <row>
                <id>1</id>
                <name>Donald Ball</name>
              </row>
              <row>
                <id>2</id>
                <name>Stefano Mazzocchi</name>
              </row>
            </rowset>
          </row>
          <row>
            <id>2</id>
            <name>Loungers</name>
            <rowset nrofrows="1" name="employee">
              <row>
                <id>3</id>
                <name>Pierpaolo Fumagalli</name>
              </row>
            </rowset>
          </row>
        </rowset>
      </page>
     ]]>
    </source>

</s2>

<s2 title="in- and out-parameters">

<p>
Stored procedures can return data as a parameter. To make use of this 
functionality in java, you have to register these parameters as 'out 
parameters'. Since this information is application specific, the SQLTransformer 
uses reflection to retrieve the data in the right format. For this, an extra 
element is needed in the input XML:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <out-parameter sql:nr="1" sql:name="code" 
sql:type="java.sql.Types.INTEGER"/>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
where:
</p>
<ol>
<li>
nr: 
The targeted parameter number that will return data of a certain type.
</li>
<li>
type: 
The type of data that will be returned (defined in java.sql.Types or in database 
specific drivers, eg oracle.jdbc.driver.OracleTypes). Once the stored procedure 
returns data in the parameters, the stored procedure tries to process them. If 
the returned parameter is an instance of ResultSet, it will be translated to XML 
as we saw before. In all the other situations, the SQLTransformer will convert 
the parameter to a string.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
This is an example of how to call an oracle stored procedure and process it with 
the SQLTransformer:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <page xmlns:sql="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
        <execute-query xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0"> 
          <query isstoredprocedure="true" name="namesearch">
              begin QUICK_SEARCH.FIND_NAME('<substitute-value 
      sql:name="username"/>',?,?,?); end;
          </query>
          <out-parameter sql:nr="1" sql:name="code" 
      sql:type="java.sql.Types.INTEGER"/>
          <out-parameter sql:nr="2" sql:name="nrofrows" 
      sql:type="java.sql.Types.INTEGER"/>
          <out-parameter sql:nr="3" sql:name="resultset" 
      sql:type="oracle.jdbc.driver.OracleTypes.CURSOR"/>
        </execute-query>
      </page>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
The SQLTransformer will create 3 elements, respectively 'code', 'nrofrows' and 
'resultset' under the element 'namesearch'. Since the type 
oracle.jdbc.driver.OracleTypes.CURSOR' corresponds to a ResultSet, a 'rowset' 
element will be created, containing all the data of the resultset.
It is also possible to use an 'in-parameter' element, eg. &lt;in-parameter 
sql:nr="1" sql:value="1"/&gt;. 
This functionality is only provided to be complete, because it is available in 
java itself. You can also use the 'in-parameter' in combination with a SQL 
statement.
Used in combination with an out-parameter, a ?-parameter can be an in-parameter 
and an out-parameter at the same time.
</p>

</s2>
</s1>
<s1 title="Combined with other transformers">
<s2 title="Filtertransformer">
<p>
When you query a database and it returns too many rows too process at once, you 
might want to take a block of elements, process this block and ignore the rest 
for now. You can best compare it to a search on Google: they only return 10 
results in one time, for more results you have to click on another block (page). 
It wouldn't be wise to process more than 10 elements in the pipeline if you only 
need to display 10 elements.
</p>
<p>
Assume that a query returns 56 row elements (by using the SQLTransformer) and 
that you only want to display the first 10 elements:
</p>
<p>
Output XML from the SQLTransformer:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <rowset nrofrows="56" name="test" 
xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
        <row>
          <!-- db record -->
        </row>
        <row>
          <!-- db record -->
        </row>
        <row>
          <!-- db record -->
        </row>

        ...

        <row>
          <!-- db record -->
        </row>
      </rowset>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
By adding following lines to the sitemap, just under the SQLTransformer, you 
restrict the results to 10 elements in the first block:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <map:transform type="filter">
        <map:parameter name="element-name" value="row"/>
        <map:parameter name="count" value="10"/>
        <map:parameter name="blocknr" value="1"/>
      </map:transform>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
output XML:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <rowset nrofrows="56" name="test" 
xmlns="http://apache.org/cocoon/SQL/2.0">
        <block id="1">
          <row>
            <!-- db record -->
          </row>

          <!-- total of 10 rows -->

          <row>
            <!-- db record -->
          </row>
        </block>
        <block id="2"/>
        <block id="3"/>
        <block id="4"/>
        <block id="5"/>
        <block id="6"/>
      </rowset>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
To make it more dynamically, put something like {reqCount} and {reqBlock} in the 
values for count and blocknr respectively. These can be parameters from the 
request and they can be passed to the sitemap with an action.
</p>
<p>
The FilterTransformer is a standalone component, you don't need to use it in 
combination with the SQLTransformer.
</p>

</s2>
<s2 title="WriteDOMSessionTransformer">

<p>
If you only use the FilterTransformer in combination with the SQLTransformer, 
you have to query the database each time the user wants to see another part of 
the result. You can better store the result in the session after the first 
request and retrieve the result from the session for the subsequent requests. 
This can be done by using a selector, which checks if the data is available in 
the session or not.
</p>
<p>
WriteDOMSessionTransformer can build a DOM starting from a given element (which 
will be the root of the DOM tree) and store it in the session. If you want to 
store the result of a query, you have to add following to the sitemap:
</p>
    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <map:transform type="writeDOMsession">
        <map:parameter name="dom-name" value="DBresult"/>
        <map:parameter name="dom-root-element" value="rowset"/>
      </map:transform>
     ]]>
    </source>
<p>
The transformer will build a DOM tree with rowset as root element and will store 
it in the session with the name "DBresult".
</p>
<p>
Note: most of the times, it is not smart to keep the output XML of the 
SQLTransformer in the session. Check if it is better to do the necessary 
transformations first, so that you get a smaller DOM, and then put the result in 
the session. You probably will be able to use the FilterTransformer on the 
transformed XML also.
</p>
<p>
The WriteDOMSessionTransformer is a standalone component, you don't need to use 
it in combination with the SQLTransformer.
</p>
</s2>

<s2 title="ReadDOMSessionTransformer">

<p>
Simply transforms a DOM to SAX-events, which can be used further on in the 
pipeline. Once you stored the result of a query in the session with the 
WriteDOMSessionTransformer, you can read it again with the 
ReadDOMSessionTransformer:
</p>

    <source>
     <![CDATA[
      <map:transform type="readDOMsession">
        <map:parameter name="dom-name" value="DBresult"/>
        <map:parameter name="trigger-element" value="users"/>
        <map:parameter name="position" value="after"/>
      </map:transform>
     ]]>
    </source>

<p>
In this example, the SAX-events that came from the DOM tree that is stored in 
the session with name DBresult will be added after the users element. This means 
as soon that the transformer encounters the end-element 'users', it will start 
to generate SAX-events from the DOM tree. There are three possible positions, 
'before','in' and 'after':
</p>
<ol>
<li>'before' means that when the transformer encounters the 'users' element, it 
will FIRST translate the DOM tree to SAX-events and THEN it will continue to 
forward the other SAX-events (starting with 'users').
</li>
<li>'in' means that the transformer will forward the startElement event for 
'users' and that it IMMEDIATELY starts to generate SAX-events from the DOM-tree. 
After that, it will continue to forward the child elements of users and then all 
the other elements.
</li>
<li>'after' means that the transformer starts to generate SAX-events from the 
DOM-tree just after it has forwarded the end-element 'users'.
</li>
</ol>
<p>
The ReadDOMSessionTransformer is a standalone component, you don't need to use 
it in combination with the WriteDOMSessionTransformer.
</p>
</s2>

<p>
That's it,
</p>
<p>
Sven Beauprez
</p>


</s1>

</body>
</document>

